<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="abraham, ibrahim" generated="2025-04-13T23:17:00.093Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story generated from search: "abraham, ibrahim"</title>
    <verses_count>230</verses_count>
  </metadata>

  <verses>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="69" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.861015</score>
      <text>And verily, there came Our Messengers to Ibrahim (Abraham) with glad tidings. They said: Salam (greetings or peace!) He answered, Salam (greetings or peace!) and he hastened to entertain them with a roasted calf.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="75" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>25.140865</score>
      <text>Verily, Ibrahim (Abraham) was, without doubt, forbearing, used to invoke Allah with humility, and was repentant (to Allah all the time, again and again).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="76" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>24.058025</score>
      <text>&quot;O Ibrahim (Abraham)! Forsake this. Indeed, the Commandment of your Lord has gone forth. Verily, there will come a torment for them which cannot be turned back.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="12" verse="38" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>17.70372</score>
      <text>&quot;And I have followed the religion of my fathers, - Ibrahim (Abraham), Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya&apos;qub (Jacob)], and never could we attribute any partners whatsoever to Allah. This is from the Grace of Allah to us and to mankind, but most men thank not (i.e. they neither believe in Allah, nor worship Him).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="12" verse="6" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>18.085875</score>
      <text>&quot;Thus will your Lord choose you and teach you the interpretation of dreams (and other things) and perfect His Favour on you and on the offspring of Ya&apos;qub (Jacob), as He perfected it on your fathers, Ibrahim (Abraham) and Ishaque (Isaac) aforetime! Verily, your Lord is All-Knowing, All-Wise.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="35" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>23.717512</score>
      <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) said: &quot;O my Lord! Make this city (Makkah) one of peace and security, and keep me and my sons away from worshipping idols.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="16" verse="120" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>17.70372</score>
      <text>Verily, Ibrahim (Abraham) was an Ummah (a leader having all the good righteous qualities), or a nation, obedient to Allah, Hanifa (i.e. to worship none but Allah), and he was not one of those who were Al-Mushrikun (polytheists, idolaters, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allah, and those who joined partners with Allah).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="16" verse="123" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.861015</score>
      <text>Then, We have inspired you (O Muhammad SAW saying): &quot;Follow the religion of Ibrahim (Abraham) Hanifa (Islamic Monotheism - to worship none but Allah) and he was not of the Mushrikun (polytheists, idolaters, disbelievers, etc.).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="41" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>27.627909</score>
      <text>And mention in the Book (the Quran) Ibrahim (Abraham). Verily! He was a man of truth, a Prophet.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="46" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>22.44669</score>
      <text>He (the father) said: &quot;Do you reject my gods, O Ibrahim (Abraham)? If you stop not (this), I will indeed stone you. So get away from me safely before I punish you.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="60" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>29.065552</score>
      <text>They said: &quot;We heard a young man talking (against) them who is called Ibrahim (Abraham).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="62" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>28.569994</score>
      <text>They said: &quot;Are you the one who has done this to our gods, O Ibrahim (Abraham)?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="69" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>30.110086</score>
      <text>We (Allah) said: &quot;O fire! Be you coolness and safety for Ibrahim (Abraham)!&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="22" verse="26" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>14.615482</score>
      <text>And (remember) when We showed Ibrahim (Abraham) the site of the (Sacred) House (the Ka&apos;bah at Makkah) (saying): &quot;Associate not anything (in worship) with Me, [La ilaha ill-Allah (none has the right to be worshipped but Allah Islamic Monotheism], and sanctify My House for those who circumambulate it, and those who stand up for prayer, and those who bow (submit themselves with humility and obedience to Allah), and make prostration (in prayer, etc.);&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="22" verse="43" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>30.661022</score>
      <text>And the people of Ibrahim (Abraham) and the people of Lout (Lot),</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="22" verse="78" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>8.977652</score>
      <text>And strive hard in Allah&apos;s Cause as you ought to strive (with sincerity and with all your efforts that His Name should be superior). He has chosen you (to convey His Message of Islamic Monotheism to mankind by inviting them to His religion, Islam), and has not laid upon you in religion any hardship, it is the religion of your father Ibrahim (Abraham) (Islamic Monotheism). It is He (Allah) Who has named you Muslims both before and in this (the Quran), that the Messenger (Muhammad SAW) may be a witness over you and you be witnesses over mankind! So perform As-Salat (Iqamat-as-Salat), give Zakat and hold fast to Allah [i.e. have confidence in Allah, and depend upon Him in all your affairs] He is your Maula (Patron, Lord, etc.), what an Excellent Maula (Patron, Lord, etc.) and what an Excellent Helper!</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="16" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>24.408457</score>
      <text>And (remember) Ibrahim (Abraham) when he said to his people: &quot;Worship Allah (Alone), and fear Him, that is better for you if you did but know.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="31" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>17.337383</score>
      <text>And when Our Messengers came to Ibrahim (Abraham) with the glad tidings they said: &quot;Verily, we are going to destroy the people of this [Lout&apos;s (Lot&apos;s)] town (i.e. the town of Sodom in Palestine) truly, its people have been Zalimun [wrong-doers, polytheists and disobedient to Allah, and have also belied their Messenger Lout (Lot)].&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="124" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>25.493298</score>
      <text>And (remember) when the Lord of Ibrahim (Abraham) [i.e., Allah] tried him with (certain) Commands, which he fulfilled. He (Allah) said (to him), &quot;Verily, I am going to make you a leader (Prophet) of mankind.&quot; [Ibrahim (Abraham)] said, &quot;And of my offspring (to make leaders).&quot; (Allah) said, &quot;My Covenant (Prophethood, etc.) includes not Zalimun (polytheists and wrong-doers).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="125" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>24.609888</score>
      <text>And (remember) when We made the House (the Ka&apos;bah at Makkah) a place of resort for mankind and a place of safety. And take you (people) the Maqam (place) of Ibrahim (Abraham) [or the stone on which Ibrahim (Abraham) stood while he was building the Ka&apos;bah] as a place of prayer (for some of your prayers, e.g. two Rak&apos;at after the Tawaf of the Ka&apos;bah at Makkah), and We commanded Ibrahim (Abraham) and Isma&apos;il (Ishmael) that they should purify My House (the Ka&apos;bah at Makkah) for those who are circumambulating it, or staying (I&apos;tikaf), or bowing or prostrating themselves (there, in prayer).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="126" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>15.711786</score>
      <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) said, &quot;My Lord, make this city (Makkah) a place of security and provide its people with fruits, such of them as believe in Allah and the Last Day.&quot; He (Allah) answered: &quot;As for him who disbelieves, I shall leave him in contentment for a while, then I shall compel him to the torment of the Fire, and worst indeed is that destination!&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="127" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>20.776806</score>
      <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) and (his son) Isma&apos;il (Ishmael) were raising the foundations of the House (the Ka&apos;bah at Makkah), (saying), &quot;Our Lord! Accept (this service) from us. Verily! You are the All-Hearer, the All-Knower.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="133" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>17.70372</score>
      <text>Or were you witnesses when death approached Ya&apos;qub (Jacob)? When he said unto his sons, &quot;What will you worship after me?&quot; They said, &quot;We shall worship your Ilah (God - Allah), the Ilah (God) of your fathers, Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma&apos;il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), One Ilah (God), and to Him we submit (in Islam).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="135" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>16.9859</score>
      <text>And they say, &quot;Be Jews or Christians, then you will be guided.&quot; Say (to them, O Muhammad Peace be upon him), &quot;Nay, (We follow) only the religion of Ibrahim (Abraham), Hanifa [Islamic Monotheism, i.e. to worship none but Allah (Alone)], and he was not of Al-Mushrikun (those who worshipped others along with Allah - see V. 2:105).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="136" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>13.662188</score>
      <text>Say (O Muslims), &quot;We believe in Allah and that which has been sent down to us and that which has been sent down to Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma&apos;il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya&apos;qub (Jacob), and to Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya&apos;qub (Jacob)], and that which has been given to Musa (Moses) and &apos;Iesa (Jesus), and that which has been given to the Prophets from their Lord. We make no distinction between any of them, and to Him we have submitted (in Islam).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="140" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>13.230701</score>
      <text>Or say you that Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma&apos;il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya&apos;qub (Jacob) and Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya&apos;qub (Jacob)] were Jews or Christians? Say, &quot;Do you know better or does Allah (knows better  that they all were Muslims)? And who is more unjust than he who conceals the testimony [i.e. to believe in Prophet Muhammad Peace be upon him when he comes, written in their Books. (See Verse 7:157)] he has from Allah? And Allah is not unaware of what you do.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="258" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>26.145834</score>
      <text>Have you not looked at him who disputed with Ibrahim (Abraham) about his Lord (Allah), because Allah had given him the kingdom? When Ibrahim (Abraham) said (to him): &quot;My Lord (Allah) is He Who gives life and causes death.&quot; He said, &quot;I give life and cause death.&quot; Ibrahim (Abraham) said, &quot;Verily! Allah causes the sun to rise from the east; then cause it you to rise from the west.&quot; So the disbeliever was utterly defeated. And Allah guides not the people, who are Zalimun (wrong-doers, etc.).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="260" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.016922</score>
      <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) said, &quot;My Lord! Show me how You give life to the dead.&quot; He (Allah) said: &quot;Do you not believe?&quot; He [Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;Yes (I believe), but to be stronger in Faith.&quot; He said: &quot;Take four birds, then cause them to incline towards you (then slaughter them, cut them into pieces), and then put a portion of them on every hill, and call them, they will come to you in haste. And know that Allah is All-Mighty, All-Wise.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="33" verse="7" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>20.776806</score>
      <text>And (remember) when We took from the Prophets their covenant, and from you (O Muhammad SAW), and from Nuh (Noah), Ibrahim (Abraham), Musa (Moses), and &apos;Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary). We took from them a strong covenant.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="104" author="Daryabadi">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.daryabadi</book_id>
      <score>18.644016</score>
      <text>We cried Unto him: O Ibrahim</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="109" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>34.442253</score>
      <text>Salamun (peace) be upon Ibrahim (Abraham)!&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="83" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>29.065552</score>
      <text>And, verily, among those who followed his [Nuh&apos;s (Noah)] way (Islamic Monotheism) was Ibrahim (Abraham).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="45" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>25.523804</score>
      <text>And remember Our slaves, Ibrahim (Abraham), Ishaque (Isaac), and Ya&apos;qub (Jacob), (all) owners of strength (in worshipping Us) and (also) of religious understanding.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="65" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.861015</score>
      <text>O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Why do you dispute about Ibrahim (Abraham), while the Taurat (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel) were not revealed till after him? Have you then no sense?</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="67" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.579494</score>
      <text>Ibrahim (Abraham) was neither a Jew nor a Christian, but he was a true Muslim Hanifa (Islamic Monotheism - to worship none but Allah Alone) and he was not of Al-Mushrikun (See V. 2:105).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="68" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>20.776806</score>
      <text>Verily, among mankind who have the best claim to Ibrahim (Abraham) are those who followed him, and this Prophet (Muhammad SAW) and those who have believed (Muslims). And Allah is the Wali (Protector and Helper) of the believers.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="84" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>14.615482</score>
      <text>Say (O Muhammad SAW): &quot;We believe in Allah and in what has been sent down to us, and what was sent down to Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma&apos;il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya&apos;qub (Jacob) and Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya&apos;qub (Jacob)] and what was given to Musa (Moses), &apos;Iesa (Jesus) and the Prophets from their Lord. We make no distinction between one another among them and to Him (Allah) we have submitted (in Islam).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="95" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.305126</score>
      <text>Say (O Muhammad SAW): &quot;Allah has spoken the truth; follow the religion of Ibrahim (Abraham) Hanifa (Islamic Monotheism, i.e. he used to worship Allah Alone), and he was not of Al-Mushrikun.&quot; (See V. 2:105)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="42" verse="13" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>12.08562</score>
      <text>He (Allah) has ordained for you the same religion (Islam) which He ordained for Nuh (Noah), and that which We have inspired in you (O Muhammad SAW), and that which We ordained for Ibrahim (Abraham), Musa (Moses) and &apos;Iesa (Jesus) saying you should establish religion (i.e. to do what it orders you to do practically), and make no divisions in it (religion) (i.e. various sects in religion). Intolerable for the Mushrikun, is that to which you (O Muhammad SAW) call them. Allah chooses for Himself whom He wills, and guides unto Himself who turns to Him in repentance and in obedience.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="43" verse="26" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>26.745966</score>
      <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) said to his father and his people: &quot;Verily, I am innocent of what you worship,</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="125" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>24.74052</score>
      <text>And who can be better in religion than one who submits his face (himself) to Allah (i.e. follows Allah&apos;s Religion of Islamic Monotheism); and he is a Muhsin (a good-doer - see V. 2:112). And follows the religion of Ibrahim (Abraham) Hanifa (Islamic Monotheism - to worship none but Allah Alone). And Allah did take Ibrahim (Abraham) as a Khalil (an intimate friend).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="163" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>16.9859</score>
      <text>Verily, We have inspired you (O Muhammad SAW) as We inspired Nuh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; We (also) inspired Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma&apos;il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya&apos;qub (Jacob), and Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya&apos;qub (Jacob)], &apos;Iesa (Jesus), Ayub (Job), Yunus (Jonah), Harun (Aaron), and Sulaiman (Solomon), and to Dawud (David) We gave the Zabur (Psalms).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="53" verse="37" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>27.627909</score>
      <text>And of Ibrahim (Abraham) who fulfilled (or conveyed) all that (what Allah ordered him to do or convey),</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="57" verse="26" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.305126</score>
      <text>And indeed, We sent Nuh (Noah) and Ibrahim (Abraham), and placed in their offspring Prophethood and Scripture, and among them there is he who is guided, but many of them are Fasiqun (rebellious, disobedient to Allah).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="4" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>17.877762</score>
      <text>Indeed there has been an excellent example for you in Ibrahim (Abraham) and those with him, when they said to their people: &quot;Verily, we are free from you and whatever you worship besides Allah, we have rejected you, and there has started between us and you, hostility and hatred for ever, until you believe in Allah Alone,&quot; except the saying of Ibrahim (Abraham) to his father: &quot;Verily, I will ask for forgiveness (from Allah) for you, but I have no power to do anything for you before Allah.&quot; Our Lord! In You (Alone) we put our trust, and to You (Alone) we turn in repentance, and to You (Alone) is (our) final Return,</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="161" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>17.70372</score>
      <text>Say (O Muhammad SAW): &quot;Truly, my Lord has guided me to a Straight Path, a right religion, the religion of Ibrahim (Abraham), Hanifa [i.e. the true Islamic Monotheism - to believe in One God (Allah i.e. to worship none but Allah, Alone)] and he was not of Al-Mushrikun (see V. 2:105).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="74" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>24.058025</score>
      <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) said to his father Azar: &quot;Do you take idols as aliha (gods)? Verily, I see you and your people in manifest error.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="75" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>24.769249</score>
      <text>Thus did we show Ibrahim (Abraham) the kingdom of the heavens and the earth that he be one of those who have Faith with certainty.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="83" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>23.717512</score>
      <text>And that was Our Proof which We gave Ibrahim (Abraham) against his people. We raise whom We will in degrees. Certainly your Lord is All-Wise, All-Knowing.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="87" verse="19" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>33.08231</score>
      <text>The Scriptures of Ibrahim (Abraham) and Musa (Moses).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="9" verse="114" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>27.812544</score>
      <text>And [Ibrahim&apos;s (Abraham)] invoking (of Allah) for his father&apos;s forgiveness was only because of a promise he [Ibrahim (Abraham)] had made to him (his father). But when it became clear to him [Ibrahim (Abraham)] that he (his father) is an enemy to Allah, he dissociated himself from him. Verily Ibrahim (Abraham) was Al-Awwah (has fifteen different meanings but the correct one seems to be that he used to invoke Allah with humility, glorify Him and remember Him much), and was forbearing. (Tafsir Al-Qurtubi).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="58" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>15.711786</score>
      <text>Those were they unto whom Allah bestowed His Grace from among the Prophets, of the offspring of Adam, and of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Nuh (Noah), and of the offspring of Ibrahim (Abraham) and Israel and from among those whom We guided and chose. When the Verses of the Most Beneficent (Allah) were recited unto them, they fell down prostrating and weeping.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="51" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>23.386505</score>
      <text>And indeed We bestowed aforetime on Ibrahim (Abraham) his (portion of) guidance, and We were Well-Acquainted with him (as to his Belief in the Oneness of Allah, etc.).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="130" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.305126</score>
      <text>And who turns away from the religion of Ibrahim (Abraham) (i.e. Islamic Monotheism) except him who befools himself? Truly, We chose him in this world and verily, in the Hereafter he will be among the righteous.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="132" author="Mubarakpuri">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.mubarakpuri</book_id>
      <score>21.037651</score>
      <text>And this (submission to Allah, Islam) was enjoined by Ibrahim (Abraham) upon his sons and by Ya`qub (Jacob) (saying), &quot;O my sons! Allah has chosen for you the (true) religion, then die not except as Muslims.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="33" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>25.140865</score>
      <text>Allah chose Adam, Nuh (Noah), the family of Ibrahim (Abraham) and the family of &apos;Imran above the &apos;Alamin (mankind and jinns) (of their times).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="97" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>14.122765</score>
      <text>In it are manifest signs (for example), the Maqam (place) of Ibrahim (Abraham); whosoever enters it, he attains security. And Hajj (pilgrimage to Makkah) to the House (Ka&apos;bah) is a duty that mankind owes to Allah, those who can afford the expenses (for one&apos;s conveyance, provision and residence); and whoever disbelieves [i.e. denies Hajj (pilgrimage to Makkah), then he is a disbeliever of Allah], then Allah stands not in need of any of the &apos;Alamin (mankind and jinns).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="9" verse="70" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>16.32402</score>
      <text>Has not the story reached them of those before them? - The people of Nuh (Noah), &apos;Ad, and Thamud, the people of Ibrahim (Abraham), the dwellers of Madyan (Midian) and the cities overthrown [i.e. the people to whom Lout (Lot) preached], to them came their Messengers with clear proofs. So it was not Allah Who wronged them, but they used to wrong themselves.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="69" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>32.441833</score>
      <text>And recite to them the story of Ibrahim (Abraham).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="54" author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedraza</book_id>
      <score>20.776806</score>
      <text>Or do they envy people due to what Allah has given them from His grace? In that case, We bestowed the Book and the wisdom upon the family of Ibrahim (Abraham), and We gave them a great kingdom.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="74" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.861015</score>
      <text>Then when the fear had gone away from (the mind of) Ibrahim (Abraham), and the glad tidings had reached him, he began to plead with Us (Our Messengers) for the people of Lout (Lot).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="51" verse="31" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>30.661022</score>
      <text>[Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;Then for what purpose you have come, O Messengers?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="51" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>31.232498</score>
      <text>And tell them about the guests (the angels) of Ibrahim (Abraham).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="47" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>25.140865</score>
      <text>Ibrahim (Abraham) said: &quot;Peace be on you! I will ask Forgiveness of my Lord for you. Verily! He is unto me, Ever Most Gracious.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="51" verse="24" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>26.745966</score>
      <text>Has the story reached you, of the honoured guests [three angels; Jibrael (Gabriel) along with another two] of Ibrahim (Abraham)?</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="25" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>17.337383</score>
      <text>And [Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;You have taken (for worship) idols instead of Allah, and the love between you is only in the life of this world, but on the Day of Resurrection, you shall disown each other, and curse each other, and your abode will be the Fire, and you shall have no helper.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="26" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>25.877285</score>
      <text>So Lout (Lot) believed in him [Ibrahim&apos;s (Abraham) Message of Islamic Monotheism]. He [Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;I will emigrate for the sake of my Lord. Verily, He is the All-Mighty, the All-Wise.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="32" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>17.337383</score>
      <text>Ibrahim (Abraham) said: &quot;But there is Lout (Lot) in it.&quot; They said:&quot;We know better who is there, we will verily save him [Lout (Lot)] and his family, except his wife, she will be of those who remain behind (i.e. she will be destroyed along with those who will be destroyed from her folk).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="66" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>27.627909</score>
      <text>[Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;Do you then worship besides Allah, things that can neither profit you, nor harm you?</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="52" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>27.627909</score>
      <text>When they entered unto him, and said: Salaman (peace)! [Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;Indeed! We are afraid of you.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="54" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>25.140865</score>
      <text>[Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;Do you give me glad tidings (of a son) when old age has overtaken me? Of what then is your news?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="27" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>24.03092</score>
      <text>And We bestowed on him [Ibrahim (Abraham)], Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya&apos;qub (Jacob), and ordained among his offspring Prophethood and the Book [i.e. the Taurat (Torah) (to Musa - Moses), the Injeel (Gospel) (to &apos;Iesa - Jesus), the Quran (to Muhammad SAW), all from the offspring of Ibrahim (Abraham)], and We granted him his reward in this world, and verily, in the Hereafter he is indeed among the righteous.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="103" author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedraza</book_id>
      <score>14.030052</score>
      <text>Then (remember) when they both submitted to Allah’s command, and Ibrahim lay his son facing downwards. (The knife did not hurt Ismail)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="57" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>28.569994</score>
      <text>[Ibrahim (Abraham) again] said: &quot;What then is the business on which you have come, O Messengers?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="65" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>26.325779</score>
      <text>Then they turned to themselves (their first thought and said): &quot;Indeed you [Ibrahim (Abraham)] know well that these (idols) speak not!&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="24" author="Ahmed Ali">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>10.727101</score>
      <text>The people (of Abraham) had no answer except: &quot;Kill him or burn him;&quot; but God saved him from the fire. There are lessons in this for those who believe.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="102" author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedraza</book_id>
      <score>10.231836</score>
      <text>And when he became capable of working with him, Ibrahim said, “O my son, I dreamt that I am sacrificing you – therefore now consider what is your opinion”; he said, “O my father! Do what you are commanded! Allah willing, you will soon find me patiently enduring!”</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="77" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>10.435812</score>
      <text>When Abraham saw the rising moon, he said, &quot;This is my lord.&quot; But when it faded away, he said, &quot;If my Lord does not guide me I shall certainly go astray.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="84" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>13.6690235</score>
      <text>We gave (Abraham) Isaac and Jacob. Both had received Our guidance. Noah received Our guidance before Abraham and so did his descendants: David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron. Thus is the reward for the righteous people.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="73" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>21.861015</score>
      <text>They said: &quot;Do you wonder at the Decree of Allah? The Mercy of Allah and His Blessings be on you, O the family [of Ibrahim (Abraham)]. Surely, He (Allah) is All-Praiseworthy, All-Glorious.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="56" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>28.091055</score>
      <text>[Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;And who despairs of the Mercy of his Lord except those who are astray?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="49" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>11.531805</score>
      <text>When (Abraham) rejected his people and what they worshipped instead of God, We gave him Isaac and Jacob and made both of them Prophets.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="22" verse="27" author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedraza</book_id>
      <score>11.387939</score>
      <text>“And publicly announce the pilgrimage to all people – they will come to you, on foot and on every lean she-camel, coming from every far distant journey.” (The announcement by Prophet Ibrahim reached each and every soul.)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="75" author="Wahiduddin Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.wahiduddin</book_id>
      <score>14.063833</score>
      <text>Abraham said, &quot;Have you really thought about what you have been worshipping,</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="99" author="Maududi">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>14.063833</score>
      <text>Abraham said: “I am going to my Lord; He will guide me.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="43" verse="28" author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedraza</book_id>
      <score>16.011261</score>
      <text>And Ibrahim kept this declaration among his progeny, in order that they may desist.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="76" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>10.435812</score>
      <text>When it became dark at night, he (Abraham) saw a star and said, &quot;This is my lord.&quot; But when it disappeared, he said, &quot;I do not love those who fade away&quot;.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="78" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>9.649712</score>
      <text>When he saw the rising sun, he said, &quot;This is my Lord for it is greater (than the others).&quot; But when this too faded away, (Abraham) said, &quot;My people, I disavow whatever you consider equal to God.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="90" verse="3" author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedraza</book_id>
      <score>16.298962</score>
      <text>And by oath of your forefather Ibrahim, and by you – his illustrious son!</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="12" verse="754" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>8.670072</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Ikrima:
I saw a person praying at Muqam-lbrahim (the place of Abraham by the Ka&apos;ba) and he was saying Takbir on every bowing, rising, standing and sitting. I asked Ibn &apos;Abbas (about this prayer). He admonished me saying: &quot;Isn&apos;t that the prayer of the Prophet?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="18" verse="153" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>12.645538</score>
      <text>Narrated Al-Mughira bin Shu&apos;ba:
&quot;The sun eclipsed in the life-time of Allah&apos;s Apostle on the day when (his son) Ibrahim died. So the people said that the sun had eclipsed because of the death of Ibrahim. Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;The sun and the moon do not eclipse because of the death or life (i.e. birth) of some-one. When you see the eclipse pray and invoke Allah.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="18" verse="168" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>7.911541</score>
      <text>Narrated Al-Mughira bin Shu&apos;ba :
On the day of Ibrahim&apos;s death, the sun eclipsed and the people said that the eclipse was due to the death of Ibrahim (the son of the Prophet). Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;The sun and the moon are two signs amongst the signs of Allah. They do not eclipse because of someone&apos;s death or life. So when you see them, invoke Allah and pray till the eclipse is clear.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="18" verse="170" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>5.865266</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Bakra:
In the life-time of the Allah&apos;s Apostle (p.b.u.h) the sun eclipsed and he went out dragging his clothes till he reached the Mosque. The people gathered around him and he led them and offered two Rakat. When the sun (eclipse) cleared, he said, &quot;The sun and the moon are two signs amongst the signs of Allah; they do not eclipse because of the death of someone, and so when an eclipse occurs, pray and invoke Allah till the eclipse is over.&quot; It happened that a son of the Prophet called Ibrahim died on that day and the people were talking about that (saying that the eclipse was caused by his death).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="283" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>5.3153496</score>
      <text>Narrated Nafi&apos;:
Ibn &apos;Umar never offered the Duha prayer except on two occasions:
(1) Whenever he reached Mecca; and he always used to reach Mecca in the forenoon. He would perform Tawaf round the Ka&apos;ba and then offer two Rakat at the rear of Maqam Ibrahim.
(2) Whenever he visited Quba, for he used to visit it every Saturday. When he entered the Mosque, he disliked to leave it without offering a prayer. Ibn &apos;Umar narrated that Allah&apos;s Apostle used to visit the Mosque of Quba (sometime) walking and (sometime) riding. And he (i.e. Ibn &apos;Umar) used to say, &quot;I do only what my companions used to do and I don&apos;t forbid anybody to pray at any time during the day or night except that one should not intend to pray at sunrise or sunset.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="52" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>13.567339</score>
      <text>Abraham asked his father and his people, &quot;What are these statues which you worship?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="54" author="Wahiduddin Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.wahiduddin</book_id>
      <score>14.325962</score>
      <text>Abraham said, &quot;Indeed, you and your fathers have been clearly misguided.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="56" author="Wahiduddin Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.wahiduddin</book_id>
      <score>11.888537</score>
      <text>Abraham replied, &quot;Your Lord is the Lord of the heavens and the earth, who created them, and I bear witness to that.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="57" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>12.672581</score>
      <text>Abraham said to himself, &quot;By God! I will devise a plan against their idols when they are away.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="63" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>27.179783</score>
      <text>[Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: &quot;Nay, this one, the biggest of them (idols) did it. Ask them, if they can speak!&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="70" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>13.567339</score>
      <text>They had devised an evil plan (against Abraham), but We turned it into failure.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="71" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>12.672581</score>
      <text>We took Abraham and Lot safely to the land in which We had sent blessings to the worlds.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="365" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>6.185219</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim:
Once a meal was brought to &apos;Abdur-Rahman bin &apos;Auf and he was fasting. He said, &quot;Mustab bin &apos;Umar was martyred and he was better than I and was shrouded in his Burd and when his head was covered with it, his legs became bare, and when his legs were covered his head got uncovered. Hamza was martyred and was better than I. Now the worldly wealth have been bestowed upon us (or said a similar thing). No doubt, I fear that the rewards of my deeds might have been given earlier in this world.&quot; Then he started weeping and left his food.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="390" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>13.897245</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
We went with Allah&apos;s Apostle (p.b.u.h) to the blacksmith Abu Saif, and he was the husband of the wet-nurse of Ibrahim (the son of the Prophet). Allah&apos;s Apostle took Ibrahim and kissed him and smelled him and later we entered Abu Saif&apos;s house and at that time Ibrahim was in his last breaths, and the eyes of Allah&apos;s Apostle (p.b.u.h) started shedding tears. &apos;Abdur Rahman bin &apos;Auf said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle, even you are weeping!&quot; He said, &quot;O Ibn &apos;Auf, this is mercy.&quot; Then he wept more and said, &quot;The eyes are shedding tears and the heart is grieved, and we will not say except what pleases our Lord, O Ibrahim ! Indeed we are grieved by your separation.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="464" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>14.030052</score>
      <text>Narrated Al-Bara&apos;:
When Ibrahim (the son of Prophet) expired, Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;There is a wet-nurse for him in Paradise.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="468" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>0.8553076</score>
      <text>Narrated Samura bin Jundab:
Whenever the Prophet finished the (morning) prayer, he would face us and ask, &quot;Who amongst you had a dream last night?&quot; So if anyone had seen a dream he would narrate it. The Prophet would say: &quot;Ma sha&apos;a-llah&quot; (An Arabic maxim meaning literally, &apos;What Allah wished,&apos; and it indicates a good omen.) One day, he asked us whether anyone of us had seen a dream. We replied in the negative. The Prophet said, &quot;But I had seen (a dream) last night that two men came to me, caught hold of my hands, and took me to the Sacred Land (Jerusalem). There, I saw a person sitting and another standing with an iron hook in his hand pushing it inside the mouth of the former till it reached the jaw-bone, and then tore off one side of his cheek, and then did the same with the other side; in the mean-time the first side of his cheek became normal again and then he repeated the same operation again. I said, &apos;What is this?&apos; They told me to proceed on and we went on till we came to a man Lying flat on his back, and another man standing at his head carrying a stone or a piece of rock, and crushing the head of the Lying man, with that stone. Whenever he struck him, the stone rolled away.
The man went to pick it up and by the time he returned to him, the crushed head had returned to its normal state and the man came back and struck him again (and so on). I said, &apos;Who is this?&apos; They told me to proceed on; so we proceeded on and passed by a hole like an oven; with a narrow top and wide bottom, and the fire was kindling underneath that hole. Whenever the fire-flame went up, the people were lifted up to such an extent that they about to get out of it, and whenever the fire got quieter, the people went down into it, and there were naked men and women in it. I said, &apos;Who is this?&apos; They told me to proceed on. So we proceeded on till we reached a river of blood and a man was in it, and another man was standing at its bank with stones in front of him, facing the man standing in the river. Whenever the man in the river wanted to come out, the other one threw a stone in his mouth and caused him to retreat to his original position; and so whenever he wanted to come out the other would throw a stone in his mouth, and he would retreat to his original position. I asked, &apos;What is this?&apos; They told me to proceed on and we did so till we reached a well-flourished green garden having a huge tree and near its root was sitting an old man with some children. (I saw) Another man near the tree with fire in front of him and he was kindling it up. Then they (i.e. my two companions) made me climb up the tree and made me enter a house, better than which I have ever seen. In it were some old men and young men, women and children.
Then they took me out of this house and made me climb up the tree and made me enter another house that was better and superior (to the first) containing old and young people. I said to them (i.e. my two companions), &apos;You have made me ramble all the night. Tell me all about that I have seen.&apos; They said, &apos;Yes. As for the one whose cheek you saw being torn away, he was a liar and he used to tell lies, and the people would report those lies on his authority till they spread all over the world. So, he will be punished like that till the Day of Resurrection.
The one whose head you saw being crushed is the one whom Allah had given the knowledge of Quran (i.e. knowing it by heart) but he used to sleep at night (i.e. he did not recite it then) and did not use to act upon it (i.e. upon its orders etc.) by day; and so this punishment will go on till the Day of Resurrection. And those you saw in the hole (like oven) were adulterers (those men and women who commit illegal sexual intercourse). And those you saw in the river of blood were those dealing in Riba (usury). And the old man who was sitting at the base of the tree was Abraham and the little children around him were the offspring of the people. And the one who was kindling the fire was Malik, the gate-keeper of the Hell-fire. And the first house in which you have gone was the house of the common believers, and the second house was of the martyrs. I am Gabriel and this is Michael. Raise your head.&apos; I raised my head and saw a thing like a cloud over me. They said, &apos;That is your place.&apos; I said, &apos;Let me enter my place.&apos; They said, &apos;You still have some life which you have not yet completed, and when you complete (that remaining portion of your life) you will then enter your place.&apos; &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="611" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>9.583242</score>
      <text>Narrated Said bin Jubair:
Ibn &apos;Umar used to oil his hair. I told that to Ibrahim who said, &quot;What do you think about this statement: Narrated Aswad from &apos;Aisha: As if I were now observing the glitter of the scent in the parting of the hair of the Prophet while he was Muhrim?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="653" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>9.759402</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Aisha:
(the wife of the Prophet) that Allah&apos;s Apostle said to her, &quot;Do you know that when your people (Quraish) rebuilt the Ka&apos;ba, they decreased it from its original foundation laid by Abraham?&quot; I said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Why don&apos;t you rebuild it on its original foundation laid by Abraham?&quot; He replied, &quot;Were it not for the fact that your people are close to the pre-lslamic Period of ignorance (i.e. they have recently become Muslims) I would have done so.&quot; The sub-narrator, &apos;Abdullah (bin &apos;Umar ) stated: &apos;Aisha &apos;must have heard this from Allah&apos;s Apostle for in my opinion Allah&apos;s Apostle had not placed his hand over the two corners of the Ka&apos;ba opposite Al-Hijr only because the Ka&apos;ba was not rebuilt on its original foundations laid by Abraham.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="655" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>8.120479</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Aisha:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said to me, &quot;Were your people not close to the Pre-lslamic period of ignorance, I would have demolished the Ka&apos;ba and would have rebuilt it on its original foundations laid by Abraham (for Quraish had curtailed its building), and I would have built a back door (too).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="656" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>5.2742605</score>
      <text>Narrated Yazid bin Ruman from &apos;Urwa:
&apos;Aisha said that the Prophet said to her, &quot;O Aisha! Were your nation not close to the Pre-lslamic Period of Ignorance, I would have had the Ka&apos;ba demolished and would have included in it the portion which had been left, and would have made it at a level with the ground and would have made two doors for it, one towards the east and the other towards the west, and then by doing this it would have been built on the foundations laid by Abraham.&quot; That was what urged Ibn-Az-Zubair to demolish the Ka&apos;ba. Jazz said, &quot;I saw Ibn-Az-Zubair when he demolished and rebuilt the Ka&apos;ba and included in it a portion of Al-Hijr (the unroofed portion of Ka&apos;ba which is at present in the form of a compound towards the north-west of the Ka&apos;ba). I saw the original foundations of Abraham which were of stones resembling the humps of camels.&quot; So Jarir asked Yazid, &quot;Where was the place of those stones?&quot; Jazz said, &quot;I will just now show it to you.&quot; So Jarir accompanied Yazid and entered Al-Hijr, and Jazz pointed to a place and said, &quot;Here it is.&quot; Jarir said, &quot;It appeared to me about six cubits from Al-Hijr or so.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="671" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>9.640203</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
When Allah&apos;s Apostle came to Mecca, he refused to enter the Ka&apos;ba with idols in it. He ordered (idols to be taken out). So they were taken out. The people took out the pictures of Abraham and Ishmael holding Azlams in their hands. Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;May Allah curse these people. By Allah, both Abraham and Ishmael never did the game of chance with Azlams.&quot; Then he entered the Ka&apos;ba and said Takbir at its corners but did not offer the prayer in it.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="690" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>12.08562</score>
      <text>Narrated Amr:
We asked Ibn Umar: &quot;May a man have sexual relations with his wife during the Umra before performing Tawaf between Safa and Marwa?&quot; He said, &quot;Allah&apos;s Apostle arrived (in Mecca) and circumambulated the Kaba seven times, then offered two Rakat behind Maqam Ibrahim (the station of Abraham), then performed Tawaf between Safa and Marwa.&quot; Ibn Umar added, &quot;Verily! In Allah&apos;s Apostle you have a good example.&quot; And I asked Jabir bin Abdullah (the same question), and he replied, &quot;You should not go near your wives (have sexual relations) till you have finished Tawaf between Safa and Marwa. &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="693" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>10.974597</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Umar:
The Prophet reached Mecca, circumambulated the Kaba seven times and then offered a two Rakat prayer behind Maqam ibrahim. Then he went towards the Safa. Allah has said, &quot;Verily, in Allah&apos;s Apostle you have a good example.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="70" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>15.798237</score>
      <text>Tell them the story of Abraham,</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="708" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>5.865266</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Amr bin Dinar:
We asked Ibn &apos;Umar whether a man who, while performing &apos;Umra, had performed Tawaf of the Ka&apos;ba; and had not yet performed Tawaf between Safa and Marwa, could have sexual relation with his wife, Ibn &apos;Umar replied &quot;The Prophet (p.b.u.h) reached Mecca and performed the seven rounds (of Tawaf) of the Ka&apos;ba and then offered a two-Rakat prayer behind Maqam ibrahim and then performed the seven rounds (of Tawaf) between Safa and Marwa.&quot; He added, &quot;Verily! In Allah&apos;s Apostle (p.b.u.h) you have a good example.&quot; We asked Jabir bin &apos;Abdullah (the same question) and he said, &quot;He (that man) should not come near (his wife) till he has completed Tawaf between Safa and Marwa.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="72" author="Ahmed Ali">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>14.880668</score>
      <text>(Abraham) asked: &quot;Do they hear when you call them?</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="750" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>2.5576515</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn &apos;Umar:
During the last Hajj (Hajj-al-Wada&apos;) of Allah&apos;s Apostle he performed &apos;Umra and Hajj. He drove a Hadi along with him from Dhul-Hulaifa. Allah&apos;s Apostle started by assuming Ihram for&apos;Umra and Hajj. And the people, too, performed the &apos;Umra and Hajj along with the Prophet. Some of them brought the Hadi and drove it along with them, while the others did not. So, when the Prophet arrived at Mecca. he said to the people, &quot;Whoever among you has driven the Hadi, should not finish his Ihram till he completes his Hajj. And whoever among you has not (driven) the Hadi with him, should perform Tawaf of the Ka&apos;ba and the Tawaf between Safa and Marwa, then cut short his hair and finish his Ihram, and should later assume Ihram for Hajj; but he must offer a Hadi (sacrifice); and if anyone cannot afford a Hadi, he should fast for three days during the Hajj and seven days when he returns home. The Prophet performed Tawaf of the Ka&apos;ba on his arrival (at Mecca); he touched the (Black Stone) corner first of all and then did Ramal (fast walking with moving of the shoulders) during the first three rounds round the Ka&apos;ba, and during the last four rounds he walked. After finishing Tawaf of the Ka&apos;ba, he offered a two Rakat prayer at Maqam Ibrahim, and after finishing the prayer he went to Safa and Marwa and performed seven rounds of Tawaf between them and did not do any deed forbidden because of Ihram, till he finished all the ceremonies of his Hajj and sacrificed his Hadi on the day of Nahr (10th day of Dhul-Hijja). He then hastened onwards (to Mecca) and performed Tawaf of the Ka&apos;ba and then everything that was forbidden because of Ihram became permissible. Those who took and drove the Hadi with them did the same as Allah&apos;s Apostle did.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="76" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>13.567339</score>
      <text>(Abraham) said, &quot;Do you know that what you worship and what your grandfathers worshipped</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="806" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>5.0773306</score>
      <text>Narrated Al-Amash:
I heard Al-Hajjaj saying on the pulpit, &quot;The Sura in which Al-Baqara (the cow) is mentioned and the Sura in which the family of &apos;Imran is mentioned and the Sura in which the women (An-Nisa) is mentioned.&quot; I mentioned this to Ibrahim, and he said, &apos;Abdur-Rahman bin Yazid told me, &apos;I was with Ibn Masud, when he did the Rami of the Jamrat-ul-Aqaba. He went down the middle of the valley, and when he came near the tree (which was near the Jamra) he stood opposite to it and threw seven small pebbles and said: &apos;Allahu-Akbar&apos; on throwing every pebble.&apos; Then he said, &apos;By Him, except Whom none has the right to be worshipped, here (at this place) stood the one on whom Surat-al-Baqra was revealed (i.e. Allah&apos;s Apostle).&apos; &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="83" author="Maududi">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>12.672581</score>
      <text>(And then Abraham prayed): &quot;My Lord, endow me with knowledge and wisdom and join me with the righteous,</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="131" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>12.075311</score>
      <text>When God commanded Abraham to submit, he replied, &quot;I have submitted myself to the Will of the Lord of the universe.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="134" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>11.195858</score>
      <text>That nation (children of Abraham) is gone. They have reaped what they sowed, and the same applies to you. You are not responsible for their deeds.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="144" author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.qaribullah</book_id>
      <score>7.206803</score>
      <text>We have seen you turning your face towards the heaven, We shall surely turn you to a direction that shall satisfy you. So turn your face towards the Sacred Mosque (built by Abraham); wherever you are, turn your faces to it&apos; Those to whom the Book was given know this to be the truth from their Lord. Allah is not inattentive of what they do.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="264" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>3.506938</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim bin Sad from his father from his grand-father:
Abdur Rahman bin Auf said, &quot;When we came to Medina as emigrants, Allah&apos;s Apostle established a bond of brotherhood between me and Sad bin Ar-Rabi&apos;. Sad bin Ar-Rabi&apos; said (to me), &apos;I am the richest among the Ansar, so I will give you half of my wealth and you may look at my two wives and whichever of the two you may choose I will divorce her, and when she has completed the prescribed period (before marriage) you may marry her.&apos; Abdur-Rahman replied, &quot;I am not in need of all that. Is there any market-place where trade is practiced?&apos; He replied, &quot;The market of Qainuqa.&quot; Abdur-Rahman went to that market the following day and brought some dried butter-milk (yogurt) and butter, and then he continued going there regularly. Few days later, &apos;AbdurRahman came having traces of yellow (scent) on his body. Allah&apos;s Apostle asked him whether he had got married. He replied in the affirmative. The Prophet said, &apos;Whom have you married?&apos; He replied, &apos;A woman from the Ansar.&apos; Then the Prophet asked, &apos;How much did you pay her?&apos; He replied, &apos;(I gave her) a gold piece equal in weigh to a date stone (or a date stone of gold)! The Prophet said, &apos;Give a Walima (wedding banquet) even if with one sheep .&apos; &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="339" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>14.569063</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Abdullah bin Zaid:
The Prophet said, &quot;The Prophet Abraham made Mecca a sanctuary, and asked for Allah&apos;s blessing in it. I made Medina a sanctuary as Abraham made Mecca a sanctuary and I asked for Allah&apos;s Blessing in its measures the Mudd and the Sa as Abraham did for Mecca.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="420" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>11.209338</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;The Prophet Abraham emigrated with Sarah and entered a village where there was a king or a tyrant. (The king) was told that Abraham had entered (the village) accompanied by a woman who was one of the most charming women. So, the king sent for Abraham and asked, &apos;O Abraham! Who is this lady accompanying you?&apos; Abraham replied, &apos;She is my sister (i.e. in religion).&apos; Then Abraham returned to her and said, &apos;Do not contradict my statement, for I have informed them that you are my sister. By Allah, there are no true believers on this land except you and 1.&apos; Then Abraham sent her to the king. When the king got to her, she got up and performed ablution, prayed and said, &apos;O Allah! If I have believed in You and Your Apostle, and have saved my private parts from everybody except my husband, then please do not let this pagan overpower me.&apos; On that the king fell in a mood of agitation and started moving his legs. Seeing the condition of the king, Sarah said, &apos;O Allah! If he should die, the people will say that I have killed him.&apos; The king regained his power, and proceeded towards her but she got up again and performed ablution, prayed and said, &apos;O Allah! If I have believed in You and Your Apostle and have kept my private parts safe from all except my husband, then please do not let this pagan overpower me.&apos; The king again fell in a mood of agitation and started moving his legs. On seeing that state of the king, Sarah said, &apos;O Allah! If he should die, the people will say that I have killed him.&apos; The king got either two or three attacks, and after recovering from the last attack he said, &apos;By Allah! You have sent a satan to me. Take her to Abraham and give her Ajar.&apos; So she came back to Abraham and said, &apos;Allah humiliated the pagan and gave us a slavegirl for service.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="100" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>15.174448</score>
      <text>Abraham prayed, &quot;Lord, grant me a righteous son&quot;.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="107" author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedraza</book_id>
      <score>12.315643</score>
      <text>And We rescued him in exchange of a great sacrifice. (The sacrifice of Ibrahim and Ismail – peace be upon them – is commemorated every year on 10, 11 and 12 Zil Haj).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="112" author="Wahiduddin Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.wahiduddin</book_id>
      <score>13.567339</score>
      <text>We gave Abraham the good news of Isaac, a prophet and a righteous man,</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="95" author="Maududi">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>13.104704</score>
      <text>Abraham said to them: “Do you worship what you yourselves have carved with your own hands</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="39" verse="520" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>3.506938</score>
      <text>Narrated Rafi&apos; bin Khadij:
We worked on farms more than anybody else in Medina. We used to rent the land at the yield of specific delimited portion of it to be given to the landlord. Sometimes the vegetation of that portion was affected by blights etc., while the rest remained safe and vice versa, so the Prophet forbade this practice. At that time gold or silver were not used (for renting the land). If they provided the seeds, they would get so-and-so much. Al-Hasan said, &quot;There is no harm if the land belongs to one but both spend on it and the yield is divided between them.&quot; Az-Zuhri had the same opinion. Al-Hasan said, &quot;There is no harm if cotton is picked on the condition of having half the yield.&quot; Ibrahim, Ibn Siain, &apos;Ata&apos;, Al-Hakam, Az-Zuhri and Qatada said, &quot;There is no harm in giving the yarn to the weaver to weave into cloth on the basis that one-third or one-fourth (or any other portion) of the cloth is given to the weaver for his labor.&quot; Ma&apos;am said, &quot;There is no harm in hiring animals for a definite (fixed) period on the basis that one-third or one-fourth of the products carried by the animals is given to the owner of the animals.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="120" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>10.974597</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim bin Al-Mundhir:
Ibn Abi Fudaik narrated the same as above (Hadith...119) but added that the Prophet had moved his hands as if filling them with something and then he emptied them in the Rida&apos; of Abu Huraira.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="41" verse="571" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>15.7121315</score>
      <text>Narrated Al-Amash:
When we were with Ibrahim, we talked about mortgaging in deals of Salam. Ibrahim narrated from Aswad that &apos;Aisha had said, &quot;The Prophet bought some foodstuff on credit from a Jew and mortgaged an iron armor to him.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="42" verse="15" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>8.977652</score>
      <text>So unto this (religion of Islam, alone and this Quran) then invite (people) (O Muhammad SAW), and Istaqim [(i.e. stand firm and straight on Islamic Monotheism by performing all that is ordained by Allah (good deeds, etc.), and by abstaining from all that is forbidden by Allah (sins and evil deeds, etc.)], as you are commanded, and follow not their desires but say: &quot;I believe in whatsoever Allah has sent down of the Book [all the holy Books, this Quran and the Books of the old from the Taurat (Torah), or the Injeel (Gospel) or the Pages of Ibrahim (Abraham)] and I am commanded to do justice among you, Allah is our Lord and your Lord. For us our deeds and for you your deeds. There is no dispute between us and you. Allah will assemble us (all), and to Him is the final return.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="47" verse="803" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>12.252682</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;The Prophet Abraham migrated with Sarah. The people (of the town where they migrated) gave her Ajar (i.e. Hajar). Sarah returned and said to Abraham, &quot;Do you know that Allah has humiliated that pagan and he has given a slave-girl for my service?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="48" verse="820" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>7.644827</score>
      <text>Narrated Abdullah:
The Prophet said, &quot;The people of my generation are the best, then those who follow them, and then whose who follow the latter. After that there will come some people whose witness will go ahead of their oaths, and their oaths will go ahead of their witness.&quot; Ibrahim (a sub-narrator) said, &quot;We used to be beaten for taking oaths by saying, &apos;I bear witness by the Name of Allah or by the Covenant of Allah.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="140" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>2.9716463</score>
      <text>Narrated Kuraib:
Ibn &apos;Abbas said, &quot;The Prophet slept till he snored and then prayed (or probably lay till his breath sounds were heard and then got up and prayed).&quot; Ibn &apos;Abbas added: &quot;I stayed overnight in the house of my aunt, Maimuna, the Prophet slept for a part of the night, (See Fateh-al-Bari page 249, Vol. 1), and late in the night, he got up and performed ablution from a hanging water skin, a light (perfect) ablution and stood up for the prayer. I, too, performed a similar ablution, then I went and stood on his left. He drew me to his right and prayed as much as Allah wished, and again lay and slept till his breath sounds were heard. Later on the Mua&apos;dhdhin (callmaker for the prayer) came to him and informed him that it was time for Prayer. The Prophet went with him for the prayer without performing a new ablution.&quot; (Sufyan said to &apos;Amr that some people said, &quot;The eyes of Allah&apos;s Apostle sleep but his heart does not sleep.&quot; &apos;Amr replied, &quot;I heard &apos;Ubaid bin &apos;Umar saying that the dreams of Prophets were Divine Inspiration, and then he recited the verse: &apos;I (Abraham) see in a dream, (O my son) that I offer you in sacrifice (to Allah).&quot; (37.102) (See Hadith No. 183)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="51" verse="26" author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>26.325779</score>
      <text>Then he turned to his household, so brought out a roasted calf [as the property of Ibrahim (Abraham) was mainly cows].</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="52" verse="139" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>6.068759</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
I went along with the Prophet to Khaibar so as to serve him. (Later on) when the Prophet returned he, on seeing the Uhud mountain, said, &quot;This is a mountain that loves us andis loved by us.&quot; Then he pointed to Medina with his hand saying, &quot;O Allah! I make the area which is in between Medina&apos;s two mountains a sanctuary, as Abraham made Mecca a sanctuary. O Allah! Bless us in our Sa and Mudd (i.e. units of measuring).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="52" verse="143" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>2.1672573</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
The Prophet said to Abu Talha, &quot;Choose one of your boy servants to serve me in my expedition to Khaibar.&quot; So, Abu Talha took me letting me ride behind him while I was a boy nearing the age of puberty. I used to serve Allah&apos;s Apostle when he stopped to rest. I heard him saying repeatedly, &quot;O Allah! I seek refuge with You from distress and sorrow, from helplessness and laziness, from miserliness and cowardice, from being heavily in debt and from being overcome by men.&quot; Then we reached Khaibar; and when Allah enabled him to conquer the Fort (of Khaibar), the beauty of Safiya bint Huyai bin Akhtab was described to him. Her husband had been killed while she was a bride. So Allah&apos;s Apostle selected her for himself and took her along with him till we reached a place called Sad-AsSahba,&apos; where her menses were over and he took her for his wife. Haris (a kind of dish) was served on a small leather sheet. Then Allah&apos;s Apostle told me to call those who were around me. So, that was the marriage banquet of Allah&apos;s Apostle and Safiya. Then we left for Medina. I saw Allah&apos;s Apostle folding a cloak round the hump of the camel so as to make a wide space for Safiya (to sit on behind him) He sat beside his camel letting his knees for Safiya to put her feet on so as to mount the camel. Then, we proceeded till we approached Medina; he looked at Uhud (mountain) and said, &quot;This is a mountain which loves us and is loved by us.&quot; Then he looked at Medina and said, &quot;O Allah! I make the area between its (i.e. Medina&apos;s) two mountains a sanctuary as Abraham made Mecca a sanctuary. O Allah! Bless them (i.e. the people of Medina) in their Mudd and Sa (i.e. measures).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="52" verse="239" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>8.1975355</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim Abu Isma&apos;il As-Saksaki:
I heard Abu Burda who accompanied Yazid bin Abi Kabsha on a journey. Yazid used to observe fasting on journeys. Abu Burda said to him, &quot;I heard Abu Musa several times saying that Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &apos;When a slave falls ill or travels, then he will get reward similar to that he gets for good deeds practiced at home when in good health.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="53" verse="397" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>4.6599855</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim At-Tamimi&apos;s father:
&apos;Ali delivered a sermon saying, &quot;We have no book to read except the Book of Allah and what is written in this paper which contains verdicts regarding (retaliation for) wounds, the ages of the camels (given as Zakat or as blood money) and the fact that Medina is a sanctuary in between Air mountain to so-and-so (mountain). So, whoever innovates in it an heresy or commits a sin or gives shelter in it, to such an innovator will incur the Curse of Allah, the angels and all the people, and none of his compulsory or optional good deeds of worship will be accepted. And whoever (freed slave) takes as his master (i.e. befriends) other than his real masters will incur the same (Curse). And the asylum granted by any Muslim is to be secured by all the other Muslims, and whoever betrays a Muslim in this respect will incur the same (Curse).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="417" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>8.1975355</score>
      <text>Narrated Muhammad bin Ibrahim bin Al-Harith:
from Abu Salama bin &apos;Abdur-Rahman who had a dispute with some people on a piece of land, and so he went to &apos;Aisha and told her about it. She said, &quot;O Abu Salama, avoid the land, for Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &apos;Any person who takes even a span of land unjustly, his neck shall be encircled with it down seven earths.&apos; &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="429" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0.9208908</score>
      <text>Narrated Malik bin Sasaa:
The Prophet said, &quot;While I was at the House in a state midway between sleep and wakefulness, (an angel recognized me) as the man lying between two men. A golden tray full of wisdom and belief was brought to me and my body was cut open from the throat to the lower part of the abdomen and then my abdomen was washed with Zam-zam water and (my heart was) filled with wisdom and belief. Al-Buraq, a white animal, smaller than a mule and bigger than a donkey was brought to me and I set out with Gabriel. When I reached the nearest heaven. Gabriel said to the heaven gate-keeper, &apos;Open the gate.&apos; The gatekeeper asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; He said, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; The gate-keeper,&apos; Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; The gate-keeper said, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Yes.&apos; Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What a wonderful visit his is!&apos; Then I met Adam and greeted him and he said, &apos;You are welcomed O son and a Prophet.&apos; Then we ascended to the second heaven. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was said, &apos;Who is with you?&apos; He said, &apos;Muhammad&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been sent for?&apos; He said, &apos;Yes.&apos; It was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What a wonderful visit his is!&quot; Then I met Jesus and Yahya (John) who said, &apos;You are welcomed, O brother and a Prophet.&apos; Then we ascended to the third heaven. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is with you? Gabriel said, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been sent for?&apos; &apos;Yes,&apos; said Gabriel. &apos;He is welcomed. What a wonderful visit his is!&apos; (The Prophet added:). There I met Joseph and greeted him, and he replied, &apos;You are welcomed, O brother and a Prophet!&apos; Then we ascended to the 4th heaven and again the same questions and answers were exchanged as in the previous heavens. There I met Idris and greeted him. He said, &apos;You are welcomed O brother and Prophet.&apos; Then we ascended to the 5th heaven and again the same questions and answers were exchanged as in previous heavens. there I met and greeted Aaron who said, &apos;You are welcomed O brother and a Prophet&quot;. Then we ascended to the 6th heaven and again the same questions and answers were exchanged as in the previous heavens. There I met and greeted Moses who said, &apos;You are welcomed O brother and. a Prophet.&apos; When I proceeded on, he started weeping and on being asked why he was weeping, he said, &apos;O Lord! Followers of this youth who was sent after me will enter Paradise in greater number than my followers.&apos; Then we ascended to the seventh heaven and again the same questions and answers were exchanged as in the previous heavens. There I met and greeted Abraham who said, &apos;You are welcomed o son and a Prophet.&apos; Then I was shown Al-Bait-al-Ma&apos;mur (i.e. Allah&apos;s House). I asked Gabriel about it and he said, This is Al Bait-ul-Ma&apos;mur where 70,000 angels perform prayers daily and when they leave they never return to it (but always a fresh batch comes into it daily).&apos; Then I was shown Sidrat-ul-Muntaha (i.e. a tree in the seventh heaven) and I saw its Nabk fruits which resembled the clay jugs of Hajr (i.e. a town in Arabia), and its leaves were like the ears of elephants, and four rivers originated at its root, two of them were apparent and two were hidden. I asked Gabriel about those rivers and he said, &apos;The two hidden rivers are in Paradise, and the apparent ones are the Nile and the Euphrates.&apos; Then fifty prayers were enjoined on me. I descended till I met Moses who asked me, &apos;What have you done?&apos; I said, &apos;Fifty prayers have been enjoined on me.&apos; He said, &apos;I know the people better than you, because I had the hardest experience to bring Bani Israel to obedience. Your followers cannot put up with such obligation. So, return to your Lord and request Him (to reduce the number of prayers.&apos; I returned and requested Allah (for reduction) and He made it forty. I returned and (met Moses) and had a similar discussion, and then returned again to Allah for reduction and He made it thirty, then twenty, then ten, and then I came to Moses who repeated the same advice. Ultimately Allah reduced it to five. When I came to Moses again, he said, &apos;What have you done?&apos; I said, &apos;Allah has made it five only.&apos; He repeated the same advice but I said that I surrendered (to Allah&apos;s Final Order)&apos;&quot; Allah&apos;s Apostle was addressed by Allah, &quot;I have decreed My Obligation and have reduced the burden on My slaves, and I shall reward a single good deed as if it were ten good deeds.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="477" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>17.88013</score>
      <text>Narrated Al-Bara (bin Azib):
The Prophet, after the death of his son Ibrahim, said, &quot;There is a wet-nurse for him (i.e. Ibrahim) in Paradise.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="568" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>3.9486961</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The Prophet said, &quot;You will be gathered (on the Day of Judgment), bare-footed, naked and not circumcised.&quot; He then recited:--&apos;As We began the first creation, We, shall repeat it: A Promise We have undertaken: Truly we shall do it.&apos; (21.104) He added, &quot;The first to be dressed on the Day of Resurrection, will be Abraham, and some of my companions will be taken towards the left side (i.e. to the (Hell) Fire), and I will say: &apos;My companions! My companions!&apos; It will be said: &apos;They renegade from Islam after you left them.&apos; Then I will say as the Pious slave of Allah (i.e. Jesus) said. &apos;And I was a witness Over them while I dwelt amongst them. When You took me up You were the Watcher over them, And You are a witness to all things. If You punish them. They are Your slaves And if You forgive them, Verily you, only You are the All-Mighty, the All-Wise.&quot; (5.120-121)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="569" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>11.425893</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;On the Day of Resurrection Abraham will meet his father Azar whose face will be dark and covered with dust.(The Prophet Abraham will say to him): &apos;Didn&apos;t I tell you not to disobey me?&apos; His father will reply: &apos;Today I will not disobey you.&apos; &apos;Abraham will say: &apos;O Lord! You promised me not to disgrace me on the Day of Resurrection; and what will be more disgraceful to me than cursing and dishonoring my father?&apos; Then Allah will say (to him):&apos; &apos;I have forbidden Paradise for the disbelievers.&quot; Then he will be addressed, &apos;O Abraham! Look! What is underneath your feet?&apos; He will look and there he will see a Dhabh (an animal,) blood-stained, which will be caught by the legs and thrown in the (Hell) Fire.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="570" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>11.022686</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The Prophet entered the Ka&apos;ba and found in it the pictures of (Prophet) Abraham and Mary. On that he said&apos; &quot;What is the matter with them ( i.e. Quraish)? They have already heard that angels do not enter a house in which there are pictures; yet this is the picture of Abraham. And why is he depicted as practicing divination by arrows?&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="571" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>11.693461</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
When the Prophet saw pictures in the Ka&apos;ba, he did not enter it till he ordered them to be erased. When he saw (the pictures of Abraham and Ishmael carrying the arrows of divination, he said, &quot;May Allah curse them (i.e. the Quraish)! By Allah, neither Abraham nor Ishmael practiced divination by arrows.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="572" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>5.2411213</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The people said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Who is the most honorable amongst the people (in Allah&apos;s Sight)?&quot; He said, &quot;The most righteous amongst them.&quot; They said, &quot;We do not ask you, about this. &quot; He said, &quot;Then Joseph, Allah&apos;s Prophet, the son of Allah&apos;s Prophet, The son of Allah&apos;s Prophet the son of Allah&apos;s Khalil (i.e. Abraham).&quot; They said, &quot;We do not want to ask about this,&quot; He said&apos; &quot;Then you want to ask about the descent of the Arabs. Those who were the best in the pre-lslamic period of ignorance will be the best in Islam provided they comprehend the religious knowledge.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="573" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>8.870184</score>
      <text>Narrated Samura:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Two persons came to me at night (in dream) (and took me along with them). We passed by a tall man who was so tall that I was not able to see his head and that person was Abraham.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="574" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>5.5435247</score>
      <text>Narrated Mujahid:
That when the people mentioned before Ibn &apos;Abbas that the Dajjal would have the word Kafir, (i.e. unbeliever) or the letters Kafir (the root of the Arabic verb &apos;disbelieve&apos;) written on his forehead, I heard Ibn &apos;Abbas saying, &quot;I did not hear this, but the Prophet said, &apos;If you want to see Abraham, then look at your companion (i.e. the Prophet) but Moses was a curly-haired, brown man (who used to ride) a red camel, the reins of which was made of fires of date-palms. As if I were now looking down a valley.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="575" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>12.672581</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Abraham did his circumcision with an adze at the age of eighty.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="577" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>13.104704</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Abraham did not tell a lie except on three occasions.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="578" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>9.976946</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Abraham did not tell a lie except on three occasion. Twice for the Sake of Allah when he said, &quot;I am sick,&quot; and he said, &quot;(I have not done this but) the big idol has done it.&quot; The (third was) that while Abraham and Sarah (his wife) were going (on a journey) they passed by (the territory of) a tyrant. Someone said to the tyrant, &quot;This man (i.e. Abraham) is accompanied by a very charming lady.&quot; So, he sent for Abraham and asked him about Sarah saying, &quot;Who is this lady?&quot; Abraham said, &quot;She is my sister.&quot; Abraham went to Sarah and said, &quot;O Sarah! There are no believers on the surface of the earth except you and I. This man asked me about you and I have told him that you are my sister, so don&apos;t contradict my statement.&quot; The tyrant then called Sarah and when she went to him, he tried to take hold of her with his hand, but (his hand got stiff and) he was confounded. He asked Sarah. &quot;Pray to Allah for me, and I shall not harm you.&quot; So Sarah asked Allah to cure him and he got cured. He tried to take hold of her for the second time, but (his hand got as stiff as or stiffer than before and) was more confounded. He again requested Sarah, &quot;Pray to Allah for me, and I will not harm you.&quot; Sarah asked Allah again and he became alright. He then called one of his guards (who had brought her) and said, &quot;You have not brought me a human being but have brought me a devil.&quot; The tyrant then gave Hajar as a girl-servant to Sarah. Sarah came back (to Abraham) while he was praying. Abraham, gesturing with his hand, asked, &quot;What has happened?&quot; She replied, &quot;Allah has spoiled the evil plot of the infidel (or immoral person) and gave me Hajar for service.&quot; (Abu Huraira then addressed his listeners saying, &quot;That (Hajar) was your mother, O Bani Ma-is-Sama (i.e. the Arabs, the descendants of Ishmael, Hajar&apos;s son).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="579" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>11.707454</score>
      <text>Narrated Um Sharik:
Allah&apos;s Apostle ordered that the salamander should be killed and said, &quot;It (i.e. the salamander) blew (the fire) on Abraham.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="581" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>8.565858</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
One day some meat was given to the Prophet and he said, &quot;On the Day of Resurrection Allah will gather all the first and the last (people) in one plain, and the voice of the announcer will reach all of them, and one will be able to see them all, and the sun will come closer to them.&quot; (The narrator then mentioned the narration of intercession): &quot;The people will go to Abraham and say: &apos;You are Allah&apos;s Prophet and His Khalil on the earth. Will you intercede for us with your Lord?&apos; Abraham will then remember his lies and say: &apos;Myself! Myself! Go to Moses.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="582" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>6.703942</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn &apos;Abbas:
The Prophet said, &quot;May Allah bestow His Mercy on the mother of Ishmael! Had she not hastened (to fill her water-skin with water from the Zam-zam well). Zam-zam would have been a stream flowing on the surface of the earth.&quot; Ibn &apos;Abbas further added, &quot;(The Prophet) Abraham brought Ishmael and his mother (to Mecca) and she was suckling Ishmael and she had a water-skin with her.&apos;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="583" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>5.59138</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The first lady to use a girdle was the mother of Ishmael. She used a girdle so that she might hide her tracks from Sarah. Abraham brought her and her son Ishmael while she was suckling him, to a place near the Ka&apos;ba under a tree on the spot of Zam-zam, at the highest place in the mosque. During those days there was nobody in Mecca, nor was there any water So he made them sit over there and placed near them a leather bag containing some dates, and a small water-skin containing some water, and set out homeward. Ishmael&apos;s mother followed him saying, &quot;O Abraham! Where are you going, leaving us in this valley where there is no person whose company we may enjoy, nor is there anything (to enjoy)?&quot; She repeated that to him many times, but he did not look back at her Then she asked him, &quot;Has Allah ordered you to do so?&quot; He said, &quot;Yes.&quot; She said, &quot;Then He will not neglect us,&quot; and returned while Abraham proceeded onwards, and on reaching the Thaniya where they could not see him, he faced the Ka&apos;ba, and raising both hands, invoked Allah saying the following prayers:
&apos;O our Lord! I have made some of my offspring dwell in a valley without cultivation, by Your Sacred House (Kaba at Mecca) in order, O our Lord, that they may offer prayer perfectly. So fill some hearts among men with love towards them, and (O Allah) provide them with fruits, so that they may give thanks.&apos; (14.37) Ishmael&apos;s mother went on suckling Ishmael and drinking from the water (she had).
When the water in the water-skin had all been used up, she became thirsty and her child also became thirsty. She started looking at him (i.e. Ishmael) tossing in agony; She left him, for she could not endure looking at him, and found that the mountain of Safa was the nearest mountain to her on that land. She stood on it and started looking at the valley keenly so that she might see somebody, but she could not see anybody. Then she descended from Safa and when she reached the valley, she tucked up her robe and ran in the valley like a person in distress and trouble, till she crossed the valley and reached the Marwa mountain where she stood and started looking, expecting to see somebody, but she could not see anybody. She repeated that (running between Safa and Marwa) seven times.&quot;
The Prophet said, &quot;This is the source of the tradition of the walking of people between them (i.e. Safa and Marwa). When she reached the Marwa (for the last time) she heard a voice and she asked herself to be quiet and listened attentively. She heard the voice again and said, &apos;O, (whoever you may be)! You have made me hear your voice; have you got something to help me?&quot; And behold! She saw an angel at the place of Zam-zam, digging the earth with his heel (or his wing), till water flowed from that place. She started to make something like a basin around it, using her hand in this way, and started filling her water-skin with water with her hands, and the water was flowing out after she had scooped some of it.&quot;
The Prophet added, &quot;May Allah bestow Mercy on Ishmael&apos;s mother! Had she let the Zam-zam (flow without trying to control it) (or had she not scooped from that water) (to fill her water-skin), Zam-zam would have been a stream flowing on the surface of the earth.&quot; The Prophet further added, &quot;Then she drank (water) and suckled her child. The angel said to her, &apos;Don&apos;t be afraid of being neglected, for this is the House of Allah which will be built by this boy and his father, and Allah never neglects His people.&apos; The House (i.e. Kaba) at that time was on a high place resembling a hillock, and when torrents came, they flowed to its right and left. She lived in that way till some people from the tribe of Jurhum or a family from Jurhum passed by her and her child, as they (i.e. the Jurhum people) were coming through the way of Kada&apos;. They landed in the lower part of Mecca where they saw a bird that had the habit of flying around water and not leaving it. They said, &apos;This bird must be flying around water, though we know that there is no water in this valley.&apos; They sent one or two messengers who discovered the source of water, and returned to inform them of the water. So, they all came (towards the water).&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;Ishmael&apos;s mother was sitting near the water. They asked her, &apos;Do you allow us to stay with you?&quot; She replied, &apos;Yes, but you will have no right to possess the water.&apos; They agreed to that.&quot; The Prophet further said, &quot;Ishmael&apos;s mother was pleased with the whole situation as she used to love to enjoy the company of the people. So, they settled there, and later on they sent for their families who came and settled with them so that some families became permanent residents there. The child (i.e. Ishmael) grew up and learnt Arabic from them and (his virtues) caused them to love and admire him as he grew up, and when he reached the age of puberty they made him marry a woman from amongst them.
After Ishmael&apos;s mother had died, Abraham came after Ishmael&apos;s marriage in order to see his family that he had left before, but he did not find Ishmael there. When he asked Ishmael&apos;s wife about him, she replied, &apos;He has gone in search of our livelihood.&apos; Then he asked her about their way of living and their condition, and she replied, &apos;We are living in misery; we are living in hardship and destitution,&apos; complaining to him. He said, &apos;When your husband returns, convey my salutation to him and tell him to change the threshold of the gate (of his house).&apos; When Ishmael came, he seemed to have felt something unusual, so he asked his wife, &apos;Has anyone visited you?&apos; She replied, &apos;Yes, an old man of so-and-so description came and asked me about you and I informed him, and he asked about our state of living, and I told him that we were living in a hardship and poverty.&apos; On that Ishmael said, &apos;Did he advise you anything?&apos; She replied, &apos;Yes, he told me to convey his salutation to you and to tell you to change the threshold of your gate.&apos; Ishmael said, &apos;It was my father, and he has ordered me to divorce you. Go back to your family.&apos; So, Ishmael divorced her and married another woman from amongst them (i.e. Jurhum).
Then Abraham stayed away from them for a period as long as Allah wished and called on them again but did not find Ishmael. So he came to Ishmael&apos;s wife and asked her about Ishmael. She said, &apos;He has gone in search of our livelihood.&apos; Abraham asked her, &apos;How are you getting on?&apos; asking her about their sustenance and living. She replied, &apos;We are prosperous and well-off (i.e. we have everything in abundance).&apos; Then she thanked Allah&apos; Abraham said, &apos;What kind of food do you eat?&apos; She said. &apos;Meat.&apos; He said, &apos;What do you drink?&apos; She said, &apos;Water.&quot; He said, &quot;O Allah! Bless their meat and water.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;At that time they did not have grain, and if they had grain, he would have also invoked Allah to bless it.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;If somebody has only these two things as his sustenance, his health and disposition will be badly affected, unless he lives in Mecca.&quot; The Prophet added,&quot; Then Abraham said Ishmael&apos;s wife, &quot;When your husband comes, give my regards to him and tell him that he should keep firm the threshold of his gate.&apos; When Ishmael came back, he asked his wife, &apos;Did anyone call on you?&apos; She replied, &apos;Yes, a good-looking old man came to me,&apos; so she praised him and added. &apos;He asked about you, and I informed him, and he asked about our livelihood and I told him that we were in a good condition.&apos; Ishmael asked her, &apos;Did he give you any piece of advice?&apos; She said, &apos;Yes, he told me to give his regards to you and ordered that you should keep firm the threshold of your gate.&apos; On that Ishmael said, &apos;It was my father, and you are the threshold (of the gate). He has ordered me to keep you with me.&apos;
Then Abraham stayed away from them for a period as long as Allah wished, and called on them afterwards. He saw Ishmael under a tree near Zamzam, sharpening his arrows. When he saw Abraham, he rose up to welcome him (and they greeted each other as a father does with his son or a son does with his father). Abraham said, &apos;O Ishmael! Allah has given me an order.&apos; Ishmael said, &apos;Do what your Lord has ordered you to do.&apos; Abraham asked, &apos;Will you help me?&apos; Ishmael said, &apos;I will help you.&apos; Abraham said, Allah has ordered me to build a house here,&apos; pointing to a hillock higher than the land surrounding it.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;Then they raised the foundations of the House (i.e. the Ka&apos;ba). Ishmael brought the stones and Abraham was building, and when the walls became high, Ishmael brought this stone and put it for Abraham who stood over it and carried on building, while Ishmael was handing him the stones, and both of them were saying, &apos;O our Lord! Accept (this service) from us, Verily, You are the All-Hearing, the All-Knowing.&apos; The Prophet added, &quot;Then both of them went on building and going round the Ka&apos;ba saying: O our Lord ! Accept (this service) from us, Verily, You are the All-Hearing, the All-Knowing.&quot; (2.127)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="584" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>7.322792</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
When Abraham had differences with his wife), (because of her jealousy of Hajar, Ishmael&apos;s mother), he took Ishmael and his mother and went away. They had a water-skin with them containing some water, Ishmael&apos;s mother used to drink water from the water-skin so that her milk would increase for her child. When Abraham reached Mecca, he made her sit under a tree and afterwards returned home. Ishmael&apos;s mother followed him, and when they reached Kada&apos;, she called him from behind, &apos;O Abraham! To whom are you leaving us?&apos; He replied, &apos;(I am leaving you) to Allah&apos;s (Care).&apos; She said, &apos;I am satisfied to be with Allah.&apos; She returned to her place and started drinking water from the water-skin, and her milk increased for her child. When the water had all been used up, she said to herself, &apos;I&apos;d better go and look so that I may see somebody.&apos; She ascended the Safa mountain and looked, hoping to see somebody, but in vain. When she came down to the valley, she ran till she reached the Marwa mountain. She ran to and fro (between the two mountains) many times. They she said to herself, &apos;i&apos;d better go and see the state of the child,&apos; she went and found it in a state of one on the point of dying. She could not endure to watch it dying and said (to herself), &apos;If I go and look, I may find somebody.&apos; She went and ascended the Safa mountain and looked for a long while but could not find anybody. Thus she completed seven rounds (of running) between Safa and Marwa. Again she said (to herself), &apos;I&apos;d better go back and see the state of the child.&apos; But suddenly she heard a voice, and she said to that strange voice, &apos;Help us if you can offer any help.&apos; Lo! It was Gabriel (who had made the voice). Gabriel hit the earth with his heel like this (Ibn &apos;Abbas hit the earth with his heel to Illustrate it), and so the water gushed out. Ishmael&apos;s mother was astonished and started digging. (Abu Al-Qasim) (i.e. the Prophet) said, &quot;If she had left the water, (flow naturally without her intervention), it would have been flowing on the surface of the earth.&quot;) Ishmael&apos;s mother started drinking from the water and her milk increased for her child . Afterwards some people of the tribe of Jurhum, while passing through the bottom of the valley, saw some birds, and that astonished them, and they said, &apos;Birds can only be found at a place where there is water.&apos; They sent a messenger who searched the place and found the water, and returned to inform them about it. Then they all went to her and said, &apos;O ishmael&apos;s mother! Will you allow us to be with you (or dwell with you)?&apos; (And thus they stayed there.) Later on her boy reached the age of puberty and married a lady from them. Then an idea occurred to Abraham which he disclosed to his wife (Sarah), &apos;I want to call on my dependents I left (at Mecca).&apos; When he went there, he greeted (Ishmael&apos;s wife) and said, &apos;Where is Ishmael?&apos; She replied, &apos;He has gone out hunting.&apos; Abraham said (to her), &apos;When he comes, tell him to change the threshold of his gate.&apos; When he came, she told him the same whereupon Ishmael said to her, &apos;You are the threshold, so go to your family (i.e. you are divorced).&apos; Again Abraham thought of visiting his dependents whom he had left (at Mecca), and he told his wife (Sarah) of his intentions. Abraham came to Ishmael&apos;s house and asked. &quot;Where is Ishmael?&quot; Ishmael&apos;s wife replied, &quot;He has gone out hunting,&quot; and added, &quot;Will you stay (for some time) and have something to eat and drink?&apos; Abraham asked, &apos;What is your food and what is your drink?&apos; She replied, &apos;Our food is meat and our drink is water.&apos; He said, &apos;O Allah! Bless their meals and their drink.&quot; Abu Al-Qa-sim (i.e. Prophet) said, &quot;Because of Abraham&apos;s invocation there are blessings (in Mecca).&quot; Once more Abraham thought of visiting his family he had left (at Mecca), so he told his wife (Sarah) of his decision. He went and found Ishmael behind the Zam-zam well, mending his arrows. He said, &quot;O Ishmael, Your Lord has ordered me to build a house for Him.&quot; Ishmael said, &quot;Obey (the order of) your Lord.&quot; Abraham said, &quot;Allah has also ordered me that you should help me therein.&quot; Ishmael said, &quot;Then I will do.&quot; So, both of them rose and Abraham started building (the Ka&apos;ba) while Ishmael went on handing him the stones, and both of them were saying, &quot;O our Lord ! Accept (this service) from us, Verily, You are the All-Hearing, the All-Knowing.&quot; (2.127). When the building became high and the old man (i.e. Abraham) could no longer lift the stones (to such a high position), he stood over the stone of Al-Maqam and Ishmael carried on handing him the stones, and both of them were saying, &apos;O our Lord! Accept (this service) from us, Verily You are All-Hearing, All-Knowing.&quot; (2.127)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="586" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>8.295768</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
When the mountain of Uhud came in the sight of Allah&apos;s Apostle he said. &quot;This is a mountain that loves us and is loved by us. O Allah! Abraham made Mecca a sanctuary, and I make (the area) in between these two mountains (of Medina) a sanctuary.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="587" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>10.862826</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Aisha:
(the wife of the Prophet) Allah&apos;s Apostle said (to her). &quot;Don&apos;t you see that when your folk built the Ka&apos;ba, they did not build it on all the foundations built by Abraham?&quot; I said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Why don&apos;t we rebuild it on the foundations of Abraham?&quot; He said. &quot;But for the fact that your folk have recently given up infidelity (I would have done so).&quot;
Narrated Ibn Umar: Aisha must have heard this from Allah&apos;s Apostle for I see that Allah&apos;s Apostle used not to touch the two corners facing Al-Hijr only because the House had not been built on the foundations of Abraham&apos;&apos;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="589" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>10.784621</score>
      <text>Narrated Abdur-Rahman bin Abi Laila:
Ka&apos;b bin Ujrah met me and said, &quot;Shall I not give you a present I got from the Prophet?&quot; &apos;Abdur-Rahman said, &quot;Yes, give it to me.&quot; I said, &quot;We asked Allah&apos;s Apostle saying, &apos;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! How should one (ask Allah to) send blessings on you, the members of the family, for Allah has taught us how to salute you (in the prayer)?&apos; He said, &apos;Say: O Allah! Send Your Mercy on Muhammad and on the family of Muhammad, as You sent Your Mercy on Abraham and on the family of Abraham, for You are the Most Praise-worthy, the Most Glorious. O Allah! Send Your Blessings on Muhammad and the family of Muhammad, as You sent your Blessings on Abraham and on the family of Abraham, for You are the Most Praise-worthy, the Most Glorious.&apos; &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="590" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>7.4876266</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn &apos;Abbas:
The Prophet used to seek Refuge with Allah for Al-Hasan and Al-Husain and say: &quot;Your forefather (i.e. Abraham) used to seek Refuge with Allah for Ishmael and Isaac by reciting the following: &apos;O Allah! I seek Refuge with Your Perfect Words from every devil and from poisonous pests and from every evil, harmful, envious eye.&apos; &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="591" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>8.965522</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;We are more liable to be in doubt than Abraham when he said, &apos;My Lord! Show me how You give life to the dead.&quot; . He (i.e. Allah) slid: &apos;Don&apos;t you believe then?&apos; He (i.e. Abraham) said: &quot;Yes, but (I ask) in order to be stronger in Faith.&quot; (2.260) And may Allah send His Mercy on Lot! He wished to have a powerful support. If I were to stay in prison for such a long time as Joseph did I would have accepted the offer (of freedom without insisting on having my guiltless less declared).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="596" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>10.29602</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Umar:
The Prophet said, &quot;The honorable is the son of the honorable, the son the honorable, i.e. Joseph, the son of Jacob, the son of Isaac, the son of Abraham,</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="603" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>2.9716463</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Urwa:
I asked &apos;Aisha the wife of the Prophet about the meaning of the following Verse: -- &quot;(Respite will be granted) &apos;Until when the apostles give up hope (of their people) and thought that they were denied (by their people)...............&quot;(12.110) &apos;Aisha replied, &quot;Really, their nations did not believe them.&quot; I said, &quot;By Allah! They were definite that their nations treated them as liars and it was not a matter of suspecting.&quot; &apos;Aisha said, &quot;O &apos;Uraiya (i.e. &apos;Urwa)! No doubt, they were quite sure about it.&quot;
I said, &quot;May the Verse be read in such a way as to mean that the apostles thought that Allah did not help them?&quot; Aisha said, &quot;Allah forbid! (Impossible) The Apostles did not suspect their Lord of such a thing. But this Verse is concerned with the Apostles&apos; followers who had faith in their Lord and believed in their apostles and their period of trials was long and Allah&apos;s Help was delayed till the apostles gave up hope for the conversion of the disbelievers amongst their nation and suspected that even their followers were shaken in their belief, Allah&apos;s Help then came to them.&quot;
Narrated Ibn &apos;Umar: The Prophet said, &quot;The honorable, the son of the honorable, the son of the honorable, (was) Joseph, the son of Jacob! the son of Isaac, the son of Abraham.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="607" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>4.7255564</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;On the night of my Ascension to Heaven, I saw (the prophet) Moses who was a thin person with lank hair, looking like one of the men of the tribe of Shanua; and I saw Jesus who was of average height with red face as if he had just come out of a bathroom. And I resemble prophet Abraham more than any of his offspring does. Then I was given two cups, one containing milk and the other wine. Gabriel said, &apos;Drink whichever you like.&apos; I took the milk and drank it. Gabriel said, &apos;You have accepted what is natural, (True Religion i.e. Islam) and if you had taken the wine, your followers would have gone astray.&apos; &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="647" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>3.9486961</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;I met Moses on the night of my Ascension to heaven.&quot; The Prophet then described him saying, as I think, &quot;He was a tall person with lank hair as if he belonged to the people of the tribe of Shanu&apos;s.&apos; The Prophet further said, &quot;I met Jesus.&quot; The Prophet described him saying, &quot;He was one of moderate height and was red-faced as if he had just come out of a bathroom. I saw Abraham whom I resembled more than any of his children did.&quot; The Prophet further said, &quot;(That night) I was given two cups; one full of milk and the other full of wine. I was asked to take either of them which I liked, and I took the milk and drank it. On that it was said to me, &apos;You have taken the right path (religion). If you had taken the wine, your (Muslim) nation would have gone astray.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="648" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>8.120479</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Umar:
The Prophet said, &quot;I saw Moses, Jesus and Abraham (on the night of my Ascension to the heavens). Jesus was of red complexion, curly hair and a broad chest. Moses was of brown complexion, straight hair and tall stature as if he was from the people of Az-Zutt.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="656" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>3.648775</score>
      <text>Narrted Ibn Abbas:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;You will be resurrected (and assembled) bare-footed, naked and uncircumcised.&quot; The Prophet then recited the Divine Verse:-- &quot;As We began the first creation, We shall repeat it: A promise We have undertaken. Truly we shall do it.&quot; (21.104)
He added, &quot;The first to be dressed will be Abraham. Then some of my companions will take to the right and to the left. I will say: &apos;My companions! &apos;It will be said, &apos;They had been renegades since you left them.&apos; I will then say what the Pious Slave Jesus, the son of Mary said: &apos;And I was a witness over them while I dwelt amongst them; when You did take me up, You were the Watcher over them, and You are a Witness to all things. If You punish them, they are Your slaves, and if you forgive them, You, only You are the All-Mighty the All-Wise.&apos; &quot; (5.117-118) Narrated Quaggas, &quot;Those were the apostates who renegade from Islam during the Caliphate of Abu Bakr who fought them&quot;.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="57" verse="3" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>8.504984</score>
      <text>Narrated Abdullah:
The Prophet said, &quot;The best people are those living in my generation, and then those who will follow them, and then those who will follow the latter. Then there will come some people who will bear witness before taking oaths, and take oaths before bearing witness.&quot; (Ibrahim, a sub-narrator said, &quot;They used to beat us for witnesses and covenants when we were still children.&quot;)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="57" verse="86" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>10.231836</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim: &apos;Alqama went to Sham and when he entered the mosque, he said, &quot;O Allah ! Bless me with a pious companion.&quot; So he sat with Abu Ad-Darda. Abu Ad-Darda&apos; asked him, &quot;Where are you from?&quot; &apos;Alqama replied, &quot;From the people of Kufa.&quot; Abu Ad</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="124" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>4.002063</score>
      <text>Narrated Sa&apos;d&apos;s father:
When the emigrants reached Medina. Allah&apos;s Apostle established the bond of fraternity between &apos;Abdur-Rahman and Sad bin Ar-Rabi. Sad said to &apos;Abdur-Rahman, &quot;I am the richest of all the Ansar, so I want to divide my property (between us), and I have two wives, so see which of the two you like and tell me, so that I may divorce her, and when she finishes her prescribed period (i.e. &apos;Idda) of divorce, then marry her.&quot; Abdur-Rahman said, &quot;May Allah bless your family and property for you; where is your market?&quot; So they showed him the Qainuqa&apos; market. (He went there and) returned with a profit in the form of dried yogurt and butter. He continued going (to the market) till one day he came, bearing the traces of yellow scent. The Prophet asked, &quot;What is this (scent)?&quot; He replied, &quot;I got married.&quot; The Prophet asked, &quot;How much Mahr did you give her?&quot; He replied, &quot;I gave her a date-stone of gold or a gold piece equal to the weight of a date-stone.&quot; (The narrator, Ibrahim, is in doubt as to which is correct.)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="169" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>5.4136724</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Abdullah bin &apos;Umar:
The Prophet met Zaid bin &apos;Amr bin Nufail in the bottom of (the valley of) Baldah before any Divine Inspiration came to the Prophet. A meal was presented to the Prophet but he refused to eat from it. (Then it was presented to Zaid) who said, &quot;I do not eat anything which you slaughter in the name of your stone idols. I eat none but those things on which Allah&apos;s Name has been mentioned at the time of slaughtering.&quot; Zaid bin &apos;Amr used to criticize the way Quraish used to slaughter their animals, and used to say, &quot;Allah has created the sheep and He has sent the water for it from the sky, and He has grown the grass for it from the earth; yet you slaughter it in other than the Name of Allah. He used to say so, for he rejected that practice and considered it as something abominable.
Narrated Ibn &apos;Umar: Zaid bin &apos;Amr bin Nufail went to Sham, inquiring about a true religion to follow. He met a Jewish religious scholar and asked him about their religion. He said, &quot;I intend to embrace your religion, so tell me some thing about it.&quot; The Jew said, &quot;You will not embrace our religion unless you receive your share of Allah&apos;s Anger.&quot; Zaid said, &quot;&apos;I do not run except from Allah&apos;s Anger, and I will never bear a bit of it if I have the power to avoid it. Can you tell me of some other religion?&quot; He said, &quot;I do not know any other religion except the Hanif.&quot; Zaid enquired, &quot;What is Hanif?&quot; He said, &quot;Hanif is the religion of (the prophet) Abraham who was neither a Jew nor a Christian, and he used to worship None but Allah (Alone)&quot; Then Zaid went out and met a Christian religious scholar and told him the same as before. The Christian said, &quot;You will not embrace our religion unless you get a share of Allah&apos;s Curse.&quot; Zaid replied, &quot;I do not run except from Allah&apos;s Curse, and I will never bear any of Allah&apos;s Curse and His Anger if I have the power to avoid them. Will you tell me of some other religion?&quot; He replied, &quot;I do not know any other religion except Hanif.&quot; Zaid enquired, &quot;What is Hanif?&quot; He replied, Hanif is the religion of (the prophet) Abraham who was neither a Jew nor a Christian and he used to worship None but Allah (Alone)&quot; When Zaid heard their Statement about (the religion of) Abraham, he left that place, and when he came out, he raised both his hands and said, &quot;O Allah! I make You my Witness that I am on the religion of Abraham.&quot;
Narrated Asma bint Abi Bakr: I saw Zaid bin Amr bin Nufail standing with his back against the Ka&apos;ba and saying, &quot;O people of Quraish! By Allah, none amongst you is on the religion of Abraham except me.&quot; He used to preserve the lives of little girls: If somebody wanted to kill his daughter he would say to him, &quot;Do not kill her for I will feed her on your behalf.&quot; So he would take her, and when she grew up nicely, he would say to her father, &quot;Now if you want her, I will give her to you, and if you wish, I will feed her on your behalf.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="227" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>0.521225</score>
      <text>Narrated Abbas bin Malik:
Malik bin Sasaa said that Allah&apos;s Apostle described to them his Night Journey saying, &quot;While I was lying in Al-Hatim or Al-Hijr, suddenly someone came to me and cut my body open from here to here.&quot; I asked Al-Jarud who was by my side, &quot;What does he mean?&quot; He said, &quot;It means from his throat to his pubic area,&quot; or said, &quot;From the top of the chest.&quot; The Prophet further said, &quot;He then took out my heart. Then a gold tray of Belief was brought to me and my heart was washed and was filled (with Belief) and then returned to its original place. Then a white animal which was smaller than a mule and bigger than a donkey was brought to me.&quot; (On this Al-Jarud asked, &quot;Was it the Buraq, O Abu Hamza?&quot; I (i.e. Anas) replied in the affirmative). The Prophet said, &quot;The animal&apos;s step (was so wide that it) reached the farthest point within the reach of the animal&apos;s sight. I was carried on it, and Gabriel set out with me till we reached the nearest heaven.
When he asked for the gate to be opened, it was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel answered, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has Muhammad been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!&apos; The gate was opened, and when I went over the first heaven, I saw Adam there. Gabriel said (to me). &apos;This is your father, Adam; pay him your greetings.&apos; So I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious son and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me till we reached the second heaven. Gabriel asked for the gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel answered, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel answered in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!&apos; The gate was opened.
When I went over the second heaven, there I saw Yahya (i.e. John) and &apos;Isa (i.e. Jesus) who were cousins of each other. Gabriel said (to me), &apos;These are John and Jesus; pay them your greetings.&apos; So I greeted them and both of them returned my greetings to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the third heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed, what an excellent visit his is!&apos; The gate was opened, and when I went over the third heaven there I saw Joseph. Gabriel said (to me), &apos;This is Joseph; pay him your greetings.&apos; So I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the fourth heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed, what an excel lent visit his is!&apos;
The gate was opened, and when I went over the fourth heaven, there I saw Idris. Gabriel said (to me), &apos;This is Idris; pay him your greetings.&apos; So I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the fifth heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked. &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said He is welcomed, what an excellent visit his is! So when I went over the fifth heaven, there I saw Harun (i.e. Aaron), Gabriel said, (to me). This is Aaron; pay him your greetings.&apos; I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the sixth heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked. &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. It was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!&apos;
When I went (over the sixth heaven), there I saw Moses. Gabriel said (to me),&apos; This is Moses; pay him your greeting. So I greeted him and he returned the greetings to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; When I left him (i.e. Moses) he wept. Someone asked him, &apos;What makes you weep?&apos; Moses said, &apos;I weep because after me there has been sent (as Prophet) a young man whose followers will enter Paradise in greater numbers than my followers.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the seventh heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked,&apos; Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!&apos;
So when I went (over the seventh heaven), there I saw Abraham. Gabriel said (to me), &apos;This is your father; pay your greetings to him.&apos; So I greeted him and he returned the greetings to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious son and pious Prophet.&apos; Then I was made to ascend to Sidrat-ul-Muntaha (i.e. the Lote Tree of the utmost boundary) Behold! Its fruits were like the jars of Hajr (i.e. a place near Medina) and its leaves were as big as the ears of elephants. Gabriel said, &apos;This is the Lote Tree of the utmost boundary) . Behold ! There ran four rivers, two were hidden and two were visible, I asked, &apos;What are these two kinds of rivers, O Gabriel?&apos; He replied,&apos; As for the hidden rivers, they are two rivers in Paradise and the visible rivers are the Nile and the Euphrates.&apos;
Then Al-Bait-ul-Ma&apos;mur (i.e. the Sacred House) was shown to me and a container full of wine and another full of milk and a third full of honey were brought to me. I took the milk. Gabriel remarked, &apos;This is the Islamic religion which you and your followers are following.&apos; Then the prayers were enjoined on me: They were fifty prayers a day. When I returned, I passed by Moses who asked (me), &apos;What have you been ordered to do?&apos; I replied, &apos;I have been ordered to offer fifty prayers a day.&apos; Moses said, &apos;Your followers cannot bear fifty prayers a day, and by Allah, I have tested people before you, and I have tried my level best with Bani Israel (in vain). Go back to your Lord and ask for reduction to lessen your followers&apos; burden.&apos; So I went back, and Allah reduced ten prayers for me. Then again I came to Moses, but he repeated the same as he had said before. Then again I went back to Allah and He reduced ten more prayers. When I came back to Moses he said the same, I went back to Allah and He ordered me to observe ten prayers a day. When I came back to Moses, he repeated the same advice, so I went back to Allah and was ordered to observe five prayers a day.
When I came back to Moses, he said, &apos;What have you been ordered?&apos; I replied, &apos;I have been ordered to observe five prayers a day.&apos; He said, &apos;Your followers cannot bear five prayers a day, and no doubt, I have got an experience of the people before you, and I have tried my level best with Bani Israel, so go back to your Lord and ask for reduction to lessen your follower&apos;s burden.&apos; I said, &apos;I have requested so much of my Lord that I feel ashamed, but I am satisfied now and surrender to Allah&apos;s Order.&apos; When I left, I heard a voice saying, &apos;I have passed My Order and have lessened the burden of My Worshipers.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="59" verse="303" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>13.81635</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Abdur-Rahman bin &apos;Auf:
(the grandfather of Salih bin Ibrahim) the story of Badr, namely, the narration regarding the sons of &apos;Afra&apos;.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="59" verse="376" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>5.865266</score>
      <text>Narrated Sad bin Ibrahim:
A meal was brought to &apos;Abdur-Rahman bin &apos;Auf while he was fasting. He said, &quot;Musab bin &apos;Umar was martyred, and he was better than I, yet he was shrouded in a Burda (i.e. a sheet) so that, if his head was covered, his feet became naked, and if his feet were covered, his head became naked.&quot; &apos;Abdur-Rahman added, &quot;Hamza was martyred and he was better than 1. Then worldly wealth was bestowed upon us and we were given thereof too much. We are afraid that the reward of our deeds have been given to us in this life.&quot; &apos;Abdur-Rahman then started weeping so much that he left the food.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="59" verse="410" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>8.295768</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
When the mountain of Uhud appeared before Allah&apos;s Apostle he said, &quot;This IS a mountain that loves us and is loved by us. O, Allah! Abraham made Mecca a Sanctuary, and I have made Medina (i.e. the area between its two mountains) a Sanctuary as well.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="59" verse="584" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>8.965522</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
When Allah&apos;s Apostle arrived in Mecca, he refused to enter the Ka&apos;ba while there were idols in it. So he ordered that they be taken out. The pictures of the (Prophets) Abraham and Ishmael, holding arrows of divination in their hands, were carried out. The Prophet said, &quot;May Allah ruin them (i.e. the infidels) for they knew very well that they (i.e. Abraham and Ishmael) never drew lots by these (divination arrows). Then the Prophet entered the Ka&apos;ba and said. &quot;Allahu Akbar&quot; in all its directions and came out and not offer any prayer therein.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="59" verse="635" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>13.906622</score>
      <text>Narrated Amr bin Maimuin:
When Mu&apos;adh arrived at Yemen, he led them (i.e. the people of Yemen) in the Fajr prayer wherein he recited: &apos;Allah took Abraham as a Khalil.&apos; A man amongst the people said, &quot;(How) glad the mother of Abraham is!&quot; (In another narration) &apos;Amr said, &quot;The Prophet sent Mu&apos;adh to Yemen and he (led the people) in the Fajr prayer and recited: &apos;Allah took Abraham as a Khalil. A man behind him said, &quot;(How) glad the mother of Abraham is!&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="10" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>3.648775</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas:
Umar said, &quot;I agreed with Allah in three things,&quot; or said, &quot;My Lord agreed with me in three things. I said, &apos;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Would that you took the station of Abraham as a place of prayer.&apos; I also said, &apos;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Good and bad persons visit you! Would that you ordered the Mothers of the believers to cover themselves with veils.&apos; So the Divine Verses of Al-Hijab (i.e. veiling of the women) were revealed. I came to know that the Prophet had blamed some of his wives so I entered upon them and said, &apos;You should either stop (troubling the Prophet ) or else Allah will give His Apostle better wives than you.&apos; When I came to one of his wives, she said to me, &apos;O &apos;Umar! Does Allah&apos;s Apostle haven&apos;t what he could advise his wives with, that you try to advise them?&apos; &quot; Thereupon Allah revealed:--
&quot;It may be, if he divorced you (all) his Lord will give him instead of you, wives better than you Muslims (who submit to Allah)..&quot; (66.5)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="149" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>3.648775</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
Allah&apos;s Apostle delivered a sermon and said, &quot;O people! You will be gathered before Allah bare-footed, naked and not circumcised.&quot; Then (quoting Quran) he said:--
&quot;As We began the first creation, We shall repeat it. A promise We have undertaken: Truly we shall do it..&quot; (21.104)
The Prophet then said, &quot;The first of the human beings to be dressed on the Day of Resurrection, will be Abraham. Lo! Some men from my followers will be brought and then (the angels) will drive them to the left side (Hell-Fire). I will say. &apos;O my Lord! (They are) my companions!&apos; Then a reply will come (from Almighty), &apos;You do not know what they did after you.&apos; I will say as the pious slave (the Prophet Jesus) said: And I was a witness over them while I dwelt amongst them. When You took me up. You were the Watcher over them and You are a Witness to all things.&apos; (5.117) Then it will be said, &quot;These people have continued to be apostates since you left them.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="210" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>10.1599245</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Abdullah bin Umar:
The Prophet said, &quot;The honorable, the son of the honorable the son of the honorable, i.e. Joseph, the son of Jacob, the son of Isaac, the son of Abraham.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="211" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>4.970005</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle was asked, &quot;Who are the most honorable of the people?&quot; The Prophet said, &quot;The most honorable of them in Allah&apos;s Sight are those who keep their duty to Allah and fear Him. They said, &quot;We do not ask you about that.&quot; He said, &quot;Then the most honorable of the people is Joseph, Allah&apos;s prophet, the son of Allah&apos;s prophet, the son of Allah&apos;s prophet, the son of Allah&apos;s Khalil i.e. Abraham) They said, &quot;We do not ask you about that.&quot; The Prophet said, Do you ask about (the virtues of the ancestry of the Arabs?&quot; They said, &quot;Yes,&quot; He said, &quot;Those who were the best amongst you in the Pre-lslamic Period are the</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="216" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>9.640203</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;May Allah bestow His Mercy on (Prophet) Lot. (When his nation troubled him) he wished if he could betake himself to some powerful support; and if I were to remain in prison for the period Joseph had remained, I would surely respond to the call; and we shall have more right (to be in doubt) than Abraham: When Allah said to him, &quot;Don&apos;t you believe?&apos; Abraham said, &apos;Yes, (I do believe) but to be stronger in faith; (2.260)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="236" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>2.561305</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Some (cooked) meat was brought to Allah Apostle and the meat of a forearm was presented to him as he used to like it. He ate a morsel of it and said, &quot;I will be the chief of all the people on the Day of Resurrection. Do you know the reason for it? Allah will gather all the human being of early generations as well as late generation on one plain so that the announcer will be able to make them all-hear his voice and the watcher will be able to see all of them. The sun will come so close to the people that they will suffer such distress and trouble as they will not be able to bear or stand. Then the people will say, &apos;Don&apos;t you see to what state you have reached? Won&apos;t you look for someone who can intercede for you with your Lord&apos; Some people will say to some others, &apos;Go to Adam.&apos; So they will go to Adam and say to him. &apos;You are the father of mankind; Allah created you with His Own Hand, and breathed into you of His Spirit (meaning the spirit which he created for you); and ordered the angels to prostrate before you; so (please) intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are? Don&apos;t you see what condition we have reached?&apos; Adam will say, &apos;Today my Lord has become angry as He has never become before, nor will ever become thereafter. He forbade me (to eat of the fruit of) the tree, but I disobeyed Him . Myself! Myself! Myself! (has more need for intercession). Go to someone else; go to Noah.&apos; So they will go to Noah and say (to him), &apos;O Noah! You are the first (of Allah&apos;s Messengers) to the people of the earth, and Allah has named you a thankful slave; please intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&apos; He will say.&apos; Today my Lord has become angry as He has never become nor will ever become thereafter. I had (in the world) the right to make one definitely accepted invocation, and I made it against my nation. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Abraham.&apos; They will go to Abraham and say, &apos;O Abraham! You are Allah&apos;s Apostle and His Khalil from among the people of the earth; so please intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&apos; He will say to them, &apos;My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before, nor will ever become thereafter. I had told three lies (Abu Haiyan (the sub-narrator) mentioned them in the Hadith) Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Moses.&apos; The people will then go to Moses and say, &apos;O Moses! You art Allah&apos;s Apostle and Allah gave you superiority above the others with this message and with His direct Talk to you; (please) intercede for us with your Lord Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&apos; Moses will say, &apos;My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before, nor will become thereafter, I killed a person whom I had not been ordered to kill. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Jesus.&apos; So they will go to Jesus and say, &apos;O Jesus! You are Allah&apos;s Apostle and His Word which He sent to Mary, and a superior soul created by Him, and you talked to the people while still young in the cradle. Please intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&apos; Jesus will say. &apos;My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before nor will ever become thereafter. Jesus will not mention any sin, but will say, &apos;Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Muhammad.&apos; So they will come to me and say, &apos;O Muhammad ! You are Allah&apos;s Apostle and the last of the prophets, and Allah forgave your early and late sins. (Please) intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;Then I will go beneath Allah&apos;s Throne and fall in prostration before my Lord. And then Allah will guide me to such praises and glorification to Him as He has never guided anybody else before me. Then it will be said, &apos;O Muhammad Raise your head. Ask, and it will be granted. Intercede It (your intercession) will be accepted.&apos; So I will raise my head and Say, &apos;My followers, O my Lord! My followers, O my Lord&apos;. It will be said, &apos;O Muhammad! Let those of your followers who have no accounts, enter through such a gate of the gates of Paradise as lies on the right; and they will share the other gates with the people.&quot; The Prophet further said, &quot;By Him in Whose Hand my soul is, the distance between every two gate-posts of Paradise is like the distance between Mecca and Busra (in Sham).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="264" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>3.9486961</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The Prophet delivered a sermon and said, &quot;You (people) will be gathered before Allah (on the Day of Resurrection) bare-footed, naked and uncircumcised.&quot; (The Prophet then recited):-- &apos;As We began the first creation We shall repeat it. (It is) a promise We have undertaken and truly We shall do it.&apos; and added, &quot;The first man who will be dressed on the Day of Resurrection, will be Abraham. Lo! Some men from my followers will be brought and taken towards the left side, whereupon I will say, &apos;O Lord, (these are) my companions!&apos; It will be said, &apos;You do not know what new things they introduced (into the religion) after you.&apos; I will then say as the righteous pious slave, Jesus, said, &apos;I was a witness over them while I dwelt among them...(to His Statement)..and You are the Witness to all things.&apos; (5.117) Then it will be said, &apos;(O Muhammad) These people never stopped to apostate since you left them.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="291" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>11.195858</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;On the Day of Resurrection Abraham will see his father covered with Qatara and Ghabara. (i.e. having a dark face).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="292" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>8.120479</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, Abraham will meet his father (on the Day of Resurrection) and will say, &apos;O my Lords You promised me that You would not let me in disgrace on the Day when people will be resurrected.&apos; Allah will say, &apos;I have forbidden Paradise to the non-believers.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="3" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>1.4060555</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, &quot;On the Day of Resurrection the Believers will assemble and say, &apos;Let us ask somebody to intercede for us with our Lord.&apos; So they will go to Adam and say, &apos;You are the father of all the people, and Allah created you with His Own Hands, and ordered the angels to prostrate to you, and taught you the names of all things; so please intercede for us with your Lord, so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; Adam will say, &apos;I am not fit for this (i.e. intercession for you).&apos; Then Adam will remember his sin and feel ashamed thereof. He will say, &apos;Go to Noah, for he was the first Apostle, Allah sent to the inhabitants of the earth.&apos; They will go to him and Noah will say,
&apos;I am not fit for this undertaking.&apos; He will remember his appeal to his Lord to do what he had no knowledge of, then he will feel ashamed thereof and will say, &apos;Go to the Khalil--r-Rahman (i.e. Abraham).&apos; They will go to him and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking. Go to Moses, the slave to whom Allah spoke (directly) and gave him the Torah .&apos; So they will go to him and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking.&apos; and he will mention (his) killing a person who was not a killer, and so he will feel ashamed thereof before his Lord, and he will say, &apos;Go to Jesus, Allah&apos;s Slave, His Apostle and Allah&apos;s Word and a Spirit coming from Him. Jesus will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking, go to Muhammad the Slave of Allah whose past and future sins were forgiven by Allah.&apos; So they will come to me and I will proceed till I will ask my Lord&apos;s Permission and I will be given permission. When I see my Lord, I will fall down in Prostration and He will let me remain in that state as long as He wishes and then I will be addressed.&apos; (Muhammad!) Raise your head. Ask, and your request will be granted; say, and your saying will be listened to; intercede, and your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will raise my head and praise Allah with a saying (i.e. invocation) He will teach me, and then I will intercede. He will fix a limit for me (to intercede for) whom I will admit into Paradise. Then I will come back again to Allah, and when I see my Lord, the same thing will happen to me. And then I will intercede and Allah will fix a limit for me to intercede whom I will let into Paradise, then I will come back for the third time; and then I will come back for the fourth time, and will say, &apos;None remains in Hell but those whom the Quran has imprisoned (in Hell) and who have been destined to an eternal stay in Hell.&apos; &quot; (The compiler) Abu &apos;Abdullah said: &apos;But those whom the Qur&apos;an has imprisoned in Hell,&apos; refers to the Statement of Allah:
&quot;They will dwell therein forever.&quot; (16.29)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="320" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>10.715311</score>
      <text>Narrated Ka&apos;b bin Ujra:
It was said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! We know how to greet you, but how to invoke Allah for you?&quot; The Prophet said, &quot;Say: Allahumma salli ala Muhammadin wa&apos;ala Ali Muhammaddin, kama sallaita &apos;ala all Ibrahim, innaka Hamidun Majid.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="321" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>15.79617</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Said Al-Khudri:
We said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! (We know) this greeting (to you) but how shall we invoke Allah for you?&quot; He said, &quot;Say! Allahumma salli ala Muhammadin &apos;Abdika wa rasulika kama- sallaita &apos;ala all Ibrahim wa barik ala Muhammadin wa&apos;ala all Muhammadin kama barakta &apos;ala all Ibrahim.&apos; Al-Laith said: &apos;Ala Muhammadin wa &apos;ala all Muhammadin kama barakta ala all Ibrahim.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="322" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>12.838581</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abi Hazim and Ad-Darawardi:
Yazid said, &quot;Kama sallaita ala Ibrahima wa barik &apos;ala Muhammad in wa all Muhammadin kama barakta &apos;ala Abrahima wa all Ibrahim.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="468" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>5.576784</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim:
The companions of &apos;Abdullah (bin Mas&apos;ud) came to Abu Darda&apos;, (and before they arrived at his home), he looked for them and found them. Then he asked them,: &apos;Who among you can recite (Qur&apos;an) as &apos;Abdullah recites it?&quot; They replied, &quot;All of us.&quot; He asked, &quot;Who among you knows it by heart?&quot; They pointed at &apos;Alqama. Then he asked Alqama. &quot;How did you hear &apos;Abdullah bin Mas&apos;ud reciting Surat Al-Lail (The Night)?&quot; Alqama recited:
&apos;By the male and the female.&apos; Abu Ad-Darda said, &quot;I testify that I heard me Prophet reciting it likewise, but these people want me to recite it:--
&apos;And by Him Who created male and female.&apos; but by Allah, I will not follow them.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="61" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>8.478792</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;We have more right to be in doubt than Abraham when he said, &apos;My Lord! Show me how You give life to the dead.&apos; He said, &apos;Do you not believe?&apos; He said, &apos;Yes (I believe) but to be stronger in Faith.&apos; &quot;(2.260)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="86" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>6.703942</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
&apos;Allah is Sufficient for us and He Is the Best Disposer of affairs,&quot; was said by Abraham when he was thrown into the fire; and it was said by Muhammad when they (i.e. hypocrites) said, &quot;A great army is gathering against you, therefore, fear them,&quot; but it only increased their faith and they said: &quot;Allah is Sufficient for us, and He is the Best Disposer (of affairs, for us).&quot; (3.173)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="87" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>10.29602</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The last statement of Abraham when he was thrown into the fire was:--&quot;Allah is Sufficient for us and He is the Best Disposer (of affairs for us).&quot; (3.173)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="62" verse="155" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>6.4779377</score>
      <text>Narrated Aisha:
That Allah&apos;s Apostle said to her, &quot;I you are pleased with me or angry with me.&quot; I said, &quot;Whence do you know that?&quot; He said, &quot;When you are pleased with me, you say, &apos;No, by the Lord of Muhammad,&apos; but when you are angry with me, then you say, &apos;No, by the Lord of Abraham.&apos; &quot; Thereupon I said, &quot;Yes (you are right), but by Allah, O Allah&apos;s Apostle, I leave nothing but your name.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="62" verse="21" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>9.888243</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said: Abraham did not tell lies except three. (One of them was) when Abraham passed by a tyrant and (his wife) Sara was accompanying him (Abu Huraira then mentioned the whole narration and said:) (The tyrant) gave her Hajar. Sara said, &quot;Allah saved me from the hands of the Kafir (i.e. infidel) and gave me Hajar to serve me.&quot; (Abu Huraira added:) That (Hajar) is your mother, O Banu Ma&apos;-As-Sama&apos; (i.e., the Arabs).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="65" verse="336" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>2.9716463</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said to Abu Talha, &quot;Seek one of your boys to serve me.&quot; Abu Talha mounted me behind him (on his riding animal) and took me (to the Prophet ). So I used to serve Allah&apos;s Apostle whenever he dismounted (to stay somewhere). I used to hear him saying very often, &quot;O Allah! I seek refuge with You from, having worries sadness, helplessness, laziness, miserliness, cowardice, from being heavily in debt and from being overpowered by other persons unjustly.&quot; I kept on serving till we -returned from the battle of Khaibar. The Prophet then brought Safiyya bint Huyai whom he had won from the war booty. I saw him folding up a gown or a garment for her to sit on behind him (on his she-camel). When he reached As-Sahba&apos;, he prepared Hais and placed it on a dining sheet. Then he sent me to invite men, who (came and) ate; and that was his and Safiyya&apos;s wedding banquet. Then the Prophet proceeded, and when he saw (noticed) the mountain of Uhud, he said, &quot;This mountain loves us, and we love it.&quot; When we approached Medina, he said, &quot;O Allah! I make the area between its two mountains a sanctuary as Abraham has made Mecca a sanctuary. O Allah! Bless their Mudd and Sa (special kinds of measure).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="66" verse="376" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>10.231836</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Musa:
A son was born to me and I took him to the Prophet who named him Ibrahim, did Tahnik for him with a date, invoked Allah to bless him and returned him to me. (The narrator added: That was Abu Musa&apos;s eldest son.)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="69" verse="500" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>6.542095</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim:
I asked Al-Aswad, &quot;Did you ask &apos;Aisha, Mother of the Believers, about the containers in which it is disliked to prepare (non-alcoholic) drinks?&quot; He said, &quot;Yes, I said to her, &apos;O Mother of the Believers! What containers did the Prophet forbid to use for preparing (non-alcoholic) drinks?&quot; She said, &apos;The Prophet forbade us, (his family), to prepare (nonalcoholic) drinks in Ad-Dubba and Al-Muzaffat.&apos; I asked, &apos;Didn&apos;t you mention Al Jar and Al Hantam?&apos; She said, &apos;I tell what I have heard; shall I tell you what I have not heard?&apos; &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="80" author="Sarwar">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>8.870184</score>
      <text>In an argument with his people, (Abraham) asked them, &quot;Why do you argue with me about God who has given me guidance? Your idols can do no harm to me unless God wills. God knows all things. Why, then, do you not consider this?</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="72" verse="795" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>5.8829613</score>
      <text>Narrated Mujahid:
We were with Ibn &apos;Abbas and the people mentioned Ad-Dajjal. Someone said, &quot;The word &apos;Kafir&apos; (unbeliever) is written in between his (Ad-Dajjal&apos;s) eyes.&quot; Ibn &apos;Abbas said, &quot;I have not heard the Prophet saying this, but he said, &apos;As regards Abraham, he looks like your companion (i.e. the Prophet, Muhammad), and as regards Moses, he is a brown curly haired man riding a camel and reigned with a strong jute rope, as if lam now looking at him getting down in the valley and saying, &quot;Labbaik&quot;.&apos;&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="73" verse="101" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>7.7912226</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Aisha:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot; I know whether you are angry or pleased.&quot; I said, &quot;How do you know that, Allah&apos;s Apostle?&quot; He said, &quot;When you are pleased, you say, &quot;Yes, by the Lord of Muhammad,&apos; but when you are angry, you say, &apos;No, by the Lord of Abraham!&apos; &quot; I said, &quot;Yes, I do not leave, except your name.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="73" verse="214" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>10.467995</score>
      <text>Narrated Isma&apos;il:
I asked Abi Aufa, &quot;Did you see Ibrahim, the son of the Prophet ?&quot; He said, &quot;Yes, but he died in his early childhood. Had there been a Prophet after Muhammad then his son would have lived, but there is no Prophet after him.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="73" verse="215" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>13.81635</score>
      <text>Narrated Al-Bara:
When Ibrahim (the son of the Prophet) died, Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;There is a wet nurse for him in Paradise.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="73" verse="218" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>9.194677</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Musa:
I got a son and I took him to the Prophet who named him Ibrahim, and put in his mouth the juice of a date fruit (which be himself had chewed?, and invoked for Allah&apos;s blessing upon him, and then gave him back to me. He was the eldest son of Abii Musa.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="74" verse="295" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>4.30604</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim:
&apos;Alaqama went to Sham and came to the mosque and offered a two-Rak&apos;at prayer, and invoked Allah: &quot;O Allah! Bless me with a (pious) good companion.&quot; So he sat beside Abu Ad-Darda&apos; who asked, &quot;From where are you?&quot; He said, &quot;From the people of Kufa.&quot; Abu Darda&apos; said, &quot;Wasn&apos;t there among you the person who keeps the secrets (of the Prophet ) which nobody knew except him (i.e., Hudhaifa (bin Al-Yaman)). And isn&apos;t there among you the person whom Allah gave refuge from Satan through the request (tongue) of Allah&apos;s Apostle? (i.e., &apos;Ammar). Isn&apos;t there among you the one who used to carry the Siwak and the cushion (or pillows (of the Prophets)? (i.e., Ibn Mas&apos;ud). How did Ibn Mas&apos;ud use to recite &apos;By the night as it conceals (the light)?&quot; (Sura 92). &apos;Alqama said, &quot;Wadhdhakari Wal Untha&apos; (And by male and female.&quot;) Abu Ad-Darda added. &apos;These people continued to argue with me regarding it till they were about to cause me to have doubts although I heard it from Allah&apos;s Apostle &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="74" verse="313" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>6.068759</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said &quot;The Prophet) Abraham circumcised himself after he had passed the age of eighty years and he circumcised himself with an adze.&quot;
Narrated Said bin Jubair: Ibn &apos;Abbas was asked, &quot;How old were you when the Prophet died?&quot; He replied. &quot;At that time I had been circumcised.&quot; At that time, people did not circumcise the boys till they attained the age of puberty. Sa&apos;id bin Jubair said, &quot;Ibn &apos;Abbas said, &apos;When the Prophet died, I had already been circumcised. &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="75" verse="369" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>9.194677</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri:
We said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle This is (i.e. we know) the greeting to you; will you tell us how to send Salat on you?&quot; He said, &quot;Say: &apos;Allahumma Salli &apos;ala Muhammadin &apos;abdika wa rasulika kama sal-laita &apos;ala Ibrahima wa barik &apos;ala Muhammadin wa all Muhammadin kama barakta &apos;ala Ibrahima wa Ali Ibrahim.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="75" verse="371" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>14.45979</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Humaid As-Saidi:
The people said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle ! How may we send Salat on you?&quot; He said, &quot;Say: Allahumma Salli &apos;ala- Muhammadin wa azwajihi wa dhurriyyatihi kama sal-laita &apos;ala ali Ibrahim; wa barik &apos;ala Muhammadin wa azwajihi wa dhurriyyatihi kamabarakta &apos;ala ali Ibrahim innaka hamidun majid.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="75" verse="374" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>2.7985306</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
The Prophet said to Abu Talha, &quot;Choose one of your boys to serve me.&quot; So Abu Talha took me (to serve the Prophet ) by giving me a ride behind him (on his camel). So I used to serve Allah&apos;s Apostle whenever he stayed somewhere. I used to hear him saying, &quot;O Allah! I seek refuge with you (Allah) from (worries) care and grief, from incapacity and laziness, from miserliness and cowardice, from being heavily in debt and from being overpowered by other men.&quot; I kept on serving him till he returned from (the battle of) Khaibar. He then brought Safiya, the daughter of Huyay whom he had got (from the booty). I saw him making a kind of cushion with a cloak or a garment for her. He then let her ride behind him. When we reached a place called As-Sahba&apos;, he prepared (a special meal called) Hais, and asked me to invite the men who (came and) ate, and that was the marriage banquet given on the consummation of his marriage to her. Then he proceeded till the mountain of Uhud appeared, whereupon he said, &quot;This mountain loves us and we love it.&quot; When he approached Medina, he said, &quot;O Allah! I make the land between its (i.e., Medina&apos;s) two mountains a sanctuary, as the prophet Abraham made Mecca a sanctuary. O Allah! Bless them (the people of Medina) in their Mudd and the Sa&apos; (units of measuring).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="533" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>4.117938</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibn &apos;Abbas:
The Prophet stood up among us and addressed (saying) &quot;You will be gathered, barefooted, naked, and uncircumcised (as Allah says): &apos;As We began the first creation, We shall repeat it..&apos; (21.104) And the first human being to be dressed on the Day of Resurrection will be (the Prophet) Abraham Al-Khalil. Then will be brought some men of my followers who will be taken towards the left (i.e., to the Fire), and I will say: &apos;O Lord! My companions whereupon Allah will say: You do not know what they did after you left them. I will then say as the pious slave, Jesus said, And I was witness over them while I dwelt amongst them..........(up to) ...the All-Wise.&apos; (5.117-118). The narrator added: Then it will be said that those people (relegated from Islam, that is) kept on turning on their heels (deserted Islam).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="570" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>1.7055788</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Allah will gather all the people on the Day of Resurrection and they will say, &apos;Let us request someone to intercede for us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; Then they will go to Adam and say, &apos;You are the one whom Allah created with His Own Hands, and breathed in you of His soul, and ordered the angels to prostrate to you; so please intercede for us with our Lord.&apos; Adam will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking, and will remember his sin, and will say, &apos;Go to Noah, the first Apostle sent by Allah&apos; They will go to him and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking&apos;, and will remember his sin and say, &apos;Go to Abraham whom Allah took as a Khalil. They will go to him (and request similarly). He will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and will remember his sin and say, &apos;Go to Moses to whom Allah spoke directly.&apos; They will go to Moses and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and will remember his sin and say, &apos;Go to Jesus.&apos; They will go to him, and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking, go to Muhammad as Allah has forgiven his past and future sins.&apos; They will come to me and I will ask my Lord&apos;s permission, and when I see Him, I will fall down in prostration to Him, and He will leave me in that state as long as (He) Allah will, and then I will be addressed. &apos;Raise up your head (O Muhammad)! Ask, and your request will be granted, and say, and your saying will be listened to; intercede, and your intercession will be accepted.&apos; Then I will raise my head, and I will glorify and praise my Lord with a saying(i.e. invocation) He will teach me, and then I will intercede, Allah will fix a limit for me (i.e., certain type of people for whom I may intercede), and I will take them out of the (Hell) Fire and let them enter Paradise. Then I will come back (to Allah) and fall in prostration, and will do the same for the third and fourth times till no-one remains in the (Hell) Fire except those whom the Qur&apos;an has imprisoned therein.&quot; (The sub-narrator, Qatada used to say at that point, &quot;...those upon whom eternity (in Hell) has been imposed.&quot;) (See Hadith No. 3, Vol 6).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="78" verse="652" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>6.9426756</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Abdullah:
The Prophet was asked, &quot;Who are the best people?&quot; He replied: The people of my generation, and then those who will follow (come after) them, and then those who will come after the later; after that there will come some people whose witness will precede their oaths and their oaths will go ahead of their witness.&quot; Ibrahim (a sub-narrator) said, &quot;When we were young, our elder friends used to prohibit us from taking oaths by saying, &apos;I bear witness swearing by Allah, or by Allah&apos;s Covenant.&quot;&apos;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="85" verse="82" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>11.288252</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;(The Prophet) Abraham migrated with his wife Sarah till he reached a town where there was a king or a tyrant who sent a message, to Abraham, ordering him to send Sarah to him. So when Abraham had sent Sarah, the tyrant got up, intending to do evil with her, but she got up and performed ablution and prayed and said, &apos;O Allah ! If I have believed in You and in Your Apostle, then do not empower this oppressor over me.&apos; So he (the king) had an epileptic fit and started moving his legs violently. &quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="87" verse="171" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0.7047386</score>
      <text>Narrated Samura bin Jundub:
Allah&apos;s Apostle very often used to ask his companions, &quot;Did anyone of you see a dream?&quot; So dreams would be narrated to him by those whom Allah wished to tell. One morning the Prophet said, &quot;Last night two persons came to me (in a dream) and woke me up and said to me, &apos;Proceed!&apos; I set out with them and we came across a man Lying down, and behold, another man was standing over his head, holding a big rock. Behold, he was throwing the rock at the man&apos;s head, injuring it. The rock rolled away and the thrower followed it and took it back. By the time he reached the man, his head returned to the normal state. The thrower then did the same as he had done before. I said to my two companions, &apos;Subhan Allah! Who are these two persons?&apos; They said, &apos;Proceed!&apos; So we proceeded and came to a man Lying flat on his back and another man standing over his head with an iron hook, and behold, he would put the hook in one side of the man&apos;s mouth and tear off that side of his face to the back (of the neck) and similarly tear his nose from front to back and his eye from front to back. Then he turned to the other side of the man&apos;s face and did just as he had done with the other side. He hardly completed this side when the other side returned to its normal state. Then he returned to it to repeat what he had done before. I said to my two companions, &apos;Subhan Allah! Who are these two persons?&apos; They said to me, &apos;Proceed!&apos; So we proceeded and came across something like a Tannur (a kind of baking oven, a pit usually clay-lined for baking bread).&quot; I think the Prophet said, &quot;In that oven t here was much noise and voices.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;We looked into it and found naked men and women, and behold, a flame of fire was reaching to them from underneath, and when it reached them, they cried loudly. I asked them, &apos;Who are these?&apos; They said to me, &apos;Proceed!&apos; And so we proceeded and came across a river.&quot; I think he said, &quot;.... red like blood.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;And behold, in the river there was a man swimming, and on the bank there was a man who had collected many stones. Behold. while the other man was swimming, he went near him. The former opened his mouth and the latter (on the bank) threw a stone into his mouth whereupon he went swimming again. He returned and every time the performance was repeated, I asked my two companions, &apos;Who are these (two) persons?&apos; They replied, &apos;Proceed! Proceed!&apos; And we proceeded till we came to a man with a repulsive appearance, the most repulsive appearance, you ever saw a man having! Beside him there was a fire and he was kindling it and running around it. I asked my companions, &apos;Who is this (man)?&apos; They said to me, &apos;Proceed! Proceed!&apos; So we proceeded till we reached a garden of deep green dense vegetation, having all sorts of spring colors. In the midst of the garden there was a very tall man and I could hardly see his head because of his great height, and around him there were children in such a large number as I have never seen. I said to my companions, &apos;Who is this?&apos; They replied, &apos;Proceed! Proceed!&apos; So we proceeded till we came to a majestic huge garden, greater and better than I have ever seen! My two companions said to me, &apos;Go up and I went up&apos; The Prophet added, &quot;So we ascended till we reached a city built of gold and silver bricks and we went to its gate and asked (the gatekeeper) to open the gate, and it was opened and we entered the city and found in it, men with one side of their bodies as handsome as the handsomest person you have ever seen, and the other side as ugly as the ugliest person you have ever seen. My two companions ordered those men to throw themselves into the river. Behold, there was a river flowing across (the city), and its water was like milk in whiteness. Those men went and threw themselves in it and then returned to us after the ugliness (of their bodies) had disappeared and they became in the best shape.&quot; The Prophet further added, &quot;My two companions (angels) said to me, &apos;This place is the Eden Paradise, and that is your place.&apos; I raised up my sight, and behold, there I saw a palace like a white cloud! My two companions said to me, &apos;That (palace) is your place.&apos; I said to them, &apos;May Allah bless you both! Let me enter it.&apos; They replied, &apos;As for now, you will not enter it, but you shall enter it (one day) I said to them, &apos;I have seen many wonders tonight. What does all that mean which I have seen?&apos; They replied, &apos;We will inform you: As for the first man you came upon whose head was being injured with the rock, he is the symbol of the one who studies the Quran and then neither recites it nor acts on its orders, and sleeps, neglecting the enjoined prayers. As for the man you came upon whose sides of mouth, nostrils and eyes were torn off from front to back, he is the symbol of the man who goes out of his house in the morning and tells so many lies that it spreads all over the world. And those naked men and women whom you saw in a construction resembling an oven, they are the adulterers and the adulteresses;, and the man whom you saw swimming in the river and given a stone to swallow, is the eater of usury (Riba) and the bad looking man whom you saw near the fire kindling it and going round it, is Malik, the gatekeeper of Hell and the tall man whom you saw in the garden, is Abraham and the children around him are those children who die with Al-Fitra (the Islamic Faith).&quot; The narrator added: Some Muslims asked the Prophet, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! What about the children of pagans?&quot; The Prophet replied, &quot;And also the children of pagans.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;My two companions added, &apos;The men you saw half handsome and half ugly were those persons who had mixed an act that was good with another that was bad, but Allah forgave them.&apos;&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="8" verse="345" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>3.818862</score>
      <text>Narrated Abu Dhar:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;While I was at Mecca the roof of my house was opened and Gabriel descended, opened my chest, and washed it with Zam-zam water. Then he brought a golden tray full of wisdom and faith and having poured its contents into my chest, he closed it. Then he took my hand and ascended with me to the nearest heaven, when I reached the nearest heaven, Gabriel said to the gatekeeper of the heaven, &apos;Open (the gate).&apos; The gatekeeper asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel answered: &apos;Gabriel.&apos; He asked, &apos;Is there anyone with you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Yes, Muhammad I is with me.&apos; He asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Yes.&apos; So the gate was opened and we went over the nearest heaven and there we saw a man sitting with some people on his right and some on his left. When he looked towards his right, he laughed and when he looked toward his left he wept. Then he said, &apos;Welcome! O pious Prophet and pious son.&apos; I asked Gabriel, &apos;Who is he?&apos; He replied, &apos;He is Adam and the people on his right and left are the souls of his offspring. Those on his right are the people of Paradise and those on his left are the people of Hell and when he looks towards his right he laughs and when he looks towards his left he weeps.&apos;
Then he ascended with me till he reached the second heaven and he (Gabriel) said to its gatekeeper, &apos;Open (the gate).&apos; The gatekeeper said to him the same as the gatekeeper of the first heaven had said and he opened the gate. Anas said: &quot;Abu Dhar added that the Prophet met Adam, Idris, Moses, Jesus and Abraham, he (Abu Dhar) did not mention on which heaven they were but he mentioned that he (the Prophet ) met Adarn on the nearest heaven and Abraham on the sixth heaven. Anas said, &quot;When Gabriel along with the Prophet passed by Idris, the latter said, &apos;Welcome! O pious Prophet and pious brother.&apos; The Prophet asked, &apos;Who is he?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;He is Idris.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;I passed by Moses and he said, &apos;Welcome! O pious Prophet and pious brother.&apos; I asked Gabriel, &apos;Who is he?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;He is Moses.&apos; Then I passed by Jesus and he said, &apos;Welcome! O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; I asked, &apos;Who is he?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;He is Jesus.
Then I passed by Abraham and he said, &apos;Welcome! O pious Prophet and pious son.&apos; I asked Gabriel, &apos;Who is he?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;He is Abraham. The Prophet added, &apos;Then Gabriel ascended with me to a place where I heard the creaking of the pens.&quot; Ibn Hazm and Anas bin Malik said: The Prophet said, &quot;Then Allah enjoined fifty prayers on my followers when I returned with this order of Allah, I passed by Moses who asked me, &apos;What has Allah enjoined on your followers?&apos; I replied, &apos;He has enjoined fifty prayers on them.&apos; Moses said, &apos;Go back to your Lord (and appeal for reduction) for your followers will not be able to bear it.&apos; (So I went back to Allah and requested for reduction) and He reduced it to half. When I passed by Moses again and informed him about it, he said, &apos;Go back to your Lord as your followers will not be able to bear it.&apos; So I returned to Allah and requested for further reduction and half of it was reduced. I again passed by Moses and he said to me: &apos;Return to your Lord, for your followers will not be able to bear it. So I returned to Allah and He said, &apos;These are five prayers and they are all (equal to) fifty (in reward) for My Word does not change.&apos; I returned to Moses and he told me to go back once again. I replied, &apos;Now I feel shy of asking my Lord again.&apos; Then Gabriel took me till we &apos;&apos; reached Sidrat-il-Muntaha (Lote tree of; the utmost boundry) which was shrouded in colors, indescribable. Then I was admitted into Paradise where I found small (tents or) walls (made) of pearls and its earth was of musk.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="8" verse="384" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>8.836393</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim:
Hammam bin Al-Harith said, &quot;I saw Jarir bin &apos;Abdullah urinating. Then he performed ablution and passed his (wet) hands over his Khuffs, stood up and prayed. He was asked about it. He replied that he had seen the Prophet doing the same.&quot; They approved of this narration as Jarir was one of those who embraced Islam very late.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="8" verse="389" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>4.7255564</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Amr bin Dmar:
I asked Ibn &apos;Umar, &quot;Can a person who has performed the Tawaf around the Ka&apos;ba for &apos;Umra but has not performed the (Sa&apos;i) Tawaf of Safa and Marwa, have a sexual relation with his wife?&quot; Ibn &apos;Umar replied &quot;When the Prophet reached Mecca he performed the Tawaf around the Ka&apos;ba (circumambulated it seven times) and offered a two-Rak&apos;at prayer (at the place) behind the station (of Abraham) and then performed the Tawaf (Sa&apos;i) of Safa and Marwa, and verily in Allah&apos;s Apostle you have a good example.&quot; Then we put the same question to Jabir bin &apos;Abdullah and he too replied, &quot;He should not go near his wife (for sexual relation) till he has finished the Tawaf of Safa and Marwa.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="8" verse="394" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>4.30604</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Abdullah:
The Prophet prayed (and the subnarrator Ibrahim said, &quot;I do not know whether he prayed more or less than usual&quot;), and when he had finished the prayers he was asked, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Has there been any change in the prayers?&quot; He said, &quot;What is it?&apos; The people said, &quot;You have prayed so much and so much.&quot; So the Prophet bent his legs, faced the Qibla and performed two prostrations (of Sahu) and finished his prayers with Tasiim (by turning his face to right and left saying: &apos;As-Salamu&apos;Alaikum-Warahmat-ullah&apos;). When he turned his face to us he said, &quot;If there had been anything changed in the prayer, surely I would have informed you but I am a human being like you and liable to forget like you. So if I forget remind me and if anyone of you is doubtful about his prayer, he should follow what he thinks to be correct and complete his prayer accordingly and finish it and do two prostrations (of Sahu).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="8" verse="395" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>6.3141127</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Umar (bin Al-Khattab):
My Lord agreed with me in three things:
1. I said,&quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle, I wish we took the station of Abraham as our praying place (for some of our prayers). So came the Divine Inspiration: And take you (people) the station of Abraham as a place of prayer (for some of your prayers e.g. two Rakat of Tawaf of Ka&apos;ba)&quot;. (2.125)
2. And as regards the (verse of) the veiling of the women, I said, &apos;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! I wish you ordered your wives to cover themselves from the men because good and bad ones talk to them.&apos; So the verse of the veiling of the women was revealed.
3. Once the wives of the Prophet made a united front against the Prophet and I said to them, &apos;It may be if he (the Prophet) divorced you, (all) that his Lord (Allah) will give him instead of you wives better than you.&apos; So this verse (the same as I had said) was revealed.&quot; (66.5).</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="92" verse="403" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>3.302637</score>
      <text>Narrated Ibrahim At Tamii&apos;s father:
Ali addressed us while he was standing on a brick pulpit and carrying a sword from which was hanging a scroll He said &quot;By Allah, we have no book to read except Allah&apos;s Book and whatever is on this scroll,&quot; And then he unrolled it, and behold, in it was written what sort of camels were to be given as blood money, and there was also written in it: &apos;Medina is a sanctuary form &apos;Air (mountain) to such and such place so whoever innovates in it an heresy or commits a sin therein, he will incur the curse of Allah, the angles, and all the people and Allah will not accept his compulsory or optional good deeds.&apos; There was also written in it: &apos;The asylum (pledge of protection) granted by any Muslims is one and the same, (even a Muslim of the lowest status is to be secured and respected by all the other Muslims, and whoever betrays a Muslim in this respect (by violating the pledge) will incur the curse of Allah, the angels, and all the people, and Allah will not accept his compulsory or optional good deeds.&apos; There was also written in it: &apos;Whoever (freed slave) befriends (takes as masters) other than his real masters (manumitters) without their permission will incur the curse of Allah, the angels, and all the people, and Allah will not accept his compulsory or optional good deeds. &apos; (See Hadith No. 94, Vol. 3)</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="92" verse="433" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>8.478792</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
The Mountain of Uhud came in sight of Allah&apos;s Apostle who then said, &quot;This is a mountain that loves us and is loved by us. O Allah! Abraham made Mecca a sanctuary and I make the area between its (Medina&apos;s) two mountains a sanctuary.&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="92" verse="459" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>8.836393</score>
      <text>Narrated Jubair bin Mutim:
A lady came to Allah&apos;s Apostle and she talked to him about something, and he gave her some order. She said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! If I should not find you?&quot; He said, &quot;If you should not find me, then go to Abu Bakr.&quot; Ibrahim bin Sa&apos;d said, &quot;As if she meant the death (of the Prophet).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="507" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>1.9132786</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah will gather the believers on the Day of Resurrection in the same way (as they are gathered in this life), and they will say, &apos;Let us ask someone to intercede for us with our Lord that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; Then they will go to Adam and say, &apos;O Adam! Don&apos;t you see the people (people&apos;s condition)? Allah created you with His Own Hands and ordered His angels to prostrate before you, and taught you the names of all the things. Please intercede for us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; Adam will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking&apos; and mention to them the mistakes he had committed, and add, &quot;But you d better go to Noah as he was the first Apostle sent by Allah to the people of the Earth.&apos; They will go to Noah who will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and mention the mistake which he made, and add, &apos;But you&apos;d better go to Abraham, Khalil Ar-Rahman.&apos;
They will go to Abraham who will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and mention to them the mistakes he made, and add, &apos;But you&apos;d better go to Moses, a slave whom Allah gave the Torah and to whom He spoke directly&apos; They will go to Moses who will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and mention to them the mistakes he made, and add, &apos;You&apos;d better go to Jesus, Allah&apos;s slave and His Apostle and His Word (Be: And it was) and a soul created by Him.&apos; They will go to Jesus who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking, but you&apos;d better go to Muhammad whose sins of the past and the future had been forgiven (by Allah).&apos; So they will come to me and I will ask the permission of my Lord, and I will be permitted (to present myself) before Him. When I see my Lord, I will fall down in (prostration) before Him and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then it will be said to me, &apos;O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will then raise my head and praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit whom I will admit into Paradise.
I will come back again, and when I see my Lord (again), I will fall down in prostration before Him, and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then He will say, &apos;O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will then praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit to whom I will admit into Paradise, I will return again, and when I see my Lord, I will fall down (in prostration) and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then He will say, &apos;O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will then praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit to whom I will admit into Paradise. I will come back and say, &apos;O my Lord! None remains in Hell (Fire) but those whom Qur&apos;an has imprisoned therein and for whom eternity in Hell (Fire) has become inevitable.&apos; &quot;
The Prophet added, &quot;There will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: &apos;La ilaha illal-lah,&apos; and has in his heart good equal to the weight of a barley grain. Then there will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: &apos; La ilaha illal-lah,&apos; and has in his heart good equal to the weight of a wheat grain. Then there will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: &apos;La ilaha illal-lah,&apos; and has in his heart good equal to the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant).&quot;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="532" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0.8419399</score>
      <text>Narrated &apos;Ata&apos; bin Yazid Al-Laithi:
On the authority of Abu Huraira: The people said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?&quot; The Prophet said, &quot;Do you have any difficulty in seeing the moon on a full moon night?&quot; They said, &quot;No, O Allah&apos;s Apostle.&quot; He said, &quot;Do you have any difficulty in seeing the sun when there are no clouds?&quot; They said, &quot;No, O Allah&apos;s Apostle.&quot; He said, &quot;So you will see Him, like that. Allah will gather all the people on the Day of Resurrection, and say, &apos;Whoever worshipped something (in the world) should follow (that thing),&apos; so, whoever worshipped the sun will follow the sun, and whoever worshiped the moon will follow the moon, and whoever used to worship certain (other false) deities, he will follow those deities. And there will remain only this nation with its good people (or its hypocrites). (The sub-narrator, Ibrahim is in doubt.) Allah will come to them and say, &apos;I am your Lord.&apos; They will (deny Him and) say, &apos;We will stay here till our Lord comes, for when our Lord comes, we will recognize Him.&apos; So Allah will come to them in His appearance which they know, and will say, &apos;I am your Lord.&apos; They will say, &apos;You are our Lord,&apos; so they will follow Him.
Then a bridge will be laid across Hell (Fire)&apos; I and my followers will be the first ones to go across it and none will speak on that Day except the Apostles. And the invocation of the Apostles on that Day will be, &apos;O Allah, save! Save!&apos; In Hell (or over The Bridge) there will be hooks like the thorns of As-Sa&apos;dan (thorny plant). Have you seen As-Sa&apos;dan? &quot; They replied, &quot;Yes, O Allah&apos;s Apostle!&quot; He said, &quot;So those hooks look like the thorns of As-Sa&apos;dan, but none knows how big they are except Allah. Those hooks will snap the people away according to their deeds. Some of the people will stay in Hell (be destroyed) because of their (evil) deeds, and some will be cut or torn by the hooks (and fall into Hell) and some will be punished and then relieved. When Allah has finished His Judgments among the people, He will take whomever He will out of Hell through His Mercy. He will then order the angels to take out of the Fire all those who used to worship none but Allah from among those whom Allah wanted to be merciful to and those who testified (in the world) that none has the right to be worshipped but Allah. The angels will recognize them in the Fire by the marks of prostration (on their foreheads), for the Fire will eat up all the human body except the mark caused by prostration as Allah has forbidden the Fire to eat the mark of prostration. They will come out of the (Hell) Fire, completely burnt and then the water of life will be poured over them and they will grow under it as does a seed that comes in the mud of the torrent.
Then Allah will finish the judgments among the people, and there will remain one man facing the (Hell) Fire and he will be the last person among the people of Hell to enter Paradise. He will say, &apos;O my Lord! Please turn my face away from the fire because its air has hurt me and its severe heat has burnt me.&apos; So he will invoke Allah in the way Allah will wish him to invoke, and then Allah will say to him, &apos;If I grant you that, will you then ask for anything else?&apos; He will reply, &apos;No, by Your Power, (Honor) I will not ask You for anything else.&apos; He will give his Lord whatever promises and covenants Allah will demand.
So Allah will turn his face away from Hell (Fire). When he will face Paradise and will see it, he will remain quiet for as long as Allah will wish him to remain quiet, then he will say, &apos;O my Lord! Bring me near to the gate of Paradise.&apos; Allah will say to him, &apos;Didn&apos;t you give your promises and covenants that you would never ask for anything more than what you had been given? Woe on you, O Adam&apos;s son! How treacherous you are!&apos; He will say, &apos;O my lord,&apos; and will keep on invoking Allah till He says to him, &apos;If I give what you are asking, will you then ask for anything else?&apos; He will reply, &apos;No, by Your (Honor) Power, I will not ask for anything else.&apos;
Then he will give covenants and promises to Allah and then Allah will bring him near to the gate of Paradise. When he stands at the gate of Paradise, Paradise will be opened and spread before him, and he will see its splendor and pleasures whereupon he will remain quiet as long as Allah will wish him to remain quiet, and then he will say, O my Lord! Admit me into Paradise.&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Didn&apos;t you give your covenants and promises that you would not ask for anything more than what you had been given?&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Woe on you, O Adam&apos;s son! How treacherous you are! &apos;
The man will say, &apos;O my Lord! Do not make me the most miserable of Your creation,&apos; and he will keep on invoking Allah till Allah will laugh because of his sayings, and when Allah will laugh because of him, He will say to him, &apos;Enter Paradise,&apos; and when he will enter it, Allah will say to him, &apos;Wish for anything.&apos; So he will ask his Lord, and he will wish for a great number of things, for Allah Himself will remind him to wish for certain things by saying, &apos;(Wish for) so-and-so.&apos; When there is nothing more to wish for, Allah will say, &apos;This is for you, and its equal (is for you) as well.&quot;
&apos;Ata&apos; bin Yazid added: Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri who was present with Abu Huraira, did not deny whatever the latter said, but when Abu Huraira said that Allah had said, &quot;That is for you and its equal as well,&quot; Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri said, &quot;And ten times as much, O Abu Huraira!&quot; Abu Huraira said, &quot;I do not remember, except his saying, &apos;That is for you and its equal as well.&apos;&quot; Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri then said, &quot;I testify that I remember the Prophet saying, &apos;That is for you, and ten times as much.&apos; &apos; Abu Huraira then added, &quot;That man will be the last person of the people of Paradise to enter Paradise.&quot;
Narrated Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri:
We said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?&quot; He said, &quot;Do you have any difficulty in seeing the sun and the moon when the sky is clear?&quot; We said, &quot;No.&quot; He said, &quot;So you will have no difficulty in seeing your Lord on that Day as you have no difficulty in seeing the sun and the moon (in a clear sky).&quot; The Prophet then said, &quot;Somebody will then announce, &apos;Let every nation follow what they used to worship.&apos; So the companions of the cross will go with their cross, and the idolators (will go) with their idols, and the companions of every god (false deities) (will go) with their god, till there remain those who used to worship Allah, both the obedient ones and the mischievous ones, and some of the people of the Scripture. Then Hell will be presented to them as if it were a mirage. Then it will be said to the Jews, &quot;What did you use to worship?&apos; They will reply, &apos;We used to worship Ezra, the son of Allah.&apos; It will be said to them, &apos;You are liars, for Allah has neither a wife nor a son. What do you want (now)?&apos; They will reply, &apos;We want You to provide us with water.&apos; Then it will be said to them &apos;Drink,&apos; and they will fall down in Hell (instead). Then it will be said to the Christians, &apos;What did you use to worship?&apos;
They will reply, &apos;We used to worship Messiah, the son of Allah.&apos; It will be said, &apos;You are liars, for Allah has neither a wife nor a son. What: do you want (now)?&apos; They will say, &apos;We want You to provide us with water.&apos; It will be said to them, &apos;Drink,&apos; and they will fall down in Hell (instead). When there remain only those who used to worship Allah (Alone), both the obedient ones and the mischievous ones, it will be said to them, &apos;What keeps you here when all the people have gone?&apos; They will say, &apos;We parted with them (in the world) when we were in greater need of them than we are today, we heard the call of one proclaiming, &apos;Let every nation follow what they used to worship,&apos; and now we are waiting for our Lord.&apos; Then the Almighty will come to them in a shape other than the one which they saw the first time, and He will say, &apos;I am your Lord,&apos; and they will say, &apos;You are not our Lord.&apos; And none will speak: to Him then but the Prophets, and then it will be said to them, &apos;Do you know any sign by which you can recognize Him?&apos; They will say. &apos;The Shin,&apos; and so Allah will then uncover His Shin whereupon every believer will prostrate before Him and there will remain those who used to prostrate before Him just for showing off and for gaining good reputation. These people will try to prostrate but their backs will be rigid like one piece of a wood (and they will not be able to prostrate). Then the bridge will be laid across Hell.&quot; We, the companions of the Prophet said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! What is the bridge?&apos;
He said, &quot;It is a slippery (bridge) on which there are clamps and (Hooks like) a thorny seed that is wide at one side and narrow at the other and has thorns with bent ends. Such a thorny seed is found in Najd and is called As-Sa&apos;dan. Some of the believers will cross the bridge as quickly as the wink of an eye, some others as quick as lightning, a strong wind, fast horses or she-camels. So some will be safe without any harm; some will be safe after receiving some scratches, and some will fall down into Hell (Fire). The last person will cross by being dragged (over the bridge).&quot; The Prophet said, &quot;You (Muslims) cannot be more pressing in claiming from me a right that has been clearly proved to be yours than the believers in interceding with Almighty for their (Muslim) brothers on that Day, when they see themselves safe.
They will say, &apos;O Allah! (Save) our brothers (for they) used to pray with us, fast with us and also do good deeds with us.&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of one (gold) Dinar.&apos; Allah will forbid the Fire to burn the faces of those sinners. They will go to them and find some of them in Hell (Fire) up to their feet, and some up to the middle of their legs. So they will take out those whom they will recognize and then they will return, and Allah will say (to them), &apos;Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of one half Dinar.&apos; They will take out whomever they will recognize and return, and then Allah will say, &apos;Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant), and so they will take out all those whom they will recognize.&quot; Abu Sa&apos;id said: If you do not believe me then read the Holy Verse:--
&apos;Surely! Allah wrongs not even of the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant) but if there is any good (done) He doubles it.&apos; (4.40) The Prophet added, &quot;Then the prophets and Angels and the believers will intercede, and (last of all) the Almighty (Allah) will say, &apos;Now remains My Intercession. He will then hold a handful of the Fire from which He will take out some people whose bodies have been burnt, and they will be thrown into a river at the entrance of Paradise, called the water of life.
They will grow on its banks, as a seed carried by the torrent grows. You have noticed how it grows beside a rock or beside a tree, and how the side facing the sun is usually green while the side facing the shade is white. Those people will come out (of the River of Life) like pearls, and they will have (golden) necklaces, and then they will enter Paradise whereupon the people of Paradise will say, &apos;These are the people emancipated by the Beneficent. He has admitted them into Paradise without them having done any good deeds and without sending forth any good (for themselves).&apos; Then it will be said to them, &apos;For you is what you have seen and its equivalent as well.&apos;&quot;
Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, &quot;The believers will be kept (waiting) on the Day of Resurrection so long that they will become worried and say, &quot;Let us ask somebody to intercede far us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from our place.
Then they will go to Adam and say, &apos;You are Adam, the father of the people. Allah created you with His Own Hand and made you reside in His Paradise and ordered His angels to prostrate before you, and taught you the names of all things will you intercede for us with your Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours? Adam will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking.&apos; He will mention his mistakes he had committed, i.e., his eating off the tree though he had been forbidden to do so. He will add, &apos;Go to Noah, the first prophet sent by Allah to the people of the Earth.&apos; The people will go to Noah who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking&apos; He will mention his mistake which he had done, i.e., his asking his Lord without knowledge.&apos; He will say (to them), &apos;Go to Abraham, Khalil Ar-Rahman.&apos; They will go to Abraham who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking. He would mention three words by which he told a lie, and say (to them). &apos;Go to Moses, a slave whom Allah gave the Torah and spoke to, directly and brought near Him, for conversation.&apos;
They will go to Moses who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking. He will mention his mistake he made, i.e., killing a person, and will say (to them), &apos;Go to Jesus, Allah&apos;s slave and His Apostle, and a soul created by Him and His Word.&apos; (Be: And it was.) They will go to Jesus who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking but you&apos;d better go to Muhammad the slave whose past and future sins have been forgiven by Allah.&apos; So they will come to me, and I will ask my Lord&apos;s permission to enter His House and then I will be permitted. When I see Him I will fall down in prostration before Him, and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He will, and then He will say, &apos;O Muhammad, lift up your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask (for anything) for it will be granted:&apos; Then I will raise my head and glorify my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me. Allah will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people) I will take them out and make them enter Paradise.&quot; (Qatada said: I heard Anas saying that), the Prophet said, &quot;I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, and then I will return and ask my Lord for permission to enter His House and I will be permitted.
When I will see Him I will fall down in prostration before Him and He will leave me in prostration as long as He will let me (in that state), and then He will say, &apos;O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask, your request will be granted.&apos; &quot; The Prophet added, &quot;So I will raise my head and glorify and praise Him as He has taught me. Then I will intercede and He will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people). I will take them out and let them enter Paradise.&quot; (Qatada added: I heard Anas saying that) the Prophet said, &apos;I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, and I will return for the third time and will ask my Lord for permission to enter His house, and I will be allowed to enter.
When I see Him, I will fall down in prostration before Him, and will remain in prostration as long as He will, and then He will say, &apos;Raise your head, O Muhammad, and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask, for your request will be granted.&apos; So I will raise my head and praise Allah as He has taught me and then I will intercede and He will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people). I will take them out and let them enter Paradise.&quot; (Qatada said: I heard Anas saying that) the Prophet said, &quot;So I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, till none will remain in the Fire except those whom Quran will imprison (i.e., those who are destined for eternal life in the fire).&quot; The narrator then recited the Verse:-- &quot;It may be that your Lord will raise you to a Station of Praise and Glory.&apos; (17.79) The narrator added: This is the Station of Praise and Glory which Allah has promised to your Prophet.</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="601" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>1.6503582</score>
      <text>Narrated Ma&apos;bad bin Hilal Al&apos;Anzi:
We, i.e., some people from Basra gathered and went to Anas bin Malik, and we went in company with Thabit Al-Bunnani so that he might ask him about the Hadith of Intercession on our behalf. Behold, Anas was in his palace, and our arrival coincided with his Duha prayer. We asked permission to enter and he admitted us while he was sitting on his bed. We said to Thabit, &quot;Do not ask him about anything else first but the Hadith of Intercession.&quot; He said, &quot;O Abu Hamza! There are your brethren from Basra coming to ask you about the Hadith of Intercession.&quot; Anas then said, &quot;Muhammad talked to us saying, &apos;On the Day of Resurrection the people will surge with each other like waves, and then they will come to Adam and say, &apos;Please intercede for us with your Lord.&apos; He will say, &apos;I am not fit for that but you&apos;d better go to Abraham as he is the Khalil of the Beneficent.&apos; They will go to Abraham and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for that, but you&apos;d better go to Moses as he is the one to whom Allah spoke directly.&apos; So they will go to Moses and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for that, but you&apos;d better go to Jesus as he is a soul created by Allah and His Word.&apos; (Be: And it was) they will go to Jesus and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for that, but you&apos;d better go to Muhammad.&apos;
They would come to me and I would say, &apos;I am for that.&apos; Then I will ask for my Lord&apos;s permission, and it will be given, and then He will inspire me to praise Him with such praises as I do not know now. So I will praise Him with those praises and will fall down, prostrate before Him. Then it will be said, &apos;O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for your will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will say, &apos;O Lord, my followers! My followers!&apos; And then it will be said, &apos;Go and take out of Hell (Fire) all those who have faith in their hearts, equal to the weight of a barley grain.&apos; I will go and do so and return to praise Him with the same praises, and fall down (prostrate) before Him. Then it will be said, &apos;O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will say, &apos;O Lord, my followers! My followers!&apos; It will be said, &apos;Go and take out of it all those who have faith in their hearts equal to the weight of a small ant or a mustard seed.&apos; I will go and do so and return to praise Him with the same praises, and fall down in prostration before Him. It will be said, &apos;O, Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will say, &apos;O Lord, my followers!&apos; Then He will say, &apos;Go and take out (all those) in whose hearts there is faith even to the lightest, lightest mustard seed. (Take them) out of the Fire.&apos; I will go and do so.&quot;&apos;
When we left Anas, I said to some of my companions, &quot;Let&apos;s pass by Al-Hasan who is hiding himself in the house of Abi Khalifa and request him to tell us what Anas bin Malik has told us.&quot; So we went to him and we greeted him and he admitted us. We said to him, &quot;O Abu Said! We came to you from your brother Anas Bin Malik and he related to us a Hadith about the intercession the like of which I have never heard.&quot; He said, &quot;What is that?&quot; Then we told him of the Hadith and said, &quot;He stopped at this point (of the Hadith).&quot; He said, &quot;What then?&quot; We said, &quot;He did not add anything to that.&quot; He said, Anas related the Hadith to me twenty years ago when he was a young fellow. I don&apos;t know whether he forgot or if he did not like to let you depend on what he might have said.&quot; We said, &quot;O Abu Said ! Let us know that.&quot; He smiled and said, &quot;Man was created hasty. I did not mention that, but that I wanted to inform you of it.
Anas told me the same as he told you and said that the Prophet added, &apos;I then return for a fourth time and praise Him similarly and prostrate before Him me the same as he &apos;O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for you will be granted (your request): and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted .&apos; I will say, &apos;O Lord, allow me to intercede for whoever said, &apos;None has the right to be worshiped except Allah.&apos; Then Allah will say, &apos;By my Power, and my Majesty, and by My Supremacy, and by My Greatness, I will take out of Hell (Fire) whoever said: &apos;None has the right to be worshipped except Allah.&apos; &apos;&apos;</text>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="608" author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0.63071537</score>
      <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
The night Allah&apos;s Apostle was taken for a journey from the sacred mosque (of Mecca) Al-Ka&apos;ba: Three persons came to him (in a dreamy while he was sleeping in the Sacred Mosque before the Divine Inspiration was revealed to Him. One of them said, &quot;Which of them is he?&quot; The middle (second) angel said, &quot;He is the best of them.&quot; The last (third) angle said, &quot;Take the best of them.&quot; Only that much happened on that night and he did not see them till they came on another night, i.e. after The Divine Inspiration was revealed to him. (Fateh-Al-Bari Page 258, Vol. 17) and he saw them, his eyes were asleep but his heart was not----and so is the case with the prophets: their eyes sleep while their hearts do not sleep. So those angels did not talk to him till they carried him and placed him beside the well of Zam-Zam. From among them Gabriel took charge of him. Gabriel cut open (the part of his body) between his throat and the middle of his chest (heart) and took all the material out of his chest and abdomen and then washed it with Zam-Zam water with his own hands till he cleansed the inside of his body, and then a gold tray containing a gold bowl full of belief and wisdom was brought and then Gabriel stuffed his chest and throat blood vessels with it and then closed it (the chest). He then ascended with him to the heaven of the world and knocked on one of its doors.
The dwellers of the Heaven asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; He said, &quot;Gabriel.&quot; They said, &quot;Who is accompanying you?&quot; He said, &quot;Muhammad.&quot; They said, &quot;Has he been called?&quot; He said, &quot;Yes&quot; They said, &quot;He is welcomed.&quot; So the dwellers of the Heaven became pleased with his arrival, and they did not know what Allah would do to the Prophet on earth unless Allah informed them. The Prophet met Adam over the nearest Heaven. Gabriel said to the Prophet, &quot;He is your father; greet him.&quot; The Prophet greeted him and Adam returned his greeting and said, &quot;Welcome, O my Son! O what a good son you are!&quot; Behold, he saw two flowing rivers, while he was in the nearest sky. He asked, &quot;What are these two rivers, O Gabriel?&quot; Gabriel said, &quot;These are the sources of the Nile and the Euphrates.&quot;
Then Gabriel took him around that Heaven and behold, he saw another river at the bank of which there was a palace built of pearls and emerald. He put his hand into the river and found its mud like musk Adhfar. He asked, &quot;What is this, O Gabriel?&quot; Gabriel said, &quot;This is the Kauthar which your Lord has kept for you.&quot; Then Gabriel ascended (with him) to the second Heaven and the angels asked the same questions as those on the first Heaven, i.e., &quot;Who is it?&quot; Gabriel replied, &quot;Gabriel&quot;. They asked, &quot;Who is accompanying you?&quot; He said, &quot;Muhammad.&quot; They asked, &quot;Has he been sent for?&quot; He said, &quot;Yes.&quot; Then they said, &quot;He is welcomed.&apos;&apos; Then he (Gabriel) ascended with the Prophet to the third Heaven, and the angels said the same as the angels of the first and the second Heavens had said.
Then he ascended with him to the fourth Heaven and they said the same; and then he ascended with him to the fifth Heaven and they said the same; and then he ascended with him to the sixth Heaven and they said the same; then he ascended with him to the seventh Heaven and they said the same. On each Heaven there were prophets whose names he had mentioned and of whom I remember Idris on the second Heaven, Aaron on the fourth Heavens another prophet whose name I don&apos;t remember, on the fifth Heaven, Abraham on the sixth Heaven, and Moses on the seventh Heaven because of his privilege of talking to Allah directly. Moses said (to Allah), &quot;O Lord! I thought that none would be raised up above me.&quot;
But Gabriel ascended with him (the Prophet) for a distance above that, the distance of which only Allah knows, till he reached the Lote Tree (beyond which none may pass) and then the Irresistible, the Lord of Honor and Majesty approached and came closer till he (Gabriel) was about two bow lengths or (even) nearer. (It is said that it was Gabriel who approached and came closer to the Prophet. (Fate Al-Bari Page 263, 264, Vol. 17). Among the things which Allah revealed to him then, was: &quot;Fifty prayers were enjoined on his followers in a day and a night.&quot;
Then the Prophet descended till he met Moses, and then Moses stopped him and asked, &quot;O Muhammad ! What did your Lord en join upon you?&quot; The Prophet replied,&quot; He enjoined upon me to perform fifty prayers in a day and a night.&quot; Moses said, &quot;Your followers cannot do that; Go back so that your Lord may reduce it for you and for them.&quot; So the Prophet turned to Gabriel as if he wanted to consult him about that issue. Gabriel told him of his opinion, saying, &quot;Yes, if you wish.&quot; So Gabriel ascended with him to the Irresistible and said while he was in his place, &quot;O Lord, please lighten our burden as my followers cannot do that.&quot; So Allah deducted for him ten prayers where upon he returned to Moses who stopped him again and kept on sending him back to his Lord till the enjoined prayers were reduced to only five prayers.
Then Moses stopped him when the prayers had been reduced to five and said, &quot;O Muhammad! By Allah, I tried to persuade my nation, Bani Israel to do less than this, but they could not do it and gave it up. However, your followers are weaker in body, heart, sight and hearing, so return to your Lord so that He may lighten your burden.&quot;
The Prophet turned towards Gabriel for advice and Gabriel did not disapprove of that. So he ascended with him for the fifth time. The Prophet said, &quot;O Lord, my followers are weak in their bodies, hearts, hearing and constitution, so lighten our burden.&quot; On that the Irresistible said, &quot;O Muhammad!&quot; the Prophet replied, &quot;Labbaik and Sa&apos;daik.&quot; Allah said, &quot;The Word that comes from Me does not change, so it will be as I enjoined on you in the Mother of the Book.&quot; Allah added, &quot;Every good deed will be rewarded as ten times so it is fifty (prayers) in the Mother of the Book (in reward) but you are to perform only five (in practice).&quot;
The Prophet returned to Moses who asked, &quot;What have you done?&quot; He said, &quot;He has lightened our burden: He has given us for every good deed a tenfold reward.&quot; Moses said, &quot;By Allah! I tried to make Bani Israel observe less than that, but they gave it up. So go back to your Lord that He may lighten your burden further.&quot; Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;O Moses! By Allah, I feel shy of returning too many times to my Lord.&quot; On that Gabriel said, &quot;Descend in Allah&apos;s Name.&quot; The Prophet then woke while he was in the Sacred Mosque (at Mecca).</text>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>