<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="adam" generated="2026-02-01T00:03:25.295Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story generated from search: "adam"</title>
    <verses_count>112</verses_count>
    <translations_count>488</translations_count>
  </metadata>

  <verses>
    <verse chapter="17" verse="61">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When We asked the angels to bow before Adam, they all bowed but Iblis, who said: &quot;Can I bow before him whom You created from clay?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And recall when We ordered the angels that, “Prostrate before Adam” – so they all prostrated except Iblis; he said, “Shall I prostrate before one whom You have created from clay?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when We said to the angels, &apos;Bow yourselves to Adam&apos;; so they bowed themselves, save Iblis; he said,, &apos;Shall I bow myself unto one Thou hast created of clay?&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time We said unto the angels: prostrate youselves before Adam. So they prostrated themselves, but Iblis did not; he said: shall I prostrate myself before one whom Thou hast created of clay?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate unto Adam.&quot; They prostrated except Iblis (Satan). He said: &quot;Shall I prostrate to one whom You created from clay?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When We said to the angels, “Bow down before Adam,” they bowed down, except for Satan. He said, “Shall I bow down before someone You created from mud?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And recall when We asked the angels to prostrate themselves before Adam; all prostrated themselves except Iblis, who said: &quot;Shall I prostrate myself before him whom You created of clay?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate yourselves unto Adam.&quot; They prostrated themselves except Iblis. He said: &quot;Shall I prostrate myself to one whom You created from clay&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when We said unto the angels: Fall down prostrate before Adam and they fell prostrate all save Iblis, he said: Shall I fall prostrate before that which Thou hast created of clay?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>When We said to the angels, ‘Prostrate before Adam,’ they [all] prostrated, but not Iblis: he said, ‘Shall I prostrate before someone whom You have created from clay?’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>When We said to the angels: &apos;Prostrate yourselves before Adam&apos; they all prostrated themselves, except iblis (father of the jinn), who said: &apos;Shall I prostrate to him whom You have created from clay?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] when We said to the angles, &quot;Prostrate to Adam,&quot; and they prostrated, except for Iblees. He said, &quot;Should I prostrate to one You created from clay?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When We told the angels to prostrate before Adam, they all obeyed, except Iblis who said, &quot;Should I prostrate before one whom You have created out of clay?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when We said to the angels: Make obeisance to Adam; they made obeisance, but Iblis (did it not). He said: Shall I make obeisance to him whom Thou hast created of dust?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate yourselves before Adam,&quot; they all prostrated themselves except Iblis. He said, &quot;Am I to prostrate myself to someone You have created out of clay?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Behold! We said to the angels: &quot;Bow down unto Adam&quot;: They bowed down except Iblis: He said, &quot;Shall I bow down to one whom Thou didst create from clay?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="17" verse="70">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Indeed We have honoured the children of Adam, and carried them over land and sea, provided them with good things for their sustenance, and exalted them over many of Our creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed We have honoured the Descendants of Adam and transported them over land and sea, and gave them good things as sustenance, and made them better than most of Our creation.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We have honoured the Children of Adam and carried them on land and sea, and provided them with good things, and preferred them greatly over many of those We created.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We have honoured the Children of Adam: and We have borne them on the land and the sea, and We have provided them with clean things, and We have preferred them over many of them whom We have created with a preferment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We have honoured the Children of Adam, and We have carried them on land and sea, and have provided them with At-Taiyibat (lawful good things), and have preferred them above many of those whom We have created with a marked preference.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We have honored the Children of Adam, and carried them on land and sea, and provided them with good things, and greatly favored them over many of those We created.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Indeed, We honoured the progeny of Adam, and bore them across land and sea and provided them with good things for their sustenance, and exalted them above many of Our creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed We have honored the Children of Adam, and We have carried them on land and sea, and have provided them with At-Tayyibat, and have preferred them above many of those whom We have created with a marked preferment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Verily we have honoured the Children of Adam. We carry them on the land and the sea, and have made provision of good things for them, and have preferred them above many of those whom We created with a marked preferment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We have honoured the Children of Adam, and carried them over land and sea, and provided them with all the good things, and preferred them with a complete preference over many of those We have created.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We have honored the children of Adam and carried them on both land and sea. We have provided them with good things and greatly preferred them above much of Our creation.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We have certainly honored the children of Adam and carried them on the land and sea and provided for them of the good things and preferred them over much of what We have created, with [definite] preference.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We have honored the children of Adam, carried them on the land and the sea, given them pure sustenance and exalted them above most of My creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And surely We have honored the children of Adam, and We carry them in the land and the sea, and We have given them of the good things, and We have made them to excel by an appropriate excellence over most of those whom We have created.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We have honoured the children of Adam, and have borne them on the land and the sea, given them for sustenance things which are good and pure; and exalted them above many of Our creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We have honoured the sons of Adam; provided them with transport on land and sea; given them for sustenance things good and pure; and conferred on them special favours, above a great part of our creation.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="18" verse="50">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When We said to the angels: &quot;Bow before Adam in adoration,&quot; they all bowed but Iblis. He was one of the jinni and rebelled against his Lord&apos;s command. And yet you take him and his offspring as your friends instead of Me, even though they are your enemies. How sad a substitute for the evil-doers!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And recall when We commanded the angels that, “Prostrate before Adam” – so they all prostrated, except Iblis; he was of the jinn, he therefore rebelled against his Lord’s command; “What! You choose him and his offspring as your friends instead of Me, whereas they are your enemies?” And what an evil alternative did the unjust get.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when We said to the angels, &apos;Bow yourselves to Adam&apos;; so they bowed themselves, save Iblis; he was one of the jinn, and committed ungodliness against his Lord&apos;s command. What, and do you take him and his seed to be your friends, apart from Me, and they an enemy to you? How evil is that exchange for the evildoers!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time we said unto the angels: prostrate yourselves before Adam, and they prostrated themselves, but Iblis did not; he was of the genii; so he trespassed the commandment of his Lord. Would ye then take him and his progeny as patrons instead of Me, whereas they are unto you an enemy III is for the wrong-doers an exchange!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when We said to the angels; &quot;Prostrate to Adam.&quot; So they prostrated except Iblis (Satan). He was one of the jinns; he disobeyed the Command of his Lord. Will you then take him (Iblis) and his offspring as protectors and helpers rather than Me while they are enemies to you? What an evil is the exchange for the Zalimun (polytheists, and wrong-doers, etc).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We said to the angels, “Bow down to Adam.” So they bowed down, except for Satan. He was of the jinn, and he defied the command of his Lord. Will you take him and his offspring as lords instead of Me, when they are an enemy to you? Evil is the exchange for the wrongdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And recall when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate yourselves before Adam&quot;; all of them fell prostrate, except Iblis. He was of the jinn and so disobeyed the command of his Lord. Will you, then, take him and his progeny as your guardians rather than Me although they are your open enemies? What an evil substitute are these wrong-doers taking!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate yourselves unto Adam.&quot; So they prostrated themselves, except Iblis. He was one of the Jinn; he disobeyed the command of his Lord. Will you then take him and his offspring as protectors and helpers rather than Me while they are enemies to you What an evil is the exchange for the wrongdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (remember) when We said unto the angels: Fall prostrate before Adam, and they fell prostrate, all save Iblis. He was of the jinn, so he rebelled against his Lord&apos;s command. Will ye choose him and his seed for your protecting friends instead of Me, when they are an enemy unto you? Calamitous is the exchange for evil-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>When We said to the angels, ‘Prostrate before Adam,’ they prostrated, but not Iblis. He was one of the jinn, so he transgressed against his Lord’s command. Will you then take him and his offspring for guardians in My stead, though they are your enemies? How evil a substitute for the wrongdoers!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>When We said to the angels: &apos;Prostrate yourselves before Adam&apos; all prostrated themselves except iblis, who was one of the jinn, disobedient to the command of his Lord. Would you then take him and his descendants to be your guardians, other than Me, when they are your clear enemy? How evil is the exchange for the harmdoers!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] when We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate to Adam,&quot; and they prostrated, except for Iblees. He was of the jinn and departed from the command of his Lord. Then will you take him and his descendants as allies other than Me while they are enemies to you? Wretched it is for the wrongdoers as an exchange.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When We told the angels to prostrate before Adam they all obeyed except Iblis. He was a jinn and he sinned against the command of his Lord. Why do you (people) obey him and his offspring instead of Me, even though they are your enemies? How terrible will be the recompense that the wrong doers will receive!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when We said to the angels: Make obeisance to Adam; they made obeisance but Iblis (did it not). He was of the jinn, so he transgressed the commandment of his Lord. What! would you then take him and his offspring for friends rather than Me, and they are your enemies? Evil is (this) change for the unjust.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate yourselves before Adam,&quot; all prostrated themselves except Satan. He was one of the jinn and he disobeyed his Lord&apos;s command. Do you then take him and his offspring as protectors instead of Me, despite their enmity towards you? This is an evil exchange for the wrongdoers!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Behold! We said to the angels, &quot;Bow down to Adam&quot;: They bowed down except Iblis. He was one of the Jinns, and he broke the Command of his Lord. Will ye then take him and his progeny as protectors rather than Me? And they are enemies to you! Evil would be the exchange for the wrong-doers!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="20" verse="115">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We had commanded Adam before, but he disregarded it: We found him lacking in resolution.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And indeed before this We made a covenant with Adam, so he forgot, and We did not find its intention (in him).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We made covenant with Adam before, but he forgot, and We found in him no constancy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We covenanted with Adam aforetime, then he forgat, and We found not in him steadiness.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We made a covenant with Adam before, but he forgot, and We found on his part no firm will-power.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We covenanted with Adam before, but he forgot, and We found in him no resolve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Most certainly We had given Adam a command before, but he forgot. We found him lacking in firmness of resolution.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed We made a covenant with Adam before, but he forgot, and We found on his part no firm willpower.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And verily We made a covenant of old with Adam, but he forgot, and We found no constancy in him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We had enjoined Adam earlier; but he forgot, and We did not find any resoluteness in him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We made a covenant with Adam, but he forgot and We found in him no constancy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We had already taken a promise from Adam before, but he forgot; and We found not in him determination.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We had commanded Adam (certain matters). He forgot Our commandment and We did not find in him the determination to fulfil Our commandments.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We gave a commandment to Adam before, but he forgot; and We did not find in him any determination.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We made a covenant with Adam before you, but he forgot, and We found him lacking in constancy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We had already, beforehand, taken the covenant of Adam, but he forgot: and We found on his part no firm resolve.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="20" verse="116">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When We said to the angels: &apos;&apos;Bow before Adam,&apos;&apos; they all bowed but Iblis, who refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And when We commanded the angels, “Prostrate before Adam” – so they all prostrated, except Iblis; he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when We said to the angels, &apos;Bow yourselves to Adam&apos;; so they bowed themselves, save Iblis; he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time We said to the angels: prostrate yourselves before Adam. They fell prostrate, but Iblis did not; he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate yourselves to Adam.&quot; They prostrated (all) except Iblis (Satan), who refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And when We said to the angels, “Bow down to Adam.” They bowed down, except for Satan; he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Recall when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate yourselves before Adam&quot;; all prostrated themselves save Iblis. He refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate yourselves to Adam.&quot; They prostrated themselves (all) except Iblis; he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when We said unto the angels: Fall prostrate before Adam, they fell prostrate (all) save Iblis; he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>When We said to the angels, ‘Prostrate before Adam,’ they prostrated, but not Iblis: he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when We said to the angels: &apos;Prostrate yourselves before Adam&apos; they all prostrated themselves except iblis, who refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] when We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate to Adam,&quot; and they prostrated, except Iblees; he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When We told the angels to prostrate before Adam they all obeyed except Iblis (satan) who refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when We said to the angels: Make obeisance to Adam, they made obeisance, but Iblis (did it not); he refused.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate yourselves before Adam,&quot; they all prostrated themselves, except for Satan, who refused,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>When We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate yourselves to Adam&quot;, they prostrated themselves, but not Iblis: he refused.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="20" verse="117">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We said; &quot;O Adam, he is truly your enemy and your wife&apos;s. Do not let him have you turned out of Paradise and come to grief.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>We therefore said, “O Adam, he is your and your wife’s enemy, so may he not get you both out from heaven, so you then fall into hardship.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Then We said, &apos;Adam, surely this is an enemy to thee and thy wife. So let him not expel you both from the Garden, so that thou art unprosperous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then We said: Adam! verily this is an enemy unto thee and thine spouse; so let him not drive forth you twain from the Garden, lest thou be destressed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Then We said: &quot;O Adam! Verily, this is an enemy to you and to your wife. So let him not get you both out of Paradise, so that you be distressed in misery.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We said, “O Adam, this is an enemy to you and to your wife. So do not let him make you leave the Garden, for then you will suffer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Then We said: &quot;Adam! He is an enemy to you and to your wife. So let him not drive both of you out of Paradise and plunge you into affliction,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then We said: &quot;O Adam! Verily, this is an enemy to you and to your wife. So let him not get you both out of Paradise, so that you will be distressed.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Therefor we said: O Adam! This is an enemy unto thee and unto thy wife, so let him not drive you both out of the Garden so that thou come to toil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>We said, ‘O Adam! This is indeed an enemy of yours and your mate’s. So do not let him expel you from paradise, or you will be miserable.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>&apos;Adam&apos; We said, &apos;This is you and your wife&apos;s enemy. Do not let him expel you from the Garden, so that you (Adam) will be tired.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So We said, &quot;O Adam, indeed this is an enemy to you and to your wife. Then let him not remove you from Paradise so you would suffer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We said, &quot;Adam, this (satan) is your enemy and the enemy of your spouse. Let him not expel you and your spouse from Paradise lest you plunge into misery.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So We said: O Adam! This is an enemy to you and to your wife; therefore let him not drive you both forth from the garden so that you should be unhappy;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We said, &quot;Adam, [Satan] is an enemy to you and to your wife. Let him not turn you both out of Paradise and thus make you come to grief.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Then We said: &quot;O Adam! verily, this is an enemy to thee and thy wife: so let him not get you both out of the Garden, so that thou art landed in misery.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="20" verse="120">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>But then Satan tempted him by saying: &quot;O Adam, should I show you the tree of immortality, and a kingdom that will never know any wane?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So the devil incited him, saying, “O Adam, shall I show you the tree of immortality and a kingdom that does not erode?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Then Satan whispered to him saying, &apos;Adam, shall I point thee to the Tree of Eternity, and a Kingdom that decays not?&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then the Satan whispered unto him; he said: Adam! shall direct thee to the tree of eternity and a dominion that ageth not!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Then Shaitan (Satan) whispered to him, saying: &quot;O Adam! Shall I lead you to the Tree of Eternity and to a kingdom that will never waste away?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>But Satan whispered to him. He said, “O Adam, shall I show you the Tree of Immortality, and a kingdom that never decays?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>But Satan seduced him, saying: &quot;Adam! Shall I direct you to a tree of eternal life and an abiding kingdom?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then Shaytan whispered to him, saying: &quot;O Adam! Shall I lead you to the Tree of Eternity and to a kingdom that will never waste away&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>But the devil whispered to him, saying: O Adam! Shall I show thee the tree of immortality and power that wasteth not away?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Then Satan tempted him. He said, ‘O Adam! Shall I show you the tree of immortality, and an imperishable kingdom?’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But satan whispered to him saying: &apos;Adam, shall I direct you the Tree of Eternity and a kingdom which never decays&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Then Satan whispered to him; he said, &quot;O Adam, shall I direct you to the tree of eternity and possession that will not deteriorate?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Satan, trying to seduce him, said, &quot;Adam, do you want me to show you the Tree of Eternity and the Everlasting Kingdom?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>But the Shaitan made an evil suggestion to him; he said: O Adam! Shall I guide you to the tree of immortality and a kingdom which decays not?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>But Satan whispered evil to him, saying, &quot;Adam, shall I lead you to the tree of immortality and to a kingdom that never declines?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>But Satan whispered evil to him: he said, &quot;O Adam! shall I lead thee to the Tree of Eternity and to a kingdom that never decays?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="20" verse="121">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And both ate of (its fruit), and their hidden parts were exposed to one another, and they patched the leaves of the garden (to hide them). Adam disobeyed his Lord, and went astray.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So they both ate from it – thereupon their shame became manifest to them, and they started applying on themselves the leaves of heaven; and Adam lapsed in obeying his Lord, so did not reach his goal. (Of achieving immortality)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So the two of them ate of it, and their shameful parts revealed to them, and they took to stitching upon themselves leaves of the Garden. And Adam disobeyed his Lord, and so he erred.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then the twain ate thereof; so there became disclosed to them their shame, and they began sewing upon them selves some of the leaves of the Garden, so Adam disobeyed his Lord, and erred,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Then they both ate of the tree, and so their private parts appeared to them, and they began to stick on themselves the leaves from Paradise for their covering. Thus did Adam disobey his Lord, so he went astray.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And so they ate from it; whereupon their bodies became visible to them, and they started covering themselves with the leaves of the Garden. Thus Adam disobeyed his Lord, and fell.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Then the two of them ate the fruit of that tree and their shameful parts became revealed to each other, and they began to cover themselves with the leaves from the Garden. Thus Adam disobeyed his Lord and strayed into error.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then they both ate of the Tree, and so their private parts became manifest to them, and they began to cover themselves with the leaves of the Paradise for their covering. Thus Adam disobeyd his Lord, so he went astray.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Then they twain ate thereof, so that their shame became apparent unto them, and they began to hide by heaping on themselves some of the leaves of the Garden. And Adam disobeyed his Lord, so went astray.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>So they both ate of it, and their nakedness became evident to them, and they began to stitch over themselves with the leaves of paradise. Adam disobeyed his Lord, and went amiss.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>They both ate of it, and their shameful parts appeared to them, whereupon they began to stitch upon themselves leaves from the Garden. And so it was, Adam erred and disobeyed his Lord.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Adam and his wife ate of it, and their private parts became apparent to them, and they began to fasten over themselves from the leaves of Paradise. And Adam disobeyed his Lord and erred.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Adam and his wife ate (fruits) from the tree and found themselves naked. Then they started to cover themselves with the leaves from the garden. Adam disobeyed his Lord and went astray.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Then they both ate of it, so their evil inclinations became manifest to them, and they both began to cover themselves with leaves of the garden, and Adam disobeyed his Lord, so his life became evil (to him).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They both ate the fruit of this tree, and so they became conscious of their nakedness and began to cover themselves with the leaves of the Garden. Thus Adam disobeyed his Lord and fell into error.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>In the result, they both ate of the tree, and so their nakedness appeared to them: they began to sew together, for their covering, leaves from the Garden: thus did Adam disobey his Lord, and allow himself to be seduced.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="31">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Then He gave Adam knowledge of the nature and reality of all things and everything, and set them before the angels and said: &quot;Tell Me the names of these if you are truthful.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And Allah the Supreme taught Adam all the names (of things), then presented them to the angels, saying, “Tell Me the names of these, if you are truthful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And He taught Adam the names, all of them; then He presented them unto the angels and said, &apos;Now tell Me the names of these, if you speak truly.&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And He taught Adam the names, all of them; thereafter He set them before the angles, and said declare unto Me the names of those if ye say sooth.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And He taught Adam all the names (of everything), then He showed them to the angels and said, &quot;Tell Me the names of these if you are truthful.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And He taught Adam the names, all of them; then he presented them to the angels, and said, “Tell Me the names of these, if you are sincere.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Allah replied, &quot;I know what you do not know.&quot; After this he taught Adam the names of all things. Then He set these before the angels and asked, &quot;Tell Me the names of these things, if you are right (in thinking that the appointment of a vicegerent will cause disorder)&quot;.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And He taught Adam all the names (of everything), then He showed them to the angels and said, &quot;Tell Me the names of these if you are truthful.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And He taught Adam all the names, then showed them to the angels, saying: Inform Me of the names of these, if ye are truthful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And He taught Adam the Names, all of them; then presented them to the angels and said, ‘Tell me the names of these, if you are truthful.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He taught Adam (father of humans) the names all of them and then presented them to the angels, saying: &apos;Tell Me the names of these, if you are truthful&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And He taught Adam the names - all of them. Then He showed them to the angels and said, &quot;Inform Me of the names of these, if you are truthful.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>He taught Adam all the names. Then He introduced (some intelligent beings) to the angels, asking them to tell Him the names of these beings, if the angels were true to their claim (that they more deserved to be His deputies on earth).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And He taught Adam all the names, then presented them to the angels; then He said: Tell me the names of those if you are right.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>He taught Adam all the names, then He set them before the angels and said, &quot;Tell Me the names of these, if what you say be true.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And He taught Adam the names of all things; then He placed them before the angels, and said: &quot;Tell me the names of these if ye are right.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="33">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Then He said to Adam: &quot;Convey to them their names.&quot; And when he had told them, God said: &quot;Did I not tell you that I know the unknown of the heavens and the earth, and I know what you disclose and know what you hide?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He said “O Adam! Inform them the names”; and when Adam had informed them their names, He said, “Did I not tell you that I know all the secrets of the heavens and the earth? And I know all what you disclose and all what you hide?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>He said, &apos;Adam, tell them their names.&apos; And when he had told them their names He said, &apos;Did I not tell you I know the unseen things of the heavens and earth? And I know what things you reveal, and what you were hiding.&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Allah said: O Adam! declare thou unto them the names of those objects. Then when he had declared unto them the names of those, He said: said I not unto you, verily I know the hidden in the heavens and the earth, and know that which ye disclose and that which ye are wont to conceal!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He said: &quot;O Adam! Inform them of their names,&quot; and when he had informed them of their names, He said: &quot;Did I not tell you that I know the Ghaib (unseen) in the heavens and the earth, and I know what you reveal and what you have been concealing?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “O Adam, tell them their names.” And when he told them their names, He said, “Did I not tell you that I know the secrets of the heavens and the earth, and that I know what you reveal and what you conceal?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Then Allah said to Adam, &quot;Tell them the names of these things.&quot; When Adam told them the names of all those things, Allah declared, &quot;Did I not tell you that I know those truths about the Earth and the Heavens which are hidden from you? I know what you disclose and what you hide.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He said: &quot;O Adam! Inform them of their names,&quot; and when he had informed them of their names, He said: &quot;Did I not tell you that I know the Ghayb (unseen) in the heavens and the earth, and I know what you reveal and what you have been concealing&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He said: O Adam! Inform them of their names, and when he had informed them of their names, He said: Did I not tell you that I know the secret of the heavens and the earth? And I know that which ye disclose and which ye hide.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>He said, ‘O Adam, inform them of their names,’ and when he had informed them of their names, He said, ‘Did I not tell you that I know the Unseen of the heavens and the earth, and that I know whatever you disclose and whatever you conceal?’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Then He said to Adam: &apos;Tell them their names.&apos; And when Adam had named them, He said: &apos;Did I not tell you that I know the unseen of the heavens and earth, and all that you reveal and all that you hide&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>He said, &quot;O Adam, inform them of their names.&quot; And when he had informed them of their names, He said, &quot;Did I not tell you that I know the unseen [aspects] of the heavens and the earth? And I know what you reveal and what you have concealed.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The Lord said to Adam, &quot;Tell the names of the beings to the angels.&quot; When Adam said their names, the Lord said, &quot;Did I not tell you (angels) that I know the secrets of the heavens and the earth and all that you reveal or hide?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: O Adam! inform them of their names. Then when he had informed them of their names, He said: Did I not say to you that I surely know what is ghaib in the heavens and the earth and (that) I know what you manifest and what you hide?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Then He said, &quot;O Adam, tell them their names.&quot; When Adam had told them the names, God said to the angels, &quot;Did I not say to you: I know the secrets of the heavens and of the earth, and I know what you reveal and what you conceal?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He said: &quot;O Adam! Tell them their names.&quot; When he had told them, Allah said: &quot;Did I not tell you that I know the secrets of heaven and earth, and I know what ye reveal and what ye conceal?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="34">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Remember, when We asked the angels to bow in homage to Adam, they all bowed but Iblis, who disdained and turned insolent, and so became a disbeliever.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when We ordered the angels to prostrate before Adam, so they all prostrated, except Iblis (Satan – devil); he refused and was proud – and became a disbeliever.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when We said to the angels, &apos;Bow yourselves to Adam&apos;; so they bowed themselves, save Iblis; he refused, and waxed proud, and so he became one of the unbelievers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time We said unto the angels: prostrate yourselves before Adam, they prostrated themselves; but not Iblis he refused and was stiff - necked and became of the infidels.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate yourselves before Adam.&quot;. And they prostrated except Iblis (Satan), he refused and was proud and was one of the disbelievers (disobedient to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We said to the angels, “Bow down to Adam.” They bowed down, except for Satan. He refused, was arrogant, and was one of the disbelievers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Then We commanded the angels, &quot;Bow yourselves to Adam. &quot;All bowed but Iblis refused to do so; he waxed proud and joined the defiers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when We said to the angels: &quot;Prostrate yourselves before Adam.&quot; And they prostrated except Iblis (Shaytan), he refused and was proud and was one of the disbelievers (disobedient to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when We said unto the angels: Prostrate yourselves before Adam, they fell prostrate, all save Iblis. He demurred through pride, and so became a disbeliever.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And when We said to the angels, ‘Prostrate before Adam,’ they prostrated, but not Iblis: he refused and acted arrogantly, and he was one of the faithless.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when We said to the angels: &apos;Prostrate (to Me) yourselves towards Adam,&apos; they all prostrated themselves except iblis (satan, father of the jinn), who, in his pride refused and became an unbeliever.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] when We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate before Adam&quot;; so they prostrated, except for Iblees. He refused and was arrogant and became of the disbelievers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When We told the angels to prostrate before Adam, they all obeyed except Iblis (Satan) who abstained out of pride and so he became one of those who deny the truth.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when We said to the angels: Make obeisance to Adam they did obeisance, but Iblis (did it not). He refused and he was proud, and he was one of the unbelievers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When We said to the angels, &quot;Bow down before Adam,&quot; they all bowed except for Iblis [Satan]. He refused and acted proudly and became an unbeliever.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And behold, We said to the angels: &quot;Bow down to Adam&quot; and they bowed down. Not so Iblis: he refused and was haughty: He was of those who reject Faith.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="35">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We said to Adam: &quot;Both you and your spouse live in the Garden, eat freely to your fill wherever you like, but approach not this tree or you will become transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We said, “O Adam! You and your wife dwell in this Garden, and eat freely from it wherever you please – but do not approach this tree for you will become of those who transgress.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We said, &apos;Adam, dwell thou, and thy wife, in the Garden, and eat thereof easefully where you desire; but draw not nigh this tree, lest you be evildoers.&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We said: Adam! dwell thou and thine spouse in the Garden, and eat ye twain plenteously thereof as ye list, but approach not yonder tree, lest yet twain become of the wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We said: &quot;O Adam! Dwell you and your wife in the Paradise and eat both of you freely with pleasure and delight of things therein as wherever you will, but come not near this tree or you both will be of the Zalimun (wrong-doers).&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We said, “O Adam, inhabit the Garden, you and your spouse, and eat from it freely as you please, but do not approach this tree, lest you become wrongdoers.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Then We said, &quot;O Adam, you and your wife, both dwell in the Garden and eat to your hearts&apos; content where from you will, but do not go near this tree; otherwise you shall become transgressors&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We said: &quot;O Adam! Dwell you and your wife in the Paradise and eat both of you freely with pleasure and delight, of things therein wherever you will, but come not near this tree or you both will be of the Zalimin (wrongdoers). &quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We said: O Adam! Dwell thou and thy wife in the Garden, and eat ye freely (of the fruits) thereof where ye will; but come not nigh this tree lest ye become wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>We said, ‘O Adam, dwell with your mate in paradise and eat thereof freely whencesoever you wish, but do not approach this tree, lest you should be among the wrongdoers.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>To Adam We said: &apos;Dwell with your wife in Paradise and both eat of it as much as you wish and wherever you will. But neither of you should come close to this tree or else you shall both become transgressors&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We said, &quot;O Adam, dwell, you and your wife, in Paradise and eat therefrom in [ease and] abundance from wherever you will. But do not approach this tree, lest you be among the wrongdoers.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We told Adam to stay with his spouse (Eve) in the garden and enjoy the foods therein, but not to go near a certain tree lest he become one of the transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We said: O Adam! Dwell you and your wife in the garden and eat from it a plenteous (food) wherever you wish and do not approach this tree, for then you will be of the unjust.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We said, &quot;O Adam! live with your wife in Paradise and eat freely from it anywhere you may wish. Yet do not approach this tree lest you become wrongdoers.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We said: &quot;O Adam! dwell thou and thy wife in the Garden; and eat of the bountiful things therein as (where and when) ye will; but approach not this tree, or ye run into harm and transgression.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="37">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Then his Lord sent commands to Adam and turned towards him: Indeed He is compassionate and kind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Then Adam learnt from his Lord certain words (of revelation), therefore Allah accepted his repentance; indeed He only is the Most Acceptor of Repentance, the Most Merciful. (See Verse 7:23)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Thereafter Adam received certain words from his Lord, and He turned towards him; truly He turns, and is All-compassionate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then Adam learnt from his Lord certain Words, and He relented toward him, verily He! He is the Relentant, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Then Adam received from his Lord Words. And his Lord pardoned him (accepted his repentance). Verily, He is the One Who forgives (accepts repentance), the Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then Adam received words from his Lord, so He relented towards him. He is the Relenting, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>At that time Adam learnt appropriate words from his Lord and repented, and his Lord accepted his repentance, for He is very Relenting and very Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then Adam received from his Lord Words. And his Lord pardoned him (accepted his repentance). Verily, He is the One Who forgives (accepts repentance), the Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Then Adam received from his Lord words (of revelation), and He relented toward him. Lo! He is the relenting, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Then Adam received certain words from his Lord, and He turned to him clemently. Indeed He is the All-clement, the All-merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Then Adam received Words from his Lord, and his Lord relented towards him. He is the Receiver of Repentance, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Then Adam received from his Lord [some] words, and He accepted his repentance. Indeed, it is He who is the Accepting of repentance, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Adam was inspired by some words (of prayer) through which he received forgiveness from his Lord, for He is All-forgiving and All-merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Then Adam received (some) words from his Lord, so He turned to him mercifully; surely He is Oft-returning (to mercy), the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Then Adam received some words [of prayer] from his Lord and He accepted his repentance. He is the Forgiving One, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Then learnt Adam from his Lord words of inspiration, and his Lord Turned towards him; for He is Oft-Returning, Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="36" verse="60">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Did I not commit you, O children of Adam, not to worship Satan who is your acknowledged foe,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“O Descendants of Adam! Did I not take a covenant from you that you shall not worship the devil? Undoubtedly, he is your open enemy.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Made I not covenant with you, Children of Adam, that you should not serve Satan -- surely he is a manifest foe to you --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Enjoined I not on you, ye children of Adam, that ye shall not worship the Satan - verily he is Unto you manifest foe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Did I not ordain for you, O Children of Adam, that you should not worship Shaitan (Satan). Verily, he is a plain enemy to you.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Did I not covenant with you, O Children of Adam, that you shall not serve the devil? That he is your sworn enemy?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Children of Adam, did I not command you not to serve Satan -- he is to you an open enemy</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>&quot;Did I not command you, O Children of Adam, that you should not worship Shaytan Verily, he is a plain enemy to you.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Did I not charge you, O ye sons of Adam, that ye worship not the devil - Lo! he is your open foe! -</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>‘Did I not exhort you, O children of Adam, saying, “Do not worship Satan. He is indeed your manifest enemy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Children of Adam, did I not make a covenant with you, that you should not worship satan he is surely a clear enemy to you</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Did I not enjoin upon you, O children of Adam, that you not worship Satan - [for] indeed, he is to you a clear enemy -</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Children of Adam, did We not command you not to worship satan. He was your sworn enemy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Did I not charge you, O children of Adam! that you should not serve the Shaitan? Surely he is your open enemy,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Did I not enjoin you, sons of Adam, not to worship Satan -- for he is your sworn enemy,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>&quot;Did I not enjoin on you, O ye Children of Adam, that ye should not worship Satan; for that he was to you an enemy avowed?-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="33">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>God had chosen Adam and Noah and the families of Abraham and &apos;Imran in preference to others.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed Allah chose Adam, and Nooh, and the Family of Ibrahim, and the Family of Imran over the creation.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>God chose Adam and Noah and the House of Abraham and the House of Imran above all beings, the</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily did Allah choose Adam and Nuh and the house of lbrahim and the house of &apos;lmran out of the worlds</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Allah chose Adam, Nuh (Noah), the family of Ibrahim (Abraham) and the family of &apos;Imran above the &apos;Alamin (mankind and jinns) (of their times).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>God chose Adam, and Noah, and the family of Abraham, and the family of Imran, over all mankind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Truly Allah chose Adam and Noah and the descendants of Abraham and of &apos;Imran above all mankind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Allah chose Adam, Nuh (Noah), the family of Ibrahim and the family of `Imran above the nations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! Allah preferred Adam and Noah and the Family of Abraham and the Family of &apos;Imran above (all His) creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Indeed Allah chose Adam and Noah, and the progeny of Abraham and the progeny of Imran above all the nations;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Allah chose Adam and Noah, the House of Abraham and the House of Imran above all worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, Allah chose Adam and Noah and the family of Abraham and the family of &apos;Imran over the worlds -</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>God chose (and gave distinction to) Adam, Noah, the family of Abraham, and Imran over all the people of the world.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely Allah chose Adam and Nuh and the descendants of Ibrahim and the descendants of Imran above the nations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>God chose Adam and Noah and the family of Abraham and the family of &apos;Imran above all His creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Allah did choose Adam and Noah, the family of Abraham, and the family of &apos;Imran above all people,-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="11">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Verily We created you and gave you form and shape, and ordered the angels to bow before Adam in homage; and they all bowed but Iblis who was not among those who bowed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And indeed We created you, then designed you and then ordered the angels, “Prostrate before Adam”; so they all prostrated, except Iblis (Satan); he did not become of those who prostrate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We created you, then We shaped you, then We said to the angels: &apos;Bow yourselves to Adam&apos;; so they bowed themselves, save Iblis -- he was not of those that bowed themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We created you, thereafter We fashioned you, and thereafter We said to the angels: prostrate yourselves before Adam; then they fell prostrate; not so Iblis: he was not of those who fell prostrate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And surely, We created you (your father Adam) and then gave you shape (the noble shape of a human being), then We told the angels, &quot;Prostrate to Adam&quot;, and they prostrated, except Iblis (Satan), he refused to be of those who prostrate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We created you, then We shaped you, then We said to the angels, “Bow down before Adam;” so they bowed down, except for Satan; he was not of those who bowed down.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We initiated your creation, then We gave you each a shape, and then We said to the angels: &apos;Prostrate before Adam.&apos;) They all prostrated except Iblis: he was not one of those who fell Prostrate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And surely, We created you and then gave you shape; then We told the angels, &quot;Prostrate yourselves to Adam,&quot; and they prostrated, except Iblis (Shaytan), he refused to be of those who prostrated.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We created you, then fashioned you, then told the angels: Fall ye prostrate before Adam! And they fell prostrate, all save Iblis, who was not of those who make prostration.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We created you, then We formed you, then We said to the angels, ‘Prostrate before Adam.’ So they [all] prostrated, but not Iblis: he was not among those who prostrated.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We created you then We shaped you, then We said to the angels: &apos;Prostrate yourselves before Adam&apos; They all prostrated themselves except iblis he was not among the prostrated.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We have certainly created you, [O Mankind], and given you [human] form. Then We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate to Adam&quot;; so they prostrated, except for Iblees. He was not of those who prostrated.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We created and shaped you, then told the angels to prostrate themselves before Adam. All the angels obeyed except Satan who did not.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We created you, then We fashioned you, then We said to the angels: Prostrate to Adam. So they did prostrate except Iblis; he was not of those who prostrated.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We created you, then We shaped you and then We said to the angels, &quot;Prostrate yourselves before Adam,&quot; and they all prostrated themselves, except Satan. He was not among those who prostrated themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>It is We Who created you and gave you shape; then We bade the angels prostrate to Adam, and they prostrate; not so Iblis; He refused to be of those who prostrate.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="19">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And you, O Adam, and your spouse, live in the Garden and eat your fill wheresoever you like, but do not approach this tree, or you will become iniquitous.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And said, “O Adam! You and your wife dwell in Paradise – therefore eat from it from wherever you wish, and do not approach this tree for you will become of those who transgress.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>&apos;O Adam, inherit, thou and thy wife, the Garden, and eat of where you will, but come not nigh this tree, lest you be of the evildoers.&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And: O Adam: dwell thou and thy spouse in the Garden and eat ye twain thereof Whence ye will, and approach not yonder tree lest ye twain become of the wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>&quot;And O Adam! Dwell you and your wife in Paradise, and eat thereof as you both wish, but approach not this tree otherwise you both will be of the Zalimun (unjust and wrong-doers).&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And you, Adam, inhabit the Garden, you and your wife, and eat whatever you wish; but do not approach this tree, lest you become sinners.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>O Adam! Live you and your spouse in the Garden and both of you eat from it wherever you will, but never approach the tree or you shall become wrongdoers.&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>&quot;And O Adam! Dwell you and your wife in Paradise, and eat thereof as you both wish, but approach not this tree otherwise you both will be of the wrongdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (unto man): O Adam! Dwell thou and thy wife in the Garden and eat from whence ye will, but come not nigh this tree lest ye become wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>[Then He said to Adam,] ‘O Adam, dwell with your mate in paradise, and eat thereof whence you wish; but do not approach this tree, lest you should be among the wrongdoers.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>&apos;O Adam dwell with your wife in Paradise, and eat from whatever you please; but never approach this tree or you shall both become harmdoers&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And &quot;O Adam, dwell, you and your wife, in Paradise and eat from wherever you will but do not approach this tree, lest you be among the wrongdoers.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Then the Lord said, &quot;Adam, stay in the garden with your spouse and eat whatever you want therein, but do not go near this tree lest you transgress&quot;.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And (We said): O Adam! Dwell you and your wife in the garden; so eat from where you desire, but do not go near this tree, for then you will be of the unjust.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>To Adam He said, &quot;You and your wife, dwell in the Garden and eat and drink there from wherever you wish, but do not approach this tree, lest you become wrongdoers.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>&quot;O Adam! dwell thou and thy wife in the Garden, and enjoy (its good things) as ye wish: but approach not this tree, or ye run into harm and transgression.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="26">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>O sons of Adam, We have revealed to you a dress that would both hide your nakedness and be an adornment, but the raiment of piety is best. This is one of the tokens of God: You may haply reflect.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>O Descendants of Adam! We have sent down to you a garment to conceal your shame, and another garment for your elegance; and the garment of piety – that is the best; this is among the signs of Allah, so that they may remember.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Children of Adam! We have sent down on you a garment to cover your shameful parts, and feathers; and the garment of godfearing -- that is better; that is one of God&apos;s signs; haply they will remember.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>O Children of Adam! verily We have sent down unto you a garment covering your shame and as an adornment; and the garment of piety --that is the best. That is of the signss of Allah, that haply they may be admonished.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>O Children of Adam! We have bestowed raiment upon you to cover yourselves (screen your private parts, etc.) and as an adornment, and the raiment of righteousness, that is better. Such are among the Ayat (proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) of Allah, that they may remember (i.e. leave falsehood and follow truth).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>O children of Adam! We have provided you with clothing to cover your bodies, and for luxury. But the clothing of piety—that is best. These are some of God’s revelations, so that they may take heed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Indeed We have sent down to you a garment which covers your shame and provides protection and adornment. But the finest of all is the garment of piety. That is one of the signs of Allah so that they may take heed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>O Children of Adam! We have bestowed Libas (raiment) upon you to cover yourselves with, and as Rish (adornment); and the Libas (raiment) of Taqwa, that is better. Such are among the Ayat of Allah, that they may remember.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>O Children of Adam! We have revealed unto you raiment to conceal your shame, and splendid vesture, but the raiment of restraint from evil, that is best. This is of the revelations of Allah, that they may remember.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>‘O Children of Adam! We have certainly sent down to you garments to cover your nakedness, and for adornment. Yet the garment of Godwariness—that is the best.’ That is [one] of Allah’s signs, so that they may take admonition.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Children of Adam! We have sent down to you clothing that covers your nakedness, and feathers. But the clothing of piety that is better. That is one of the signs of Allah, in order that they remember.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>O children of Adam, We have bestowed upon you clothing to conceal your private parts and as adornment. But the clothing of righteousness - that is best. That is from the signs of Allah that perhaps they will remember.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Children of Adam, We have given you clothing to cover your private parts and for beauty, but the robe of piety is the best. Thus is the guidance of God so that you may take heed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>O children of Adam! We have indeed sent down to you clothing to cover your shame, and (clothing) for beauty and clothing that guards (against evil), that is the best. This is of the communications of Allah that they may be mindful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>O children of Adam! We have sent down to you clothes to cover your nakedness, and to be pleasing to the eye; but the raiment of righteousness is the best. That is one of the signs of God. So that people may take heed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>O ye Children of Adam! We have bestowed raiment upon you to cover your shame, as well as to be an adornment to you. But the raiment of righteousness,- that is the best. Such are among the Signs of Allah, that they may receive admonition!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="27">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>O sons of Adam, let not Satan beguile you as he did your parents out of Eden, and made them disrobe to expose their disgrace to them. For he and his host can see you from where you cannot see them. We have made the devils the friends of those who do not believe,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>O Descendants of Adam, beware! Do not let Satan put you in trial the way he removed your parents from Paradise and had their garments removed so that their shame become visible to them; indeed he and his tribe see you from where you do not see them; indeed We have made the devils the friends of those who do not believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Children of Adam! Let not Satan tempt you as he brought your parents out of the Garden, stripping them of their garments to show them their shameful parts. Surely he sees you, he and his tribe, from where you see them not. We have made the Satans the friends of those who do not believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>O Children of Adam! let not the Satan tempt you even as he drave forth your parents from the Garden, divesting the twain of their garment that he might discover unto the twain their shame. Verily he beholdeth you, he and his tribe, in such wise that ye behold them not. Verily We have made the Satans patrons of those only who believe not.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Let not Shaitan (Satan) deceive you, as he got your parents [Adam and Hawwa (Eve)] out of Paradise, stripping them of their raiments, to show them their private parts. Verily, he and Qabiluhu (his soldiers from the jinns or his tribe) see you from where you cannot see them. Verily, We made the Shayatin (devils) Auliya&apos; (protectors and helpers) for those who believe not.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Do not let Satan seduce you, as he drove your parents out of the Garden, stripping them of their garments, to show them their nakedness. He sees you, him and his clan, from where you cannot see them. We have made the devils friends of those who do not believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Children of Adam! Let not Satan deceive you in the manner he deceived your parents out of Paradise, pulling off from them their clothing to reveal to them their shame. He and his host surely see you from whence you do not see them. We have made satans the guardians of those who do not believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Let not Shaytan deceive you, as he got your parents out of Paradise, stripping them of their raiment, to show them their private parts. Verily, he and his tribe see you from where you cannot see them. Verily, We made the Shayatin friends of those who believe not.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Let not Satan seduce you as he caused your (first) parents to go forth from the Garden and tore off from them their robe (of innocence) that he might manifest their shame to them. Lo! he seeth you, he and his tribe, from whence ye see him not. Lo! We have made the devils protecting friends for those who believe not.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>‘O Children of Adam! Do not let Satan tempt you, like he expelled your parents from paradise, stripping them of their garments to expose to them their nakedness. Indeed he sees you—he and his hosts—whence you do not see them. We have indeed made the devils friends of those who have no faith.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Children of Adam! Do not let satan tempt you, as he brought your parents out of Paradise. He stripped them of their garments to show them their shameful parts. Indeed he and his descendants see you from where you cannot see them. We have made the satans supporters of those who do not believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>O children of Adam, let not Satan tempt you as he removed your parents from Paradise, stripping them of their clothing to show them their private parts. Indeed, he sees you, he and his tribe, from where you do not see them. Indeed, We have made the devils allies to those who do not believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Children of Adam, do not let Satan seduce you, as he caused your parents to be expelled from the garden and made them take off their clothes in order to show them their private parts. Satan and those like him see you but you do not see them. We have made the Satans as friends for those who have no faith.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>O children of Adam! let not the Shaitan cause you to fall into affliction as he expelled your parents from the garden, pulling off from them both their clothing that he might show them their evil inclinations, he surely sees you, he as well as his host, from whence you cannot see them; surely We have made the Shaitans to be the guardians of those who do not believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Children of Adam, do not let Satan seduce you, just as he turned your parents out of the Garden: he deprived them of their garment in order to make them aware of their nakedness. He and his forces watch you from where you do not see them! We have made the devils friends of those who do not believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>O ye Children of Adam! Let not Satan seduce you, in the same manner as He got your parents out of the Garden, stripping them of their raiment, to expose their shame: for he and his tribe watch you from a position where ye cannot see them: We made the evil ones friends (only) to those without faith.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="31">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>O sons of Adam, attire yourselves at every time of worship; eat and drink, but do not be wasteful, for God does not like the prodigals.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>O Descendants of Adam! Adorn yourself when you go to the mosque, and eat and drink, and do not cross limits; indeed He does not like the transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Children of Adam! Take your adornment at every place of worship; and eat and drink, but be you not prodigal; He loves not the prodigal.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>O Children of Adam! take your adornment at every worship: and eat and drink, and waste not; verily He approveth not the wasters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Take your adornment (by wearing your clean clothes), while praying and going round (the Tawaf of) the Ka&apos;bah, and eat and drink but waste not by extravagance, certainly He (Allah) likes not Al-Musrifun (those who waste by extravagance).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Dress properly at every place of worship, and eat and drink, but do not be excessive. He does not love the excessive.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Children of Adam! Take your adornment at every time of Prayer; and eat and drink without going to excesses. For Allah does not like those who go to excess.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Take your adornment to every Masjid, and eat and drink, but waste not by extravagance, certainly He (Allah) likes not the wasteful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Look to your adornment at every place of worship, and eat and drink, but be not prodigal. Lo! He loveth not the prodigals.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>O Children of Adam! Put on your adornment on every occasion of prayer, and eat and drink, but do not waste; indeed, He does not like the wasteful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Children of Adam, take your adornment at every place of prayer. Eat and drink, and do not waste. He does not love the wasteful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>O children of Adam, take your adornment at every masjid, and eat and drink, but be not excessive. Indeed, He likes not those who commit excess.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Children of Adam, dress well when attending the mosques, eat and drink but do not be excessive for God does not love those who are excessive (in what they do).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>O children of Adam! attend to your embellishments at every time of prayer, and eat and drink and be not extravagant; surely He does not love the extravagant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>O Children of Adam, dress yourself properly whenever you are at worship: and eat and drink but do not be wasteful: God does not like wasteful people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>O Children of Adam! wear your beautiful apparel at every time and place of prayer: eat and drink: But waste not by excess, for Allah loveth not the wasters.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="35">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>O sons of Adam, when apostles come to you from among you, who convey My messages, then those who take heed and amend will have neither fear nor regret.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>O Descendants of Adam! If Noble Messengers from among you come to you narrating My verses – so whoever practices piety and reforms – upon him shall be no fear nor shall he grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Children of Adam! If there should come to you Messengers from among you, relating to you My signs, then whosoever is godfearing and makes amends -- no fear shall be on them, neither shall they sorrow.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>O Children of Adam! if there come unto you apostles from amongst you recounting My signs unto you, then whosoever shall fear God and amend, on them no fear shall come nor they shall grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>O Children of Adam! If there come to you Messengers from amongst you, reciting to you, My Verses, then whosoever becomes pious and righteous, on them shall be no fear, nor shall they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>O Children of Adam! When messengers from among you come to you, relating to you My revelations—whoever practices piety and reforms—upon them shall be no fear, nor shall they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Children of Adam! If Messengers come to you from amongst yourselves who rehearse to you My signs, then those who shun disobedience and mend their ways shall have nothing to fear, nor shall they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>O Children of Adam! If there come to you Messengers from among you, reciting to you My Ayat, then whosoever has Taqwa and becomes righteous, on them shall be no fear nor shall they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>O Children of Adam! When messengers of your own come unto you who narrate unto you My revelations, then whosoever refraineth from evil and amendeth - there shall no fear come upon them neither shall they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>O Children of Adam! If there come to you apostles from among yourselves, recounting to you My signs, then those who are Godwary and righteous will have no fear, nor will they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Children of Adam, when Messengers of your own come to narrate to you My verses, those who are cautious and mend their ways will have nothing to fear neither shall they be saddened,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>O children of Adam, if there come to you messengers from among you relating to you My verses, then whoever fears Allah and reforms - there will be no fear concerning them, nor will they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Children of Adam, when Messengers from among your own people come to you to preach My revelations, those who choose piety and reform themselves will have nothing to fear nor will they be grieved.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>O children of Adam! if there come to you apostles from among you relating to you My communications, then whoever shall guard (against evil) and act aright-- they shall have no fear nor shall they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Children of Adam! If messengers come to you from among yourselves, reciting My revelations to you, then those that take warning and mend their ways, on such shall come no fear nor shall they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>O ye Children of Adam! whenever there come to you messengers from amongst you, rehearsing My signs unto you,- those who are righteous and mend (their lives),- on them shall be no fear nor shall they grieve.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="58">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>These are (some of) those who were favoured by God among the prophets of the progeny of Adam, and of those We bore in the ark with Noah, and the offspring of Abraham and Israel, and of those We guided and We chose, for they bowed weeping in adoration when the revelations of Ar-Rahman were recited to them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>It is these upon whom Allah has bestowed favour among the Prophets, from the descendants of Adam; and from those whom We boarded along with Nooh; and from the descendants of Ibrahim and Israel; and from those whom We guided and chose; when the verses of the Most Gracious were recited to them, they fell down, prostrating and weeping. (* Command of Prostration # 5.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>These are they whom God has blessed among the Prophets of the seed of Adam, and of those We bore with Noah, and of the seed of Abraham and Israel, and of those We guided and chose. When the signs of the All-merciful were recited to them, they fell down prostrate, weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>These are they whom Allah hath favoured, from among the prophets, of the progeny of Adam and of them whom We bare with Nuh, and of the progeny of Ibrahim and Isra&apos;il, and of those whom We have guided and chosen; whenever the revelations of the Compassionate were rehearsed unto them, they fell down prostrating themselves and weeping. *Chapter: 19</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Those were they unto whom Allah bestowed His Grace from among the Prophets, of the offspring of Adam, and of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Nuh (Noah), and of the offspring of Ibrahim (Abraham) and Israel and from among those whom We guided and chose. When the Verses of the Most Beneficent (Allah) were recited unto them, they fell down prostrating and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>These are some of the prophets God has blessed, from the descendants of Adam, and from those We carried with Noah, and from the descendants of Abraham and Israel, and from those We guided and selected. Whenever the revelations of the Most Gracious are recited to them, they would fall down, prostrating and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>These are the Prophets upon whom Allah bestowed His favour from the seed of Adam, and from the seed of those whom We carried (in the Ark) with Noah, and from the seed of Abraham and Israel. They were those whom We guided and chose (for an exalted position). They were such that when the words of the Most Compassionate Lord were recited to them, they fell down in prostration, weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Those were they unto whom Allah bestowed His grace from among the Prophets, of the offspring of Adam, and of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Nuh, and of the offspring of Ibrahim and Israel, and from among those whom We guided and chose. When the Ayat of the Most Gracious were recited unto them, they fell down prostrate and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>These are they unto whom Allah showed favour from among the prophets, of the seed of Adam and of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Noah, and of the seed of Abraham and Israel, and from among those whom We guided and chose. When the revelations of the Beneficent were recited unto them, they fell down, adoring and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>These are whom Allah has blessed among the Prophets from among the seed of Adam and of those whom We bore with Noah; the descendants ofAbraham, of Israel, and of those whom We have guided and chose. For when the verses of the Merciful were recited to them, they fell down prostrate, weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Those were the ones upon whom Allah bestowed favor from among the prophets of the descendants of Adam and of those We carried [in the ship] with Noah, and of the descendants of Abraham and Israel, and of those whom We guided and chose. When the verses of the Most Merciful were recited to them, they fell in prostration and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>These were the Prophets from the offspring of Adam, from those who embarked with Noah and from the offspring of Abraham and Israel. God guided them and chose them for His favor. Whenever they would hear the revelations of the Beneficent God they would bow down in prostration with tears.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>These are they on whom Allah bestowed favors, from among the prophets of the seed of Adam, and of those whom We carried with Nuh, and of the seed of Ibrahim and Israel, and of those whom We guided and chose; when the communications of the Beneficent Allah were recited to them, they fell down making obeisance and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>These are the ones whom God has favoured: the prophets from among the descendants of Adam and of those whom We carried in the Ark with Noah; the descendants of Abraham, of Israel, and of those whom We have guided and chosen. For when the revelations of the Merciful were recited to them, they fell down, prostrating themselves and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Those were some of the prophets on whom Allah did bestow His Grace,- of the posterity of Adam, and of those who We carried (in the Ark) with Noah, and of the posterity of Abraham and Israel of those whom We guided and chose. Whenever the Signs of (Allah) Most Gracious were rehearsed to them, they would fall down in prostrate adoration and in tears.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="59">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>For God the likeness of Jesus is as that of Adam whom He fashioned out of dust and said &quot;Be&quot; and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>The example of Eisa with Allah is like that of Adam; He created him (Adam) from clay and then said to him, “Be” – and it thereupon happens!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily the likeness of &apos;lsa with Allah is as the likeness of Adam: him He created out of dust, thereafter He said unto him: Be, and lo! he becometh.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, the likeness of &apos;Iesa (Jesus) before Allah is the likeness of Adam. He created him from dust, then (He) said to him: &quot;Be!&quot; - and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>The likeness of Jesus in God’s sight is that of Adam: He created him from dust, then said to him, “Be,” and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Surely, in the sight of Allah, the similitude of the creation of Jesus is as the creation of Adam whom He created out of dust, and then said: &apos;Be&apos;, and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, the likeness of `Isa before Allah is the likeness of Adam. He created him from dust, then said to him: &quot;Be!&quot; and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! the likeness of Jesus with Allah is as the likeness of Adam. He created him of dust, then He said unto him: Be! and he is.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Indeed the case of Jesus with Allah is like the case of Adam: He created him from dust, then said to him, ‘Be,’ and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Truly, the likeness of (Prophet) Jesus with Allah, is as the likeness of Adam, He created him from dust then He said to him &quot;Be&quot; and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, the example of Jesus to Allah is like that of Adam. He created Him from dust; then He said to him, &quot;Be,&quot; and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>To God the case of Jesus is as that of Adam whom He created from the earth and then said, &quot;Exist,&quot; and Adam came into existence.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely the likeness of Isa is with Allah as the likeness of Adam; He created him from dust, then said to him, Be, and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Jesus in the sight of God is like Adam. He created him from dust; then said to him, &quot;Be!&quot; and he was.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>The similitude of Jesus before Allah is as that of Adam; He created him from dust, then said to him: &quot;Be&quot;. And he was.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="172">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When your Lord brings forth from their loins the offspring of the children of Adam, He makes them witnesses over themselves, (and asks): &quot;Am I not your Lord?&quot; &apos;Indeed,&apos; they reply. &apos;We bear witness,&apos; -- lest you should say on the Day of Resurrection: &quot;We were not aware of this;&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember when your Lord brought forth the generations from the backs of the Descendants of Adam, and made them their own witness; “Am I not your Lord?”; they all said, “Yes surely You are, why not? We testify”; for you may say on the Day of Resurrection that, “We were unaware of this.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when thy Lord took from the Children of Adam, from their loins, their seed, and made them testify touching themselves, &apos;Am I not your Lord?&apos; They said, &apos;Yes, we testify&apos;-- lest you should say on the Day of Resurrection, &apos;As for us, we were heedless of this,&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time thy Lord took from the children of Adam their posterity from their backs, and made them testify as to them selves saying: am I not your lord? They said: Yea! we testify. That was lest ye should say on the Day of Resurrection verily of this we have been unaware.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when your Lord brought forth from the Children of Adam, from their loins, their seed (or from Adam&apos;s loin his offspring) and made them testify as to themselves (saying): &quot;Am I not your Lord?&quot; They said: &quot;Yes! We testify,&quot; lest you should say on the Day of Resurrection: &quot;Verily, we have been unaware of this.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And when Your Lord summoned the descendants of Adam, and made them testify about themselves. “Am I not your Lord?” They said, “Yes, we testify.” Thus you cannot say on the Day of Resurrection, “We were unaware of this.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And recall (O Prophet) when your Lord brought forth descendants from the loins of the sons of Adam, and made them witnesses against their ownselves. asking them: &apos;Am I not your Lord?&apos; They said: &apos;Yes, we do testify.&apos; We did so lest you claim on the Day of Resurrection: &apos;We were unaware of this.&apos;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when your Lord brought forth from the Children of Adam, from their loins, their seed and made them testify as to themselves (saying): &quot;Am I not your Lord&quot; They said: &quot;Yes! We testify,&quot; lest you should say on the Day of Resurrection: &quot;Verily, we were unaware of this.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (remember) when thy Lord brought forth from the Children of Adam, from their reins, their seed, and made them testify of themselves, (saying): Am I not your Lord? They said: Yea, verily. We testify. (That was) lest ye should say at the Day of Resurrection: Lo! of this we were unaware;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>When your Lord took from the Children of Adam, from their loins, their descendants and made them bear witness over themselves, [He said to them,] ‘Am I not your Lord?’ They said, ‘Yes indeed! We bear witness.’ [This,] lest you should say on the Day of Resurrection, ‘Indeed we were unaware of this,’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] when your Lord took from the children of Adam - from their loins - their descendants and made them testify of themselves, [saying to them], &quot;Am I not your Lord?&quot; They said, &quot;Yes, we have testified.&quot; [This] - lest you should say on the day of Resurrection, &quot;Indeed, we were of this unaware.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When your Lord asked all the offspring of Adam (before their birth), &quot;Am I not your Lord?&quot; All of them testified and bore witness to their testimony that on the Day of Judgment they would not say, &quot;We were not aware of this (fact),&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when your Lord brought forth from the children of Adam, from their backs, their descendants, and made them bear witness against their own souls: Am I not your Lord? They said: Yes! we bear witness. Lest you should say on the day of resurrection: Surely we were heedless of this.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When your Lord brought forth offspring from the loins of the Children of Adam and made them bear witness about themselves, He said, &quot;Am I not your Lord?&quot; They replied, &quot;We bear witness that You are.&quot; This He did, lest you should say on the Day of Resurrection, &quot;We had no knowledge of that.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>When thy Lord drew forth from the Children of Adam - from their loins - their descendants, and made them testify concerning themselves, (saying): &quot;Am I not your Lord (who cherishes and sustains you)?&quot;- They said: &quot;Yea! We do testify!&quot; (This), lest ye should say on the Day of Judgment: &quot;Of this we were never mindful&quot;:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="5" verse="27">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Narrate to them exactly the tale of the two sons of Adam. When each of them offered a sacrifice (to God), that of one was accepted, and that of the other was not. Said (the one): &quot;I will murder you,&quot; and the other replied: &quot;God only accepts from those who are upright and preserve themselves from evil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And recite to them the true tale of the two sons of Adam; when both of them offered a sacrifice each – hence the sacrifice of one was accepted and not accepted from the other; he (the other) said, “I swear I will kill you”; he answered, “Allah accepts only from the pious.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And recite thou to them the story of the two sons of Adam truthfully, when they offered a sacrifice, and it was accepted of one of them, and not accepted of the other. &apos;I will surely slay thee,&apos; said one. &apos;God accepts only of the godfearing,&apos; said the other.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And rehearse thou unto them with truth the tale of the two sons of Adam, when the twain offered an offering, and it was accepted from one of them, and was not accepted from the other; he said: surely I will slay thee. Said the other: Allah accepteth only from the God- fearing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (O Muhammad SAW) recite to them (the Jews) the story of the two sons of Adam [Habil (Abel) and Qabil (Cain)] in truth; when each offered a sacrifice (to Allah), it was accepted from the one but not from the other. The latter said to the former: &quot;I will surely kill you.&quot; The former said: &quot;Verily, Allah accepts only from those who are Al-Muttaqun (the pious - see V. 2:2).&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Narrate to them in all truth the story of the two sons of Adam. When they made an offering and it was accepted from one of them and was not accepted from the other, the latter said: &apos;I will surely kill you.&apos; Thereupon the former said: &apos;Allah accepts offerings only from the God-fearing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And recite to them the story of the two sons of Adam in truth; when each offered a sacrifice, it was accepted from the one but not from the other. The latter said to the former: &quot;I will surely, kill you.&quot; The former said: &quot;Verily, Allah accepts only from those who have Taqwa.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>But recite unto them with truth the tale of the two sons of Adam, how they offered each a sacrifice, and it was accepted from the one of them and it was not accepted from the other. (The one) said: I will surely kill thee. (The other) answered: Allah accepteth only from those who ward off (evil).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad) tell them the true story of the two sons of Adam (Abel and Cain). Each one of them offered a sacrifice. God accepted the sacrifice of one of them (Abel) but not that of the other (Cain) who then said to his brother, &quot;I shall certainly kill you.&quot; (Abel) replied, &quot;God only accepts the offerings of the pious ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And relate to them the story of the two sons of Adam with truth when they both offered an offering, but it was accepted from one of them and was not accepted from the other. He said: I will most certainly slay you. (The other) said: Allah only accepts from those who guard (against evil).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Relate to them, the true story of the two sons of Adam. When they both presented an offering, it was accepted from one of them and not from the other. The latter said, &quot;I shall kill you!&quot; The former said, &quot;God accepts [things] only from the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Recite to them the truth of the story of the two sons of Adam. Behold! they each presented a sacrifice (to Allah): It was accepted from one, but not from the other. Said the latter: &quot;Be sure I will slay thee.&quot; &quot;Surely,&quot; said the former, &quot;Allah doth accept of the sacrifice of those who are righteous.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="12">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>&quot;What prevented you&quot; (said God), &quot;from bowing (before Adam) at My bidding?&quot; &quot;I am better than him,&quot; said he. &quot;You created me from fire, and him from clay.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>(Allah) said: &quot;What prevented you (O Iblis) that you did not prostrate, when I commanded you?&quot; Iblis said: &quot;I am better than him (Adam), You created me from fire, and him You created from clay.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>(Allah) said: &quot;What prevented you (O Iblis) that you did not prostrate, when I commanded you&quot; Iblis said: &quot;I am better than him (Adam), You created me from fire, and him You created from clay.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>God asked, &quot;What made you disobey Me?&quot; Satan replied, &quot;I am better than Adam, for You have created me out of fire and Adam out of clay.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="69">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>&quot;I had no knowledge of the chiefs (angels) on high when they were disputing and discussing (about the creation of Adam).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>I had no knowledge of the exalted assembly [of angels] when they were disputing [the creation of Adam].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>I have no knowledge of the dispute among the angels (concerning their attitude towards Adam).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="28">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when your Lord said to the angels: &quot;I am going to create a man (Adam) from sounding clay of altered black smooth mud.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when your Lord said to the angels: &quot;I am going to create a man (Adam) from dried (sounding) clay of altered mud. &quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="29">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>&quot;So, when I have fashioned him completely and breathed into him (Adam) the soul which I created for him, then fall (you) down prostrating yourselves unto him.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>&quot;So, when I have fashioned him completely and breathed into him (Adam) of My spirit (the soul which I created for him,) then fall down, prostrating yourselves before him.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="53" verse="32">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Those who avoid great sins (see the Quran, Verses: 6:152, 153) and Al-Fawahish (illegal sexual intercourse, etc.) except the small faults, verily, your Lord is of vast forgiveness. He knows you well when He created you from the earth (Adam), and when you were fetuses in your mothers&apos; wombs. So ascribe not purity to yourselves. He knows best him who fears Allah and keep his duty to Him [i.e. those who are Al-Muttaqun (pious - see V. 2:2)].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Those who avoid great sins and Al-Fawahish (immoral sins) except Al-Lamam -- verily, your Lord is of vast forgiveness. He knows you well when He created you from the earth (Adam), and when you were fetuses in your mothers&apos; wombs. So, ascribe not purity to yourselves. He knows best him who has Taqwa.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="12" verse="770">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The people said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?&quot; He replied, &quot;Do you have any doubt in seeing the full moon on a clear (not cloudy) night?&quot; They replied, &quot;No, O Allah&apos;s Apostle!&quot; He said, &quot;Do you have any doubt in seeing the sun when there are no clouds?&quot; They replied in the negative. He said, &quot;You will see Allah (your Lord) in the same way. On the Day of Resurrection, people will be gathered and He will order the people to follow what they used to worship. So some of them will follow the sun, some will follow the moon, and some will follow other deities; and only this nation (Muslims) will be left with its hypocrites. Allah will come to them and say, &apos;I am Your Lord.&apos; They will say, &apos;We shall stay in this place till our Lord comes to us and when our Lord will come, we will recognize Him. Then Allah will come to them again and say, &apos;I am your Lord.&apos; They will say, &apos;You are our Lord.&apos; Allah will call them, and As-Sirat (a bridge) will be laid across Hell and I (Muhammad) shall be the first amongst the Apostles to cross it with my followers. Nobody except the Apostles will then be able to speak and they will be saying then, &apos;O Allah! Save us. O Allah Save us.&apos;
There will be hooks like the thorns of Sa&apos;dan in Hell. Have you seen the thorns of Sa&apos;dan?&quot; The people said, &quot;Yes.&quot; He said, &quot;These hooks will be like the thorns of Sa&apos;dan but nobody except Allah knows their greatness in size and these will entangle the people according to their deeds; some of them will fall and stay in Hell forever; others will receive punishment (torn into small pieces) and will get out of Hell, till when Allah intends mercy on whomever He likes amongst the people of Hell, He will order the angels to take out of Hell those who worshipped none but Him alone. The angels will take them out by recognizing them from the traces of prostrations, for Allah has forbidden the (Hell) fire to eat away those traces. So they will come out of the Fire, it will eat away from the whole of the human body except the marks of the prostrations. At that time they will come out of the Fire as mere skeletons. The Water of Life will be poured on them and as a result they will grow like the seeds growing on the bank of flowing water. Then when Allah had finished from the Judgments amongst his creations, one man will be left between Hell and Paradise and he will be the last man from the people of Hell to enter paradise. He will be facing Hell, and will say, &apos;O Allah! Turn my face from the fire as its wind has dried me and its steam has burnt me.&apos; Allah will ask him, &quot;Will you ask for anything more in case this favor is granted to you?&apos; He will say, &quot;No by Your (Honor) Power!&quot; And he will give to his Lord (Allah) what he will of the pledges and the covenants. Allah will then turn his face from the Fire. When he will face Paradise and will see its charm, he will remain quiet as long as Allah will. He then will say, &apos;O my Lord! Let me go to the gate of Paradise.&apos; Allah will ask him, &apos;Didn&apos;t you give pledges and make covenants (to the effect) that you would not ask for anything more than what you requested at first?&apos; He will say, &apos;O my Lord! Do not make me the most wretched, amongst Your creatures.&apos; Allah will say, &apos;If this request is granted, will you then ask for anything else?&apos; He will say, &apos;No! By Your Power! I shall not ask for anything else.&apos; Then he will give to his Lord what He will of the pledges and the covenants. Allah will then let him go to the gate of Paradise. On reaching then and seeing its life, charm, and pleasure, he will remain quiet as long as Allah wills and then will say, &apos;O my Lord ! Let me enter Paradise.&apos; Allah will say, May Allah be merciful unto you, O son of Adam! How treacherous you are! Haven&apos;t you made covenants and given pledges that you will not ask for anything more that what you have been given?&apos; He will say, &apos;O my Lord! Do not make me the most wretched amongst Your creatures.&apos; So Allah will laugh and allow him to enter Paradise and will ask him to request as much as he likes. He will do so till all his desires have been fulfilled . Then Allah will say, &apos;Request more of such and such things.&apos; Allah will remind him and when all his desires and wishes; have been fulfilled, Allah will say &quot;All this is granted to you and a similar amount besides.&quot; Abu Said Al-Khudri, said to Abu Huraira, &apos;Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Allah said, &apos;That is for you and ten times more like it.&apos; &quot;Abu Huraira said, &quot;I do not remember from Allah&apos;s Apostle except (his saying), &apos;All this is granted to you and a similar amount besides.&quot; Abu Sahd said, &quot;I heard him saying, &apos;That is for you and ten times more the like of it.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="30">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>All the angels prostrated before Adam</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="17" verse="62">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.ahmedraza</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He said, “Behold this* – the one whom You have honoured above me – if You give me respite till the Day of Resurrection, I will surely crush his descendants, except a few.” (* Prophet Adam.)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="18" verse="37">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>His companion said to him, during the talk with him: &quot;Do you disbelieve in Him Who created you out of dust (i.e. your father Adam), then out of Nutfah (mixed semen drops of male and female discharge), then fashioned you into a man?</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="22" verse="5">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>O mankind! If you are in doubt about the Resurrection, then verily! We have created you (i.e. Adam) from dust, then from a Nutfah (mixed drops of male and female sexual discharge i.e. offspring of Adam), then from a clot (a piece of thick coagulated blood) then from a little lump of flesh, some formed and some unformed (miscarriage), that We may make (it) clear to you (i.e. to show you Our Power and Ability to do what We will). And We cause whom We will to remain in the wombs for an appointed term, then We bring you out as infants, then (give you growth) that you may reach your age of full strength. And among you there is he who dies (young), and among you there is he who is brought back to the miserable old age, so that he knows nothing after having known. And you see the earth barren, but when We send down water (rain) on it, it is stirred (to life), it swells and puts forth every lovely kind (of growth).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="12">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We created man (Adam) out of an extract of clay (water and earth).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="13">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Thereafter We made him (the offspring of Adam) as a Nutfah (mixed drops of the male and female sexual discharge) (and lodged it) in a safe lodging (womb of the woman).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="24" verse="553">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated &apos;Abdullah bin &apos;Umar
The Prophet said, &quot;A man keeps on asking others for something till he comes on the Day of Resurrection without any piece of flesh on his face.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;On the Day of Resurrection, the Sun will come near (to, the people) to such an extent that the sweat will reach up to the middle of the ears, so, when all the people are in that state, they will ask Adam for help, and then Moses, and then Muhammad (p.b.u.h) .&quot; The sub-narrator added &quot;Muhammad will intercede with Allah to judge amongst the people. He will proceed on till he will hold the ring of the door (of Paradise) and then Allah will exalt him to Maqam Mahmud (the privilege of intercession, etc.). And all the people of the gathering will send their praises to Allah.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="198">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(But such is their adamance) that had We revealed it to one of the non-Arabs and even if he had recited (this clear Arabic discourse) to them</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="631">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Al-Qasim bin Muhammad:
&apos; Aisha said, &quot;We set out with Allah&apos;s Apostles in the months of Hajj, and (in) the nights of Hajj, and at the time and places of Hajj and in a state of Hajj. We dismounted at Sarif (a village six miles from Mecca). The Prophet then addressed his companions and said, &quot;Anyone who has not got the Hadi and likes to do Umra instead of Hajj may do so (i.e. Hajj-al-Tamattu) and anyone who has got the Hadi should not finish the Ihram after performing &apos; Umra). (i.e. Hajj-al-Qiran). Aisha added, &quot;The companions of the Prophet obeyed the above (order) and some of them (i.e. who did not have Hadi) finished their Ihram after Umra.&quot; Allah&apos;s Apostle and some of his companions were resourceful and had the Hadi with them, they could not perform Umra (alone) (but had to perform both Hajj and Umra with one Ihram). Aisha added, &quot;Allah&apos;s Apostle came to me and saw me weeping and said, &quot;What makes you weep, O Hantah?&quot; I replied, &quot;I have heard your conversation with your companions and I cannot perform the Umra.&quot; He asked, &quot;What is wrong with you?&apos; I replied, &apos; I do not offer the prayers (i.e. I have my menses).&apos; He said, &apos; It will not harm you for you are one of the daughters of Adam, and Allah has written for you (this state) as He has written it for them. Keep on with your intentions for Hajj and Allah may reward you that.&quot; Aisha further added, &quot;Then we proceeded for Hajj till we reached Mina and I became clean from my menses. Then I went out from Mina and performed Tawaf round the Ka&apos;ba.&quot; Aisha added, &quot;I went along with the Prophet in his final departure (from Hajj) till he dismounted at Al-Muhassab (a valley outside Mecca), and we too, dismounted with him.&quot; He called &apos; Abdur-Rahman bin Abu Bakr and said to him, &apos; Take your sister outside the sanctuary of Mecca and let her assume Ihram for &apos; Umra, and when you had finished &apos; Umra, return to this place and I will wait for you both till you both return to me.&apos; &quot; &apos; Aisha added, &apos; &apos; So we went out of the sanctuary of Mecca and after finishing from the &apos; Umra and the Tawaf we returned to the Prophet at dawn. He said, &apos;Have you performed the &apos; Umra?&apos; We replied in the affirmative. So he announced the departure amongst his companions and the people set out for the journey, and the Prophet: too left for Medina.&apos;&apos;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="16">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated &apos;Aisha:
We set out assuming the Ihram for Hajj in the months of Hajj towards the sacred precincts of Hajj. We dismounted at Sarif and the Prophet said to his companions, &quot;Whoever has not got the Hadi with him and likes to make it as &apos;Umra, he should do it, but he who has got the Hadi with him should not do it.&quot; The Prophet and some of his wealthy companions had the Hadi with them, so they did not finish Ihram after performing the &apos;Umra. The Prophet came to me while I was weeping. He asked me the reason for it. I replied, &quot;I have heard of what you have said to your companions and I cannot do the &apos;Umra.&quot; He asked me, &quot;What is the matter with you?&quot; I replied, &quot;I am not praying.&quot; He said, &quot;There is no harm in it as you are one of the daughters of Adam and the same is written for you as for others. So, you should perform Hajj and I hope that Allah will enable you to perform the &apos;Umra as well.&quot; So, I carried on till we departed from Mina and halted at Al-Mahassab. The Prophet called &apos;Abdur-Rahman and said, &quot;Go out of the sanctuary with your sister and let her assume Ihram for &apos;Umra, and after both of you have finished the Tawaf I will be waiting for you at this place.&quot; We came back at mid-night and the Prophet asked us, &quot;Have you finished?&quot; I replied in the affirmative. He announced the departure and the people set out for the journey and some of them had performed the Tawaf of the Ka&apos;ba before the morning prayer, and after that the Prophet set out for Medina.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="36">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Satan made Adam and his spouse err and caused them to abandon the state in which they had been living. Then We said, &quot;Descend, you are each other&apos;s enemies! The earth will be a dwelling place for you and it will provide you with sustenance for an appointed time.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="30" verse="20">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And among His Signs is this, that He created you (Adam) from dust, and then [Hawwa&apos; (Eve) from Adam&apos;s rib, and then his offspring from the semen, and], - behold you are human beings scattered!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="35" verse="11">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And Allah did create you (Adam) from dust, then from Nutfah (male and female discharge semen drops i.e. Adam&apos;s offspring), then He made you pairs (male and female). And no female conceives or gives birth, but with His Knowledge. And no aged man is granted a length of life, nor is a part cut off from his life (or another man&apos;s life), but is in a Book (AlLauh AlMahfuz) Surely, that is easy for Allah.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="73">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Then the angels, all of them, prostrated themselves before Adam</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="75">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>(Allah) said: &quot;O Iblis (Satan)! What prevents you from prostrating yourself to one whom I have created with Both My Hands. Are you too proud (to fall prostrate to Adam) or are you one of the high exalted?&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="82">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>He said, &quot;By Your Glory, I shall seduce all of them (children of Adam).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="39" verse="538">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Once the Prophet was narrating (a story), while a bedouin was sitting with him. &quot;One of the inhabitants of Paradise will ask Allah to allow him to cultivate the land. Allah will ask him, &apos;Are you not living in the pleasures you like?&apos; He will say, &apos;Yes, but I like to cultivate the land.&apos; &quot; The Prophet added, &quot;When the man (will be permitted he) will sow the seeds and the plants will grow up and get ripe, ready for reaping and so on till it will be as huge as mountains within a wink. Allah will then say to him, &apos;O son of Adam! Take here you are, gather (the yield); nothing satisfies you.&apos; &quot; On that, the bedouin said, &quot;The man must be either from Quraish (i.e. an emigrant) or an Ansari, for they are farmers, whereas we are not farmers.&quot; The Prophet smiled (at this).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="39" verse="6">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He created you (all) from a single person (Adam); then made from him his wife [Hawwa&apos; (Eve)]. And He has sent down for you of cattle eight pairs (of the sheep, two, male and female; of the goats, two, male and female; of the oxen, two, male and female; and of the camels, two, male and female). He creates you in the wombs of your mothers, creation after creation in three veils of darkness, such is Allah your Lord. His is the kingdom, La ilaha illa Huwa (none has the right to be worshipped but He). How then are you turned away?</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="40" verse="67">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He, it is Who has created you (Adam) from dust, then from a Nutfah [mixed semen drops of male and female discharge (i.e. Adam&apos;s offspring)] then from a clot (a piece of coagulated blood), then brings you forth as children, then (makes you grow) to reach the age of full strength, and afterwards to be old (men and women), though some among you die before, and that you reach an appointed term, in order that you may understand.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="1">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>O mankind! Be dutiful to your Lord, Who created you from a single person (Adam), and from him (Adam) He created his wife [Hawwa (Eve)], and from them both He created many men and women and fear Allah through Whom you demand your mutual (rights), and (do not cut the relations of) the wombs (kinship). Surely, Allah is Ever an All-Watcher over you.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="415">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Allah the Most Superior said, &quot;The son of Adam slights Me, and he should not slight Me, and he disbelieves in Me, and he ought not to do so. As for his slighting Me, it is that he says that I have a son; and his disbelief in Me is his statement that I shall not recreate him as I have created (him) before.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="429">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Malik bin Sasaa:
The Prophet said, &quot;While I was at the House in a state midway between sleep and wakefulness, (an angel recognized me) as the man lying between two men. A golden tray full of wisdom and belief was brought to me and my body was cut open from the throat to the lower part of the abdomen and then my abdomen was washed with Zam-zam water and (my heart was) filled with wisdom and belief. Al-Buraq, a white animal, smaller than a mule and bigger than a donkey was brought to me and I set out with Gabriel. When I reached the nearest heaven. Gabriel said to the heaven gate-keeper, &apos;Open the gate.&apos; The gatekeeper asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; He said, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; The gate-keeper,&apos; Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; The gate-keeper said, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Yes.&apos; Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What a wonderful visit his is!&apos; Then I met Adam and greeted him and he said, &apos;You are welcomed O son and a Prophet.&apos; Then we ascended to the second heaven. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was said, &apos;Who is with you?&apos; He said, &apos;Muhammad&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been sent for?&apos; He said, &apos;Yes.&apos; It was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What a wonderful visit his is!&quot; Then I met Jesus and Yahya (John) who said, &apos;You are welcomed, O brother and a Prophet.&apos; Then we ascended to the third heaven. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is with you? Gabriel said, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been sent for?&apos; &apos;Yes,&apos; said Gabriel. &apos;He is welcomed. What a wonderful visit his is!&apos; (The Prophet added:). There I met Joseph and greeted him, and he replied, &apos;You are welcomed, O brother and a Prophet!&apos; Then we ascended to the 4th heaven and again the same questions and answers were exchanged as in the previous heavens. There I met Idris and greeted him. He said, &apos;You are welcomed O brother and Prophet.&apos; Then we ascended to the 5th heaven and again the same questions and answers were exchanged as in previous heavens. there I met and greeted Aaron who said, &apos;You are welcomed O brother and a Prophet&quot;. Then we ascended to the 6th heaven and again the same questions and answers were exchanged as in the previous heavens. There I met and greeted Moses who said, &apos;You are welcomed O brother and. a Prophet.&apos; When I proceeded on, he started weeping and on being asked why he was weeping, he said, &apos;O Lord! Followers of this youth who was sent after me will enter Paradise in greater number than my followers.&apos; Then we ascended to the seventh heaven and again the same questions and answers were exchanged as in the previous heavens. There I met and greeted Abraham who said, &apos;You are welcomed o son and a Prophet.&apos; Then I was shown Al-Bait-al-Ma&apos;mur (i.e. Allah&apos;s House). I asked Gabriel about it and he said, This is Al Bait-ul-Ma&apos;mur where 70,000 angels perform prayers daily and when they leave they never return to it (but always a fresh batch comes into it daily).&apos; Then I was shown Sidrat-ul-Muntaha (i.e. a tree in the seventh heaven) and I saw its Nabk fruits which resembled the clay jugs of Hajr (i.e. a town in Arabia), and its leaves were like the ears of elephants, and four rivers originated at its root, two of them were apparent and two were hidden. I asked Gabriel about those rivers and he said, &apos;The two hidden rivers are in Paradise, and the apparent ones are the Nile and the Euphrates.&apos; Then fifty prayers were enjoined on me. I descended till I met Moses who asked me, &apos;What have you done?&apos; I said, &apos;Fifty prayers have been enjoined on me.&apos; He said, &apos;I know the people better than you, because I had the hardest experience to bring Bani Israel to obedience. Your followers cannot put up with such obligation. So, return to your Lord and request Him (to reduce the number of prayers.&apos; I returned and requested Allah (for reduction) and He made it forty. I returned and (met Moses) and had a similar discussion, and then returned again to Allah for reduction and He made it thirty, then twenty, then ten, and then I came to Moses who repeated the same advice. Ultimately Allah reduced it to five. When I came to Moses again, he said, &apos;What have you done?&apos; I said, &apos;Allah has made it five only.&apos; He repeated the same advice but I said that I surrendered (to Allah&apos;s Final Order)&apos;&quot; Allah&apos;s Apostle was addressed by Allah, &quot;I have decreed My Obligation and have reduced the burden on My slaves, and I shall reward a single good deed as if it were ten good deeds.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="14">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He created man (Adam) from sounding clay like the clay of pottery.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="543">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah created Adam, making him 60 cubits tall. When He created him, He said to him, &quot;Go and greet that group of angels, and listen to their reply, for it will be your greeting (salutation) and the greeting (salutations of your offspring.&quot; So, Adam said (to the angels), As-Salamu Alaikum (i.e. Peace be upon you). The angels said, &quot;As-salamu Alaika wa Rahmatu-l-lahi&quot; (i.e. Peace and Allah&apos;s Mercy be upon you). Thus the angels added to Adam&apos;s salutation the expression, &apos;Wa Rahmatu-l-lahi,&apos; Any person who will enter Paradise will resemble Adam (in appearance and figure). People have been decreasing in stature since Adam&apos;s creation.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="544">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;The first group of people who will enter Paradise, will be glittering like the full moon and those who will follow them, will glitter like the most brilliant star in the sky. They will not urinate, relieve nature, spit, or have any nasal secretions. Their combs will be of gold, and their sweat will smell like musk. The aloes-wood will be used in their centers. Their wives will be houris. All of them will look alike and will resemble their father Adam (in statute), sixty cubits tall.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="551">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah will say to that person of the (Hell) Fire who will receive the least punishment, &apos;If you had everything on the earth, would you give it as a ransom to free yourself (i.e. save yourself from this Fire)?&apos; He will say, &apos;Yes.&apos; Then Allah will say, &apos;While you were in the backbone of Adam, I asked you much less than this, i.e. not to worship others besides Me, but you insisted on worshipping others besides me.&apos; &quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="552">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abdullah:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Whenever a person is murdered unjustly, there is a share from the burden of the crime on the first son of Adam for he was the first to start the tradition of murdering.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="556">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
We were in the company of the Prophet at a banquet and a cooked (mutton) forearm was set before him, and he used to like it. He ate a morsel of it and said, &quot;I will be the chief of all the people on the Day of Resurrection. Do you know how Allah will gather all the first and the last (people) in one level place where an observer will be able to see (all) of them and they will be able to hear the announcer, and the sun will come near to them. Some People will say: Don&apos;t you see, in what condition you are and the state to which you have reached? Why don&apos;t you look for a person who can intercede for you with your Lord? Some people will say: Appeal to your father, Adam.&apos; They will go to him and say: &apos;O Adam! You are the father of all mankind, and Allah created you with His Own Hands, and ordered the angels to prostrate for you, and made you live in Paradise. Will you not intercede for us with your Lord? Don&apos;t you see in what (miserable) state we are, and to what condition we have reached?&apos; On that Adam will reply, &apos;My Lord is so angry as He has never been before and will never be in the future; (besides), He forbade me (to eat from) the tree, but I disobeyed (Him), (I am worried about) myself! Myself! Go to somebody else; go to Noah.&apos; They will go to Noah and say; &apos;O Noah! You are the first amongst the messengers of Allah to the people of the earth, and Allah named you a thankful slave. Don&apos;t you see in what a (miserable) state we are and to what condition we have reached? Will you not intercede for us with your Lord? Noah will reply: &apos;Today my Lord has become so angry as he had never been before and will never be in the future Myself! Myself! Go to the Prophet (Muhammad). The people will come to me, and I will prostrate myself underneath Allah&apos;s Throne. Then I will be addressed: &apos;O Muhammad! Raise your head; intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask (for anything). for you will be given. &quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="567">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Said Al-Khudri:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah will say (on the Day of Resurrection), &apos;O Adam.&apos; Adam will reply, &apos;Labbaik wa Sa&apos;daik&apos;, and all the good is in Your Hand.&apos; Allah will say: &apos;Bring out the people of the fire.&apos; Adam will say: &apos;O Allah! How many are the people of the Fire?&apos; Allah will reply: &apos;From every one thousand, take out nine-hundred-and ninety-nine.&apos; At that time children will become hoary headed, every pregnant female will have a miscarriage, and one will see mankind as drunken, yet they will not be drunken, but dreadful will be the Wrath of Allah.&quot; The companions of the Prophet asked, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Who is that (excepted) one?&quot; He said, &quot;Rejoice with glad tidings; one person will be from you and one-thousand will be from Gog and Magog.&quot;
The Prophet further said, &quot;By Him in Whose Hands my life is, hope that you will be one-fourth of the people of Paradise.&quot; We shouted, &quot;Allahu Akbar!&quot; He added, &quot;I hope that you will be one-third of the people of Paradise.&quot; We shouted, &quot;Allahu Akbar!&quot; He said, &quot;I hope that you will be half of the people of Paradise.&quot; We shouted, &quot;Allahu Akbar!&quot; He further said, &quot;You (Muslims) (compared with non Muslims) are like a black hair in the skin of a white ox or like a white hair in the skin of a black ox (i.e. your number is very small as compared with theirs).&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="621">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Adam and Moses argued with each other. Moses said to Adam. &apos;You are Adam whose mistake expelled you from Paradise.&apos; Adam said to him, &apos;You are Moses whom Allah selected as His Messenger and as the one to whom He spoke directly; yet you blame me for a thing which had already been written in my fate before my creation?&quot;&apos; Allah&apos;s Apostle said twice, &quot;So, Adam overpowered Moses.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="641">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Said bin Al-Musaiyab:
Abu Huraira said, &quot;I heard Allah&apos;s Apostle saying, &apos;There is none born among the off-spring of Adam, but Satan touches it. A child therefore, cries loudly at the time of birth because of the touch of Satan, except Mary and her child.&quot; Then Abu Huraira recited: &quot;And I seek refuge with You for her and for her offspring from the outcast Satan&quot; (3.36)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="56" verse="62">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed, you have already known the first form of creation (i.e. the creation of Adam), why then do you not remember or take heed?</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="227">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abbas bin Malik:
Malik bin Sasaa said that Allah&apos;s Apostle described to them his Night Journey saying, &quot;While I was lying in Al-Hatim or Al-Hijr, suddenly someone came to me and cut my body open from here to here.&quot; I asked Al-Jarud who was by my side, &quot;What does he mean?&quot; He said, &quot;It means from his throat to his pubic area,&quot; or said, &quot;From the top of the chest.&quot; The Prophet further said, &quot;He then took out my heart. Then a gold tray of Belief was brought to me and my heart was washed and was filled (with Belief) and then returned to its original place. Then a white animal which was smaller than a mule and bigger than a donkey was brought to me.&quot; (On this Al-Jarud asked, &quot;Was it the Buraq, O Abu Hamza?&quot; I (i.e. Anas) replied in the affirmative). The Prophet said, &quot;The animal&apos;s step (was so wide that it) reached the farthest point within the reach of the animal&apos;s sight. I was carried on it, and Gabriel set out with me till we reached the nearest heaven.
When he asked for the gate to be opened, it was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel answered, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has Muhammad been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!&apos; The gate was opened, and when I went over the first heaven, I saw Adam there. Gabriel said (to me). &apos;This is your father, Adam; pay him your greetings.&apos; So I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious son and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me till we reached the second heaven. Gabriel asked for the gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel answered, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel answered in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!&apos; The gate was opened.
When I went over the second heaven, there I saw Yahya (i.e. John) and &apos;Isa (i.e. Jesus) who were cousins of each other. Gabriel said (to me), &apos;These are John and Jesus; pay them your greetings.&apos; So I greeted them and both of them returned my greetings to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the third heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed, what an excellent visit his is!&apos; The gate was opened, and when I went over the third heaven there I saw Joseph. Gabriel said (to me), &apos;This is Joseph; pay him your greetings.&apos; So I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the fourth heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed, what an excel lent visit his is!&apos;
The gate was opened, and when I went over the fourth heaven, there I saw Idris. Gabriel said (to me), &apos;This is Idris; pay him your greetings.&apos; So I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the fifth heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked. &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said He is welcomed, what an excellent visit his is! So when I went over the fifth heaven, there I saw Harun (i.e. Aaron), Gabriel said, (to me). This is Aaron; pay him your greetings.&apos; I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the sixth heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked. &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. It was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!&apos;
When I went (over the sixth heaven), there I saw Moses. Gabriel said (to me),&apos; This is Moses; pay him your greeting. So I greeted him and he returned the greetings to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; When I left him (i.e. Moses) he wept. Someone asked him, &apos;What makes you weep?&apos; Moses said, &apos;I weep because after me there has been sent (as Prophet) a young man whose followers will enter Paradise in greater numbers than my followers.&apos; Then Gabriel ascended with me to the seventh heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Gabriel.&apos; It was asked,&apos; Who is accompanying you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Muhammad.&apos; It was asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, &apos;He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!&apos;
So when I went (over the seventh heaven), there I saw Abraham. Gabriel said (to me), &apos;This is your father; pay your greetings to him.&apos; So I greeted him and he returned the greetings to me and said, &apos;You are welcomed, O pious son and pious Prophet.&apos; Then I was made to ascend to Sidrat-ul-Muntaha (i.e. the Lote Tree of the utmost boundary) Behold! Its fruits were like the jars of Hajr (i.e. a place near Medina) and its leaves were as big as the ears of elephants. Gabriel said, &apos;This is the Lote Tree of the utmost boundary) . Behold ! There ran four rivers, two were hidden and two were visible, I asked, &apos;What are these two kinds of rivers, O Gabriel?&apos; He replied,&apos; As for the hidden rivers, they are two rivers in Paradise and the visible rivers are the Nile and the Euphrates.&apos;
Then Al-Bait-ul-Ma&apos;mur (i.e. the Sacred House) was shown to me and a container full of wine and another full of milk and a third full of honey were brought to me. I took the milk. Gabriel remarked, &apos;This is the Islamic religion which you and your followers are following.&apos; Then the prayers were enjoined on me: They were fifty prayers a day. When I returned, I passed by Moses who asked (me), &apos;What have you been ordered to do?&apos; I replied, &apos;I have been ordered to offer fifty prayers a day.&apos; Moses said, &apos;Your followers cannot bear fifty prayers a day, and by Allah, I have tested people before you, and I have tried my level best with Bani Israel (in vain). Go back to your Lord and ask for reduction to lessen your followers&apos; burden.&apos; So I went back, and Allah reduced ten prayers for me. Then again I came to Moses, but he repeated the same as he had said before. Then again I went back to Allah and He reduced ten more prayers. When I came back to Moses he said the same, I went back to Allah and He ordered me to observe ten prayers a day. When I came back to Moses, he repeated the same advice, so I went back to Allah and was ordered to observe five prayers a day.
When I came back to Moses, he said, &apos;What have you been ordered?&apos; I replied, &apos;I have been ordered to observe five prayers a day.&apos; He said, &apos;Your followers cannot bear five prayers a day, and no doubt, I have got an experience of the people before you, and I have tried my level best with Bani Israel, so go back to your Lord and ask for reduction to lessen your follower&apos;s burden.&apos; I said, &apos;I have requested so much of my Lord that I feel ashamed, but I am satisfied now and surrender to Allah&apos;s Order.&apos; When I left, I heard a voice saying, &apos;I have passed My Order and have lessened the burden of My Worshipers.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="236">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Some (cooked) meat was brought to Allah Apostle and the meat of a forearm was presented to him as he used to like it. He ate a morsel of it and said, &quot;I will be the chief of all the people on the Day of Resurrection. Do you know the reason for it? Allah will gather all the human being of early generations as well as late generation on one plain so that the announcer will be able to make them all-hear his voice and the watcher will be able to see all of them. The sun will come so close to the people that they will suffer such distress and trouble as they will not be able to bear or stand. Then the people will say, &apos;Don&apos;t you see to what state you have reached? Won&apos;t you look for someone who can intercede for you with your Lord&apos; Some people will say to some others, &apos;Go to Adam.&apos; So they will go to Adam and say to him. &apos;You are the father of mankind; Allah created you with His Own Hand, and breathed into you of His Spirit (meaning the spirit which he created for you); and ordered the angels to prostrate before you; so (please) intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are? Don&apos;t you see what condition we have reached?&apos; Adam will say, &apos;Today my Lord has become angry as He has never become before, nor will ever become thereafter. He forbade me (to eat of the fruit of) the tree, but I disobeyed Him . Myself! Myself! Myself! (has more need for intercession). Go to someone else; go to Noah.&apos; So they will go to Noah and say (to him), &apos;O Noah! You are the first (of Allah&apos;s Messengers) to the people of the earth, and Allah has named you a thankful slave; please intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&apos; He will say.&apos; Today my Lord has become angry as He has never become nor will ever become thereafter. I had (in the world) the right to make one definitely accepted invocation, and I made it against my nation. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Abraham.&apos; They will go to Abraham and say, &apos;O Abraham! You are Allah&apos;s Apostle and His Khalil from among the people of the earth; so please intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&apos; He will say to them, &apos;My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before, nor will ever become thereafter. I had told three lies (Abu Haiyan (the sub-narrator) mentioned them in the Hadith) Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Moses.&apos; The people will then go to Moses and say, &apos;O Moses! You art Allah&apos;s Apostle and Allah gave you superiority above the others with this message and with His direct Talk to you; (please) intercede for us with your Lord Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&apos; Moses will say, &apos;My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before, nor will become thereafter, I killed a person whom I had not been ordered to kill. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Jesus.&apos; So they will go to Jesus and say, &apos;O Jesus! You are Allah&apos;s Apostle and His Word which He sent to Mary, and a superior soul created by Him, and you talked to the people while still young in the cradle. Please intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&apos; Jesus will say. &apos;My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before nor will ever become thereafter. Jesus will not mention any sin, but will say, &apos;Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Muhammad.&apos; So they will come to me and say, &apos;O Muhammad ! You are Allah&apos;s Apostle and the last of the prophets, and Allah forgave your early and late sins. (Please) intercede for us with your Lord. Don&apos;t you see in what state we are?&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;Then I will go beneath Allah&apos;s Throne and fall in prostration before my Lord. And then Allah will guide me to such praises and glorification to Him as He has never guided anybody else before me. Then it will be said, &apos;O Muhammad Raise your head. Ask, and it will be granted. Intercede It (your intercession) will be accepted.&apos; So I will raise my head and Say, &apos;My followers, O my Lord! My followers, O my Lord&apos;. It will be said, &apos;O Muhammad! Let those of your followers who have no accounts, enter through such a gate of the gates of Paradise as lies on the right; and they will share the other gates with the people.&quot; The Prophet further said, &quot;By Him in Whose Hand my soul is, the distance between every two gate-posts of Paradise is like the distance between Mecca and Busra (in Sham).&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="260">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Adam and Moses met, and Moses said to Adam &quot;You are the one who made people miserable and turned them out of Paradise.&quot; Adam said to him, &quot;You are the one whom Allah selected for His message and whom He selected for Himself and upon whom He revealed the Torah.&quot; Moses said, &apos;Yes.&apos; Adam said, &quot;Did you find that written in my fate before my creation?&apos; Moses said, &apos;Yes.&apos; So Adam overcame Moses with this argument.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="262">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;Moses argued with Adam and said to him (Adam), &apos;You are the one who got the people out of Paradise by your sin, and thus made them miserable.&quot; Adam replied, &apos;O Moses! You are the one whom Allah selected for His Message and for His direct talk. Yet you blame me for a thing which Allah had ordained for me before He created me?.&quot; Allah&apos;s Apostle further said, &quot;So Adam overcame Moses by this Argument.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="265">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Said Al-Khudri:
The Prophet said, &quot;On the day of Resurrection Allah will say, &apos;O Adam!&apos; Adam will reply, &apos;Labbaik our Lord, and Sa&apos;daik &apos; Then there will be a loud call (saying), Allah orders you to take from among your offspring a mission for the (Hell) Fire.&apos; Adam will say, &apos;O Lord! Who are the mission for the (Hell) Fire?&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Out of each thousand, take out 999.&apos; At that time every pregnant female shall drop her load (have a miscarriage) and a child will have grey hair. And you shall see mankind as in a drunken state, yet not drunk, but severe will be the torment of Allah.&quot; (22.2) (When the Prophet mentioned this), the people were so distressed (and afraid) that their faces got changed (in color) whereupon the Prophet said, &quot;From Gog and Magog nine-hundred ninety-nine will be taken out and one from you. You Muslims (compared to the large number of other people) will be like a black hair on the side of a white ox, or a white hair on the side of a black ox, and I hope that you will be one-fourth of the people of Paradise.&quot; On that, we said, &quot;Allahu-Akbar!&quot; Then he said, &quot;I hope that you will be) one-third of the people of Paradise.&quot; We again said, &quot;Allahu-Akbar!&quot; Then he said, &quot;(I hope that you will be) one-half of the people of Paradise.&quot; So we said, Allahu Akbar.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="3">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, &quot;On the Day of Resurrection the Believers will assemble and say, &apos;Let us ask somebody to intercede for us with our Lord.&apos; So they will go to Adam and say, &apos;You are the father of all the people, and Allah created you with His Own Hands, and ordered the angels to prostrate to you, and taught you the names of all things; so please intercede for us with your Lord, so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; Adam will say, &apos;I am not fit for this (i.e. intercession for you).&apos; Then Adam will remember his sin and feel ashamed thereof. He will say, &apos;Go to Noah, for he was the first Apostle, Allah sent to the inhabitants of the earth.&apos; They will go to him and Noah will say,
&apos;I am not fit for this undertaking.&apos; He will remember his appeal to his Lord to do what he had no knowledge of, then he will feel ashamed thereof and will say, &apos;Go to the Khalil--r-Rahman (i.e. Abraham).&apos; They will go to him and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking. Go to Moses, the slave to whom Allah spoke (directly) and gave him the Torah .&apos; So they will go to him and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking.&apos; and he will mention (his) killing a person who was not a killer, and so he will feel ashamed thereof before his Lord, and he will say, &apos;Go to Jesus, Allah&apos;s Slave, His Apostle and Allah&apos;s Word and a Spirit coming from Him. Jesus will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking, go to Muhammad the Slave of Allah whose past and future sins were forgiven by Allah.&apos; So they will come to me and I will proceed till I will ask my Lord&apos;s Permission and I will be given permission. When I see my Lord, I will fall down in Prostration and He will let me remain in that state as long as He wishes and then I will be addressed.&apos; (Muhammad!) Raise your head. Ask, and your request will be granted; say, and your saying will be listened to; intercede, and your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will raise my head and praise Allah with a saying (i.e. invocation) He will teach me, and then I will intercede. He will fix a limit for me (to intercede for) whom I will admit into Paradise. Then I will come back again to Allah, and when I see my Lord, the same thing will happen to me. And then I will intercede and Allah will fix a limit for me to intercede whom I will let into Paradise, then I will come back for the third time; and then I will come back for the fourth time, and will say, &apos;None remains in Hell but those whom the Quran has imprisoned (in Hell) and who have been destined to an eternal stay in Hell.&apos; &quot; (The compiler) Abu &apos;Abdullah said: &apos;But those whom the Qur&apos;an has imprisoned in Hell,&apos; refers to the Statement of Allah:
&quot;They will dwell therein forever.&quot; (16.29)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="351">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Allah said, &apos;The son of Adam hurts me for he abuses Time though I am Time: in My Hands are all things, and I cause the revolution of day and night.&apos;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="498">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah said: &apos;The son of Adam tells a lie against Me,, though he hasn&apos;t the right to do so. He abuses me though he hasn&apos;t the right to do so. As for his telling a lie against Me, it is his saying that I will not recreate him as I created him for the first time. In fact, the first creation was not easier for Me than new creation. As for his abusing Me, it is his saying that Allah has begotten children, while I am the One, the Self-Sufficient Master Whom all creatures need, I beget not, nor was I begotten, and there is none like unto Me.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="499">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Allah said:-- &apos;The son of Adam tells a lie against Me and he hasn&apos;t the right to do so; and he abuses me and he hasn&apos;t the right to do so. His telling a lie against Me is his saying that I will not recreate him as I created him for the first time; and his abusing Me is his saying that Allah has begotten children, while I am the self-sufficient Master, Whom all creatures need, Who begets not nor was He begotten, and there is none like unto Me.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="9">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah said, &apos;The son of Adam tells a lie against me though he has no right to do so, and he abuses Me though he has no right to do so. As for his telling a lie against Me, it is that he claims that I cannot recreate him as I created him before; and as for his abusing Me, it is his statement that I have offspring. No! Glorified be Me! I am far from taking a wife or offspring.&apos; &quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="63" verse="208">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Adam:
Shu&apos;ba relate the same Hadith and added: Barira was given the option regarding her husband</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="64" verse="264">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Allah said, &apos;O son of Adam! Spend, and I shall spend on you.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="68" verse="456">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated &apos;Aisha:
that the Prophet entered upon her when she had her menses at Sarif before entering Mecca, and she was weeping (because she was afraid that she would not be able to perform the Hajj). The Prophet said, &quot;What is wrong with you? Have you got your period?&quot; She said, &quot;Yes.&quot; He said, &quot;This is a matter Allah has decreed for all the daughters of Adam, so perform all the ceremonies of Hajj like the others, but do not perform the Tawaf around the Ka&apos;ba.&quot; &apos;Aisha added: When we were at Mina, beef was brought to me and I asked, &quot;What is this?&quot; They (the people) said, &quot;Allah&apos;s Apostle has slaughtered some cows as sacrifices on behalf of his wives.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="68" verse="466">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated &apos;Aisha:
Allah&apos;s Apostle entered upon me at Sarif while I was weeping (because I was afraid that I would not be able to perform the ,Hajj). He said, &quot;What is wrong with you? Have you got your period?&quot; I replied, &quot;Yes.&quot; He said, &quot;This is a matter Allah has decreed for all the daughters of Adam, so perform the ceremonies of the Hajj as the pilgrims do, but do not perform the Tawaf around the Ka&apos;ba.&quot; Allah&apos;s Apostle slaughtered some cows as sacrifices on behalf of his wives.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="293">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Al-Qasim:
&apos;Aisha said, &quot;We set out with the sole intention of performing Hajj and when we reached Sarif, (a place six miles from Mecca) I got my menses. Allah&apos;s Apostle came to me while I was weeping. He said &apos;What is the matter with you? Have you got your menses?&apos; I replied, &apos;Yes.&apos; He said, &apos;This is a thing which Allah has ordained for the daughters of Adam. So do what all the pilgrims do with the exception of the Taw-af (Circumambulation) round the Ka&apos;ba.&quot; &apos;Aisha added, &quot;Allah&apos;s Apostle sacrificed cows on behalf of his wives.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="302">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated &apos;Aisha:
We set out with the Prophet for Hajj and when we reached Sarif I got my menses. When the Prophet came to me, I was weeping. He asked, &quot;Why are you weeping?&quot; I said, &quot;I wish if I had not performed Hajj this year.&quot; He asked, &quot;May be that you got your menses?&quot; I replied, &quot;Yes.&quot; He then said, &quot;This is the thing which Allah has ordained for all the daughters of Adam. So do what all the pilgrims do except that you do not perform the Tawaf round the Ka&apos;ba till you are clean.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="98">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>It is He Who has created you from a single person (Adam), and has given you a place of residing (on the earth or in your mother&apos;s wombs) and a place of storage [in the earth (in your graves) or in your father&apos;s loins]. Indeed, We have explained in detail Our revelations (this Quran) for people who understand.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="73" verse="200">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Allah said, &quot;The offspring of Adam abuse the Dahr (Time), and I am the Dahr; in My Hands are the night and the day.&quot; !</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="74" verse="246">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah created Adam in his complete shape and form (directly), sixty cubits (about 30 meters) in height. When He created him, He said (to him), &quot;Go and greet that group of angels sitting there, and listen what they will say in reply to you, for that will be your greeting and the greeting of your offspring.&quot; Adam (went and) said, &apos;As-Salamu alaikum (Peace be upon you).&apos; They replied, &apos;AsSalamu-&apos;Alaika wa Rahmatullah (Peace and Allah&apos;s Mercy be on you) So they increased &apos;Wa Rahmatullah&apos; The Prophet added &apos;So whoever will enter Paradise, will be of the shape and form of Adam. Since then the creation of Adam&apos;s (offspring) (i.e. stature of human beings is being diminished continuously) to the present time.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="430">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;The son of Adam (i.e. man) grows old and so also two (desires) grow old with him, i.e., love for wealth and (a wish for) a long life.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="444">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn &apos;Abbas:
I heard the Prophet saying, &quot;If the son of Adam (the human being) had two valley of money, he would wish for a third, for nothing can fill the belly of Adam&apos;s son except dust, and Allah forgives him who repents to Him.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="445">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn &apos;Abbas:
I heard Allah&apos;s Apostle saying, &quot;If the son of Adam had money equal to a valley, then he will wish for another similar to it, for nothing can satisfy the eye of Adam&apos;s son except dust. And Allah forgives him who repents to Him.&quot; Ibn &apos;Abbas said: I do not know whether this saying was quoted from the Qur&apos;an or not. &apos;Ata&apos; said, &quot;I heard Ibn AzZubair saying this narration while he was on the pulpit.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="446">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa&apos;d:
I heard Ibn Az-Zubair who was on the pulpit at Mecca, delivering a sermon, saying, &quot;O men! The Prophet used to say, &quot;If the son of Adam were given a valley full of gold, he would love to have a second one; and if he were given the second one, he would love to have a third, for nothing fills the belly of Adam&apos;s son except dust. And Allah forgives he who repents to Him.&quot; Ubai said, &quot;We considered this as a saying from the Qur&apos;an till the Sura (beginning with) &apos;The mutual rivalry for piling up of worldly things diverts you..&apos; (102.1) was revealed.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="536">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;The first man to be called on the Day of Resurrection will be Adam who will be shown his offspring, and it will be said to them, &apos;This is your father, Adam.&apos; Adam will say (responding to the call), &apos;Labbaik and Sa&apos;daik&apos; Then Allah will say (to Adam), &apos;Take out of your offspring, the people of Hell.&apos; Adam will say, &apos;O Lord, how many should I take out?&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Take out ninety-nine out of every hundred.&quot; They (the Prophet&apos;s companions) said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! If ninety-nine out of every one hundred of us are taken away, what will remain out of us?&quot; He said, &quot;My followers in comparison to the other nations are like a white hair on a black ox.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="537">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Said:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah will say, &apos;O Adam!. Adam will reply, &apos;Labbaik and Sa&apos;daik (I respond to Your Calls, I am obedient to Your orders), wal Khair fi Yadaik (and all the good is in Your Hands)!&apos; Then Allah will say (to Adam), Bring out the people of the Fire.&apos; Adam will say, &apos;What (how many) are the people of the Fire?&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Out of every thousand (take out) nine-hundred and ninety-nine (persons).&apos; At that time children will become hoary-headed and every pregnant female will drop her load (have an abortion) and you will see the people as if they were drunk, yet not drunk; But Allah&apos;s punishment will be very severe.&quot;
That news distressed the companions of the Prophet too much, and they said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Who amongst us will be that man (the lucky one out of one-thousand who will be saved from the Fire)?&quot; He said, &quot;Have the good news that one-thousand will be from Gog and Magog, and the one (to be saved will be) from you.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;By Him in Whose Hand my soul is, I Hope that you (Muslims) will be one third of the people of Paradise.&quot; On that, we glorified and praised Allah and said, &quot;Allahu Akbar.&quot; The Prophet then said, &quot;By Him in Whose Hand my soul is, I hope that you will be one half of the people of Paradise, as your (Muslims) example in comparison to the other people (non-Muslims), is like that of a white hair on the skin of a black ox, or a round hairless spot on the foreleg of a donkey.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="562">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah will say to the person who will have the minimum punishment in the Fire on the Day of Resurrection, &apos;If you had things equal to whatever is on the earth, would you ransom yourself (from the punishment) with it?&apos; He will reply, Yes. Allah will say, &apos;I asked you a much easier thing than this while you were in the backbone of Adam, that is, not to worship others besides Me, but you refused and insisted to worship others besides Me.&quot;&apos;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="570">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;Allah will gather all the people on the Day of Resurrection and they will say, &apos;Let us request someone to intercede for us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; Then they will go to Adam and say, &apos;You are the one whom Allah created with His Own Hands, and breathed in you of His soul, and ordered the angels to prostrate to you; so please intercede for us with our Lord.&apos; Adam will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking, and will remember his sin, and will say, &apos;Go to Noah, the first Apostle sent by Allah&apos; They will go to him and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking&apos;, and will remember his sin and say, &apos;Go to Abraham whom Allah took as a Khalil. They will go to him (and request similarly). He will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and will remember his sin and say, &apos;Go to Moses to whom Allah spoke directly.&apos; They will go to Moses and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and will remember his sin and say, &apos;Go to Jesus.&apos; They will go to him, and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking, go to Muhammad as Allah has forgiven his past and future sins.&apos; They will come to me and I will ask my Lord&apos;s permission, and when I see Him, I will fall down in prostration to Him, and He will leave me in that state as long as (He) Allah will, and then I will be addressed. &apos;Raise up your head (O Muhammad)! Ask, and your request will be granted, and say, and your saying will be listened to; intercede, and your intercession will be accepted.&apos; Then I will raise my head, and I will glorify and praise my Lord with a saying(i.e. invocation) He will teach me, and then I will intercede, Allah will fix a limit for me (i.e., certain type of people for whom I may intercede), and I will take them out of the (Hell) Fire and let them enter Paradise. Then I will come back (to Allah) and fall in prostration, and will do the same for the third and fourth times till no-one remains in the (Hell) Fire except those whom the Qur&apos;an has imprisoned therein.&quot; (The sub-narrator, Qatada used to say at that point, &quot;...those upon whom eternity (in Hell) has been imposed.&quot;) (See Hadith No. 3, Vol 6).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="577">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Some people said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?&quot; He said, &quot;Do you crowd and squeeze each other on looking at the sun when it is not hidden by clouds?&quot; They replied, &quot;No, Allah&apos;s Apostle.&quot; He said, &quot;Do you crowd and squeeze each other on looking at the moon when it is full and not hidden by clouds?&quot; They replied, No, O Allah&apos;s Apostle!&quot; He said, &quot;So you will see Him (your Lord) on the Day of Resurrection similarly Allah will gather all the people and say, &apos;Whoever used to worship anything should follow that thing. &apos;So, he who used to worship the sun, will follow it, and he who used to worship the moon will follow it, and he who used to worship false deities will follow them; and then only this nation (i.e., Muslims) will remain, including their hypocrites. Allah will come to them in a shape other than they know and will say, &apos;I am your Lord.&apos; They will say, &apos;We seek refuge with Allah from you. This is our place; (we will not follow you) till our Lord comes to us, and when our Lord comes to us, we will recognize Him.
Then Allah will come to then in a shape they know and will say, &quot;I am your Lord.&apos; They will say, &apos;(No doubt) You are our Lord,&apos; and they will follow Him. Then a bridge will be laid over the (Hell) Fire.&quot; Allah&apos;s Apostle added, &quot;I will be the first to cross it. And the invocation of the Apostles on that Day, will be &apos;Allahukka Sallim, Sallim (O Allah, save us, save us!),&apos; and over that bridge there will be hooks Similar to the thorns of As Sa&apos;dan (a thorny tree). Didn&apos;t you see the thorns of As-Sa&apos;dan?&quot; The companions said, &quot;Yes, O Allah&apos;s Apostle.&quot; He added, &quot;So the hooks over that bridge will be like the thorns of As-Sa-dan except that their greatness in size is only known to Allah. These hooks will snatch the people according to their deeds. Some people will be ruined because of their evil deeds, and some will be cut into pieces and fall down in Hell, but will be saved afterwards, when Allah has finished the judgments among His slaves, and intends to take out of the Fire whoever He wishes to take out from among those who used to testify that none had the right to be worshipped but Allah.
We will order the angels to take them out and the angels will know them by the mark of the traces of prostration (on their foreheads) for Allah banned the f ire to consume the traces of prostration on the body of Adam&apos;s son. So they will take them out, and by then they would have burnt (as coal), and then water, called Maul Hayat (water of life) will be poured on them, and they will spring out like a seed springs out on the bank of a rainwater stream, and there will remain one man who will be facing the (Hell) Fire and will say, &apos;O Lord! It&apos;s (Hell&apos;s) vapor has Poisoned and smoked me and its flame has burnt me; please turn my face away from the Fire.&apos; He will keep on invoking Allah till Allah says, &apos;Perhaps, if I give you what you want), you will ask for another thing?&apos; The man will say, &apos;No, by Your Power, I will not ask You for anything else.&apos;
Then Allah will turn his face away from the Fire. The man will say after that, &apos;O Lord, bring me near the gate of Paradise.&apos; Allah will say (to him), &apos;Didn&apos;t you promise not to ask for anything else? Woe to you, O son of Adam ! How treacherous you are!&apos; The man will keep on invoking Allah till Allah will say, &apos;But if I give you that, you may ask me for something else.&apos; The man will say, &apos;No, by Your Power. I will not ask for anything else.&apos; He will give Allah his covenant and promise not to ask for anything else after that. So Allah will bring him near to the gate of Paradise, and when he sees what is in it, he will remain silent as long as Allah will, and then he will say, &apos;O Lord! Let me enter Paradise.&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Didn&apos;t you promise that you would not ask Me for anything other than that? Woe to you, O son of Adam ! How treacherous you are!&apos; On that, the man will say, &apos;O Lord! Do not make me the most wretched of Your creation,&apos; and will keep on invoking Allah till Allah will smile and when Allah will smile because of him, then He will allow him to enter Paradise, and when he will enter Paradise, he will be addressed, &apos;Wish from so-and-so.&apos; He will wish till all his wishes will be fulfilled, then Allah will say, All this (i.e. what you have wished for) and as much again therewith are for you.&apos; &quot;
Abu Huraira added: That man will be the last of the people of Paradise to enter (Paradise).
Narrated &apos;Ata (while Abu Huraira was narrating): Abu Said was sitting in the company of Abu Huraira and he did not deny anything of his narration till he reached his saying: &quot;All this and as much again therewith are for you.&quot; Then Abu Sa&apos;id said, &quot;I heard Allah&apos;s Apostle saying, &apos;This is for you and ten times as much.&apos; &quot; Abu Huraira said, &quot;In my memory it is &apos;as much again therewith.&apos; &quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="77" verse="606">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said (that Allah said), &quot;Vowing does not bring to the son of Adam anything I have not already written in his fate, but vowing is imposed on him by way of fore ordainment. Through vowing I make a miser spend of his wealth.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="77" verse="609">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn &apos;Abbas:
I did not see anything so resembling minor sins as what Abu Huraira said from the Prophet, who said, &quot;Allah has written for the son of Adam his inevitable share of adultery whether he is aware of it or not: The adultery of the eye is the looking (at something which is sinful to look at), and the adultery of the tongue is to utter (what it is unlawful to utter), and the innerself wishes and longs for (adultery) and the private parts turn that into reality or refrain from submitting to the temptation.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="77" verse="611">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;Adam and Moses argued with each other. Moses said to Adam. &apos;O Adam! You are our father who disappointed us and turned us out of Paradise.&apos; Then Adam said to him, &apos;O Moses! Allah favored you with His talk (talked to you directly) and He wrote (the Torah) for you with His Own Hand. Do you blame me for action which Allah had written in my fate forty years before my creation?&apos; So Adam confuted Moses, Adam confuted Moses,&quot; the Prophet added, repeating the Statement three times.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="78" verse="685">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah says, &apos;The vow, does not bring about for the son of Adam anything I have not decreed for him, but his vow may coincide with what has been decided for him, and by this way I cause a miser to spend of his wealth. So he gives Me (spends in charity) for the fulfillment of what has been decreed for him what he would not give Me before but for his vow.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="189">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>It is He Who has created you from a single person (Adam), and (then) He has created from him his wife [Hawwa (Eve)], in order that he might enjoy the pleasure of living with her. When he had sexual relation with her, she became pregnant and she carried it about lightly. Then when it became heavy, they both invoked Allah, their Lord (saying): &quot;If You give us a Salih (good in every aspect) child, we shall indeed be among the grateful.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="24">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>(Allah) said: &quot;Get down, one of you an enemy to the other [i.e. Adam, Hawwa (Eve), and Shaitan (Satan), etc.]. On earth will be a dwelling-place for you and an enjoyment, - for a time.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="83" verse="6">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated &apos;Abdullah:
The Prophet said, &quot;No human being is killed unjustly, but a part of responsibility for the crime is laid on the first son of Adam who invented the tradition of killing (murdering) on the earth. (It is said that he was Qabil).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="8" verse="345">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Dhar:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;While I was at Mecca the roof of my house was opened and Gabriel descended, opened my chest, and washed it with Zam-zam water. Then he brought a golden tray full of wisdom and faith and having poured its contents into my chest, he closed it. Then he took my hand and ascended with me to the nearest heaven, when I reached the nearest heaven, Gabriel said to the gatekeeper of the heaven, &apos;Open (the gate).&apos; The gatekeeper asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; Gabriel answered: &apos;Gabriel.&apos; He asked, &apos;Is there anyone with you?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;Yes, Muhammad I is with me.&apos; He asked, &apos;Has he been called?&apos; Gabriel said, &apos;Yes.&apos; So the gate was opened and we went over the nearest heaven and there we saw a man sitting with some people on his right and some on his left. When he looked towards his right, he laughed and when he looked toward his left he wept. Then he said, &apos;Welcome! O pious Prophet and pious son.&apos; I asked Gabriel, &apos;Who is he?&apos; He replied, &apos;He is Adam and the people on his right and left are the souls of his offspring. Those on his right are the people of Paradise and those on his left are the people of Hell and when he looks towards his right he laughs and when he looks towards his left he weeps.&apos;
Then he ascended with me till he reached the second heaven and he (Gabriel) said to its gatekeeper, &apos;Open (the gate).&apos; The gatekeeper said to him the same as the gatekeeper of the first heaven had said and he opened the gate. Anas said: &quot;Abu Dhar added that the Prophet met Adam, Idris, Moses, Jesus and Abraham, he (Abu Dhar) did not mention on which heaven they were but he mentioned that he (the Prophet ) met Adarn on the nearest heaven and Abraham on the sixth heaven. Anas said, &quot;When Gabriel along with the Prophet passed by Idris, the latter said, &apos;Welcome! O pious Prophet and pious brother.&apos; The Prophet asked, &apos;Who is he?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;He is Idris.&quot; The Prophet added, &quot;I passed by Moses and he said, &apos;Welcome! O pious Prophet and pious brother.&apos; I asked Gabriel, &apos;Who is he?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;He is Moses.&apos; Then I passed by Jesus and he said, &apos;Welcome! O pious brother and pious Prophet.&apos; I asked, &apos;Who is he?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;He is Jesus.
Then I passed by Abraham and he said, &apos;Welcome! O pious Prophet and pious son.&apos; I asked Gabriel, &apos;Who is he?&apos; Gabriel replied, &apos;He is Abraham. The Prophet added, &apos;Then Gabriel ascended with me to a place where I heard the creaking of the pens.&quot; Ibn Hazm and Anas bin Malik said: The Prophet said, &quot;Then Allah enjoined fifty prayers on my followers when I returned with this order of Allah, I passed by Moses who asked me, &apos;What has Allah enjoined on your followers?&apos; I replied, &apos;He has enjoined fifty prayers on them.&apos; Moses said, &apos;Go back to your Lord (and appeal for reduction) for your followers will not be able to bear it.&apos; (So I went back to Allah and requested for reduction) and He reduced it to half. When I passed by Moses again and informed him about it, he said, &apos;Go back to your Lord as your followers will not be able to bear it.&apos; So I returned to Allah and requested for further reduction and half of it was reduced. I again passed by Moses and he said to me: &apos;Return to your Lord, for your followers will not be able to bear it. So I returned to Allah and He said, &apos;These are five prayers and they are all (equal to) fifty (in reward) for My Word does not change.&apos; I returned to Moses and he told me to go back once again. I replied, &apos;Now I feel shy of asking my Lord again.&apos; Then Gabriel took me till we &apos;&apos; reached Sidrat-il-Muntaha (Lote tree of; the utmost boundry) which was shrouded in colors, indescribable. Then I was admitted into Paradise where I found small (tents or) walls (made) of pearls and its earth was of musk.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="90" verse="3">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And by the begetter (i.e. Adam) and that which he begot (i.e. his progeny);</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="91" verse="7">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And by Nafs (Adam or a person or a soul, etc.), and Him Who perfected him in proportion;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="92" verse="423">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated &apos;Abdullah:
The Prophet said, &quot;None is killed unjustly, but the first son of Adam will have a part of its burden.&quot; Sufyan said, &quot;..a part of its blood because he was the first to establish the tradition of murdering&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="507">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah will gather the believers on the Day of Resurrection in the same way (as they are gathered in this life), and they will say, &apos;Let us ask someone to intercede for us with our Lord that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; Then they will go to Adam and say, &apos;O Adam! Don&apos;t you see the people (people&apos;s condition)? Allah created you with His Own Hands and ordered His angels to prostrate before you, and taught you the names of all the things. Please intercede for us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; Adam will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking&apos; and mention to them the mistakes he had committed, and add, &quot;But you d better go to Noah as he was the first Apostle sent by Allah to the people of the Earth.&apos; They will go to Noah who will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and mention the mistake which he made, and add, &apos;But you&apos;d better go to Abraham, Khalil Ar-Rahman.&apos;
They will go to Abraham who will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and mention to them the mistakes he made, and add, &apos;But you&apos;d better go to Moses, a slave whom Allah gave the Torah and to whom He spoke directly&apos; They will go to Moses who will reply, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking,&apos; and mention to them the mistakes he made, and add, &apos;You&apos;d better go to Jesus, Allah&apos;s slave and His Apostle and His Word (Be: And it was) and a soul created by Him.&apos; They will go to Jesus who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking, but you&apos;d better go to Muhammad whose sins of the past and the future had been forgiven (by Allah).&apos; So they will come to me and I will ask the permission of my Lord, and I will be permitted (to present myself) before Him. When I see my Lord, I will fall down in (prostration) before Him and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then it will be said to me, &apos;O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will then raise my head and praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit whom I will admit into Paradise.
I will come back again, and when I see my Lord (again), I will fall down in prostration before Him, and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then He will say, &apos;O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will then praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit to whom I will admit into Paradise, I will return again, and when I see my Lord, I will fall down (in prostration) and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then He will say, &apos;O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will then praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit to whom I will admit into Paradise. I will come back and say, &apos;O my Lord! None remains in Hell (Fire) but those whom Qur&apos;an has imprisoned therein and for whom eternity in Hell (Fire) has become inevitable.&apos; &quot;
The Prophet added, &quot;There will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: &apos;La ilaha illal-lah,&apos; and has in his heart good equal to the weight of a barley grain. Then there will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: &apos; La ilaha illal-lah,&apos; and has in his heart good equal to the weight of a wheat grain. Then there will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: &apos;La ilaha illal-lah,&apos; and has in his heart good equal to the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant).&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="532">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated &apos;Ata&apos; bin Yazid Al-Laithi:
On the authority of Abu Huraira: The people said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?&quot; The Prophet said, &quot;Do you have any difficulty in seeing the moon on a full moon night?&quot; They said, &quot;No, O Allah&apos;s Apostle.&quot; He said, &quot;Do you have any difficulty in seeing the sun when there are no clouds?&quot; They said, &quot;No, O Allah&apos;s Apostle.&quot; He said, &quot;So you will see Him, like that. Allah will gather all the people on the Day of Resurrection, and say, &apos;Whoever worshipped something (in the world) should follow (that thing),&apos; so, whoever worshipped the sun will follow the sun, and whoever worshiped the moon will follow the moon, and whoever used to worship certain (other false) deities, he will follow those deities. And there will remain only this nation with its good people (or its hypocrites). (The sub-narrator, Ibrahim is in doubt.) Allah will come to them and say, &apos;I am your Lord.&apos; They will (deny Him and) say, &apos;We will stay here till our Lord comes, for when our Lord comes, we will recognize Him.&apos; So Allah will come to them in His appearance which they know, and will say, &apos;I am your Lord.&apos; They will say, &apos;You are our Lord,&apos; so they will follow Him.
Then a bridge will be laid across Hell (Fire)&apos; I and my followers will be the first ones to go across it and none will speak on that Day except the Apostles. And the invocation of the Apostles on that Day will be, &apos;O Allah, save! Save!&apos; In Hell (or over The Bridge) there will be hooks like the thorns of As-Sa&apos;dan (thorny plant). Have you seen As-Sa&apos;dan? &quot; They replied, &quot;Yes, O Allah&apos;s Apostle!&quot; He said, &quot;So those hooks look like the thorns of As-Sa&apos;dan, but none knows how big they are except Allah. Those hooks will snap the people away according to their deeds. Some of the people will stay in Hell (be destroyed) because of their (evil) deeds, and some will be cut or torn by the hooks (and fall into Hell) and some will be punished and then relieved. When Allah has finished His Judgments among the people, He will take whomever He will out of Hell through His Mercy. He will then order the angels to take out of the Fire all those who used to worship none but Allah from among those whom Allah wanted to be merciful to and those who testified (in the world) that none has the right to be worshipped but Allah. The angels will recognize them in the Fire by the marks of prostration (on their foreheads), for the Fire will eat up all the human body except the mark caused by prostration as Allah has forbidden the Fire to eat the mark of prostration. They will come out of the (Hell) Fire, completely burnt and then the water of life will be poured over them and they will grow under it as does a seed that comes in the mud of the torrent.
Then Allah will finish the judgments among the people, and there will remain one man facing the (Hell) Fire and he will be the last person among the people of Hell to enter Paradise. He will say, &apos;O my Lord! Please turn my face away from the fire because its air has hurt me and its severe heat has burnt me.&apos; So he will invoke Allah in the way Allah will wish him to invoke, and then Allah will say to him, &apos;If I grant you that, will you then ask for anything else?&apos; He will reply, &apos;No, by Your Power, (Honor) I will not ask You for anything else.&apos; He will give his Lord whatever promises and covenants Allah will demand.
So Allah will turn his face away from Hell (Fire). When he will face Paradise and will see it, he will remain quiet for as long as Allah will wish him to remain quiet, then he will say, &apos;O my Lord! Bring me near to the gate of Paradise.&apos; Allah will say to him, &apos;Didn&apos;t you give your promises and covenants that you would never ask for anything more than what you had been given? Woe on you, O Adam&apos;s son! How treacherous you are!&apos; He will say, &apos;O my lord,&apos; and will keep on invoking Allah till He says to him, &apos;If I give what you are asking, will you then ask for anything else?&apos; He will reply, &apos;No, by Your (Honor) Power, I will not ask for anything else.&apos;
Then he will give covenants and promises to Allah and then Allah will bring him near to the gate of Paradise. When he stands at the gate of Paradise, Paradise will be opened and spread before him, and he will see its splendor and pleasures whereupon he will remain quiet as long as Allah will wish him to remain quiet, and then he will say, O my Lord! Admit me into Paradise.&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Didn&apos;t you give your covenants and promises that you would not ask for anything more than what you had been given?&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Woe on you, O Adam&apos;s son! How treacherous you are! &apos;
The man will say, &apos;O my Lord! Do not make me the most miserable of Your creation,&apos; and he will keep on invoking Allah till Allah will laugh because of his sayings, and when Allah will laugh because of him, He will say to him, &apos;Enter Paradise,&apos; and when he will enter it, Allah will say to him, &apos;Wish for anything.&apos; So he will ask his Lord, and he will wish for a great number of things, for Allah Himself will remind him to wish for certain things by saying, &apos;(Wish for) so-and-so.&apos; When there is nothing more to wish for, Allah will say, &apos;This is for you, and its equal (is for you) as well.&quot;
&apos;Ata&apos; bin Yazid added: Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri who was present with Abu Huraira, did not deny whatever the latter said, but when Abu Huraira said that Allah had said, &quot;That is for you and its equal as well,&quot; Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri said, &quot;And ten times as much, O Abu Huraira!&quot; Abu Huraira said, &quot;I do not remember, except his saying, &apos;That is for you and its equal as well.&apos;&quot; Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri then said, &quot;I testify that I remember the Prophet saying, &apos;That is for you, and ten times as much.&apos; &apos; Abu Huraira then added, &quot;That man will be the last person of the people of Paradise to enter Paradise.&quot;
Narrated Abu Sa&apos;id Al-Khudri:
We said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?&quot; He said, &quot;Do you have any difficulty in seeing the sun and the moon when the sky is clear?&quot; We said, &quot;No.&quot; He said, &quot;So you will have no difficulty in seeing your Lord on that Day as you have no difficulty in seeing the sun and the moon (in a clear sky).&quot; The Prophet then said, &quot;Somebody will then announce, &apos;Let every nation follow what they used to worship.&apos; So the companions of the cross will go with their cross, and the idolators (will go) with their idols, and the companions of every god (false deities) (will go) with their god, till there remain those who used to worship Allah, both the obedient ones and the mischievous ones, and some of the people of the Scripture. Then Hell will be presented to them as if it were a mirage. Then it will be said to the Jews, &quot;What did you use to worship?&apos; They will reply, &apos;We used to worship Ezra, the son of Allah.&apos; It will be said to them, &apos;You are liars, for Allah has neither a wife nor a son. What do you want (now)?&apos; They will reply, &apos;We want You to provide us with water.&apos; Then it will be said to them &apos;Drink,&apos; and they will fall down in Hell (instead). Then it will be said to the Christians, &apos;What did you use to worship?&apos;
They will reply, &apos;We used to worship Messiah, the son of Allah.&apos; It will be said, &apos;You are liars, for Allah has neither a wife nor a son. What: do you want (now)?&apos; They will say, &apos;We want You to provide us with water.&apos; It will be said to them, &apos;Drink,&apos; and they will fall down in Hell (instead). When there remain only those who used to worship Allah (Alone), both the obedient ones and the mischievous ones, it will be said to them, &apos;What keeps you here when all the people have gone?&apos; They will say, &apos;We parted with them (in the world) when we were in greater need of them than we are today, we heard the call of one proclaiming, &apos;Let every nation follow what they used to worship,&apos; and now we are waiting for our Lord.&apos; Then the Almighty will come to them in a shape other than the one which they saw the first time, and He will say, &apos;I am your Lord,&apos; and they will say, &apos;You are not our Lord.&apos; And none will speak: to Him then but the Prophets, and then it will be said to them, &apos;Do you know any sign by which you can recognize Him?&apos; They will say. &apos;The Shin,&apos; and so Allah will then uncover His Shin whereupon every believer will prostrate before Him and there will remain those who used to prostrate before Him just for showing off and for gaining good reputation. These people will try to prostrate but their backs will be rigid like one piece of a wood (and they will not be able to prostrate). Then the bridge will be laid across Hell.&quot; We, the companions of the Prophet said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! What is the bridge?&apos;
He said, &quot;It is a slippery (bridge) on which there are clamps and (Hooks like) a thorny seed that is wide at one side and narrow at the other and has thorns with bent ends. Such a thorny seed is found in Najd and is called As-Sa&apos;dan. Some of the believers will cross the bridge as quickly as the wink of an eye, some others as quick as lightning, a strong wind, fast horses or she-camels. So some will be safe without any harm; some will be safe after receiving some scratches, and some will fall down into Hell (Fire). The last person will cross by being dragged (over the bridge).&quot; The Prophet said, &quot;You (Muslims) cannot be more pressing in claiming from me a right that has been clearly proved to be yours than the believers in interceding with Almighty for their (Muslim) brothers on that Day, when they see themselves safe.
They will say, &apos;O Allah! (Save) our brothers (for they) used to pray with us, fast with us and also do good deeds with us.&apos; Allah will say, &apos;Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of one (gold) Dinar.&apos; Allah will forbid the Fire to burn the faces of those sinners. They will go to them and find some of them in Hell (Fire) up to their feet, and some up to the middle of their legs. So they will take out those whom they will recognize and then they will return, and Allah will say (to them), &apos;Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of one half Dinar.&apos; They will take out whomever they will recognize and return, and then Allah will say, &apos;Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant), and so they will take out all those whom they will recognize.&quot; Abu Sa&apos;id said: If you do not believe me then read the Holy Verse:--
&apos;Surely! Allah wrongs not even of the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant) but if there is any good (done) He doubles it.&apos; (4.40) The Prophet added, &quot;Then the prophets and Angels and the believers will intercede, and (last of all) the Almighty (Allah) will say, &apos;Now remains My Intercession. He will then hold a handful of the Fire from which He will take out some people whose bodies have been burnt, and they will be thrown into a river at the entrance of Paradise, called the water of life.
They will grow on its banks, as a seed carried by the torrent grows. You have noticed how it grows beside a rock or beside a tree, and how the side facing the sun is usually green while the side facing the shade is white. Those people will come out (of the River of Life) like pearls, and they will have (golden) necklaces, and then they will enter Paradise whereupon the people of Paradise will say, &apos;These are the people emancipated by the Beneficent. He has admitted them into Paradise without them having done any good deeds and without sending forth any good (for themselves).&apos; Then it will be said to them, &apos;For you is what you have seen and its equivalent as well.&apos;&quot;
Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, &quot;The believers will be kept (waiting) on the Day of Resurrection so long that they will become worried and say, &quot;Let us ask somebody to intercede far us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from our place.
Then they will go to Adam and say, &apos;You are Adam, the father of the people. Allah created you with His Own Hand and made you reside in His Paradise and ordered His angels to prostrate before you, and taught you the names of all things will you intercede for us with your Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours? Adam will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking.&apos; He will mention his mistakes he had committed, i.e., his eating off the tree though he had been forbidden to do so. He will add, &apos;Go to Noah, the first prophet sent by Allah to the people of the Earth.&apos; The people will go to Noah who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking&apos; He will mention his mistake which he had done, i.e., his asking his Lord without knowledge.&apos; He will say (to them), &apos;Go to Abraham, Khalil Ar-Rahman.&apos; They will go to Abraham who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking. He would mention three words by which he told a lie, and say (to them). &apos;Go to Moses, a slave whom Allah gave the Torah and spoke to, directly and brought near Him, for conversation.&apos;
They will go to Moses who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking. He will mention his mistake he made, i.e., killing a person, and will say (to them), &apos;Go to Jesus, Allah&apos;s slave and His Apostle, and a soul created by Him and His Word.&apos; (Be: And it was.) They will go to Jesus who will say, &apos;I am not fit for this undertaking but you&apos;d better go to Muhammad the slave whose past and future sins have been forgiven by Allah.&apos; So they will come to me, and I will ask my Lord&apos;s permission to enter His House and then I will be permitted. When I see Him I will fall down in prostration before Him, and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He will, and then He will say, &apos;O Muhammad, lift up your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask (for anything) for it will be granted:&apos; Then I will raise my head and glorify my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me. Allah will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people) I will take them out and make them enter Paradise.&quot; (Qatada said: I heard Anas saying that), the Prophet said, &quot;I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, and then I will return and ask my Lord for permission to enter His House and I will be permitted.
When I will see Him I will fall down in prostration before Him and He will leave me in prostration as long as He will let me (in that state), and then He will say, &apos;O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask, your request will be granted.&apos; &quot; The Prophet added, &quot;So I will raise my head and glorify and praise Him as He has taught me. Then I will intercede and He will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people). I will take them out and let them enter Paradise.&quot; (Qatada added: I heard Anas saying that) the Prophet said, &apos;I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, and I will return for the third time and will ask my Lord for permission to enter His house, and I will be allowed to enter.
When I see Him, I will fall down in prostration before Him, and will remain in prostration as long as He will, and then He will say, &apos;Raise your head, O Muhammad, and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask, for your request will be granted.&apos; So I will raise my head and praise Allah as He has taught me and then I will intercede and He will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people). I will take them out and let them enter Paradise.&quot; (Qatada said: I heard Anas saying that) the Prophet said, &quot;So I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, till none will remain in the Fire except those whom Quran will imprison (i.e., those who are destined for eternal life in the fire).&quot; The narrator then recited the Verse:-- &quot;It may be that your Lord will raise you to a Station of Praise and Glory.&apos; (17.79) The narrator added: This is the Station of Praise and Glory which Allah has promised to your Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="575">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Said Al-Khudri:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah will say (on the Day of Resurrection), &apos;O Adam!&apos; Adam will reply, &apos;Labbaik wa Sa&apos;daik! &apos; Then a loud Voice will be heard (Saying) &apos;Allah Commands you to take out the mission of the Hell Fire from your offspring.&apos; &quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="583">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;Allah said: &quot;The son of Adam hurts Me by abusing Time, for I am Time; in My Hands are all things and I cause the revolution of night and day.&apos; &quot; (See Hadith No. 351, Vol. 6)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="601">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ma&apos;bad bin Hilal Al&apos;Anzi:
We, i.e., some people from Basra gathered and went to Anas bin Malik, and we went in company with Thabit Al-Bunnani so that he might ask him about the Hadith of Intercession on our behalf. Behold, Anas was in his palace, and our arrival coincided with his Duha prayer. We asked permission to enter and he admitted us while he was sitting on his bed. We said to Thabit, &quot;Do not ask him about anything else first but the Hadith of Intercession.&quot; He said, &quot;O Abu Hamza! There are your brethren from Basra coming to ask you about the Hadith of Intercession.&quot; Anas then said, &quot;Muhammad talked to us saying, &apos;On the Day of Resurrection the people will surge with each other like waves, and then they will come to Adam and say, &apos;Please intercede for us with your Lord.&apos; He will say, &apos;I am not fit for that but you&apos;d better go to Abraham as he is the Khalil of the Beneficent.&apos; They will go to Abraham and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for that, but you&apos;d better go to Moses as he is the one to whom Allah spoke directly.&apos; So they will go to Moses and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for that, but you&apos;d better go to Jesus as he is a soul created by Allah and His Word.&apos; (Be: And it was) they will go to Jesus and he will say, &apos;I am not fit for that, but you&apos;d better go to Muhammad.&apos;
They would come to me and I would say, &apos;I am for that.&apos; Then I will ask for my Lord&apos;s permission, and it will be given, and then He will inspire me to praise Him with such praises as I do not know now. So I will praise Him with those praises and will fall down, prostrate before Him. Then it will be said, &apos;O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for your will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will say, &apos;O Lord, my followers! My followers!&apos; And then it will be said, &apos;Go and take out of Hell (Fire) all those who have faith in their hearts, equal to the weight of a barley grain.&apos; I will go and do so and return to praise Him with the same praises, and fall down (prostrate) before Him. Then it will be said, &apos;O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will say, &apos;O Lord, my followers! My followers!&apos; It will be said, &apos;Go and take out of it all those who have faith in their hearts equal to the weight of a small ant or a mustard seed.&apos; I will go and do so and return to praise Him with the same praises, and fall down in prostration before Him. It will be said, &apos;O, Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.&apos; I will say, &apos;O Lord, my followers!&apos; Then He will say, &apos;Go and take out (all those) in whose hearts there is faith even to the lightest, lightest mustard seed. (Take them) out of the Fire.&apos; I will go and do so.&quot;&apos;
When we left Anas, I said to some of my companions, &quot;Let&apos;s pass by Al-Hasan who is hiding himself in the house of Abi Khalifa and request him to tell us what Anas bin Malik has told us.&quot; So we went to him and we greeted him and he admitted us. We said to him, &quot;O Abu Said! We came to you from your brother Anas Bin Malik and he related to us a Hadith about the intercession the like of which I have never heard.&quot; He said, &quot;What is that?&quot; Then we told him of the Hadith and said, &quot;He stopped at this point (of the Hadith).&quot; He said, &quot;What then?&quot; We said, &quot;He did not add anything to that.&quot; He said, Anas related the Hadith to me twenty years ago when he was a young fellow. I don&apos;t know whether he forgot or if he did not like to let you depend on what he might have said.&quot; We said, &quot;O Abu Said ! Let us know that.&quot; He smiled and said, &quot;Man was created hasty. I did not mention that, but that I wanted to inform you of it.
Anas told me the same as he told you and said that the Prophet added, &apos;I then return for a fourth time and praise Him similarly and prostrate before Him me the same as he &apos;O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for you will be granted (your request): and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted .&apos; I will say, &apos;O Lord, allow me to intercede for whoever said, &apos;None has the right to be worshiped except Allah.&apos; Then Allah will say, &apos;By my Power, and my Majesty, and by My Supremacy, and by My Greatness, I will take out of Hell (Fire) whoever said: &apos;None has the right to be worshipped except Allah.&apos; &apos;&apos;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="606">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, &quot;Adam and Moses debated with each other and Moses said, &apos;You are Adam who turned out your offspring from Paradise.&apos; Adam said, &quot;You are Moses whom Allah chose for His Message and for His direct talk, yet you blame me for a matter which had been ordained for me even before my creation?&apos; Thus Adam overcame Moses.&quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="607">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas:
Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;The believers will be assembled on the Day of Resurrection and they will say, &apos;Let us look for someone to intercede for us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.&apos; So they will go to Adam and say, &apos;You are Adam, the father of mankind, and Allah created you with His Own Hands and ordered the Angels to prostrate before you, and He taught you the names of all things; so please intercede for us with our Lord so that He may relieve us.&apos; Adam will say, to them, &apos;I am not fit for that,&apos; and then he will mention to them his mistake which he has committed.&apos; &quot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="608">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas bin Malik:
The night Allah&apos;s Apostle was taken for a journey from the sacred mosque (of Mecca) Al-Ka&apos;ba: Three persons came to him (in a dreamy while he was sleeping in the Sacred Mosque before the Divine Inspiration was revealed to Him. One of them said, &quot;Which of them is he?&quot; The middle (second) angel said, &quot;He is the best of them.&quot; The last (third) angle said, &quot;Take the best of them.&quot; Only that much happened on that night and he did not see them till they came on another night, i.e. after The Divine Inspiration was revealed to him. (Fateh-Al-Bari Page 258, Vol. 17) and he saw them, his eyes were asleep but his heart was not----and so is the case with the prophets: their eyes sleep while their hearts do not sleep. So those angels did not talk to him till they carried him and placed him beside the well of Zam-Zam. From among them Gabriel took charge of him. Gabriel cut open (the part of his body) between his throat and the middle of his chest (heart) and took all the material out of his chest and abdomen and then washed it with Zam-Zam water with his own hands till he cleansed the inside of his body, and then a gold tray containing a gold bowl full of belief and wisdom was brought and then Gabriel stuffed his chest and throat blood vessels with it and then closed it (the chest). He then ascended with him to the heaven of the world and knocked on one of its doors.
The dwellers of the Heaven asked, &apos;Who is it?&apos; He said, &quot;Gabriel.&quot; They said, &quot;Who is accompanying you?&quot; He said, &quot;Muhammad.&quot; They said, &quot;Has he been called?&quot; He said, &quot;Yes&quot; They said, &quot;He is welcomed.&quot; So the dwellers of the Heaven became pleased with his arrival, and they did not know what Allah would do to the Prophet on earth unless Allah informed them. The Prophet met Adam over the nearest Heaven. Gabriel said to the Prophet, &quot;He is your father; greet him.&quot; The Prophet greeted him and Adam returned his greeting and said, &quot;Welcome, O my Son! O what a good son you are!&quot; Behold, he saw two flowing rivers, while he was in the nearest sky. He asked, &quot;What are these two rivers, O Gabriel?&quot; Gabriel said, &quot;These are the sources of the Nile and the Euphrates.&quot;
Then Gabriel took him around that Heaven and behold, he saw another river at the bank of which there was a palace built of pearls and emerald. He put his hand into the river and found its mud like musk Adhfar. He asked, &quot;What is this, O Gabriel?&quot; Gabriel said, &quot;This is the Kauthar which your Lord has kept for you.&quot; Then Gabriel ascended (with him) to the second Heaven and the angels asked the same questions as those on the first Heaven, i.e., &quot;Who is it?&quot; Gabriel replied, &quot;Gabriel&quot;. They asked, &quot;Who is accompanying you?&quot; He said, &quot;Muhammad.&quot; They asked, &quot;Has he been sent for?&quot; He said, &quot;Yes.&quot; Then they said, &quot;He is welcomed.&apos;&apos; Then he (Gabriel) ascended with the Prophet to the third Heaven, and the angels said the same as the angels of the first and the second Heavens had said.
Then he ascended with him to the fourth Heaven and they said the same; and then he ascended with him to the fifth Heaven and they said the same; and then he ascended with him to the sixth Heaven and they said the same; then he ascended with him to the seventh Heaven and they said the same. On each Heaven there were prophets whose names he had mentioned and of whom I remember Idris on the second Heaven, Aaron on the fourth Heavens another prophet whose name I don&apos;t remember, on the fifth Heaven, Abraham on the sixth Heaven, and Moses on the seventh Heaven because of his privilege of talking to Allah directly. Moses said (to Allah), &quot;O Lord! I thought that none would be raised up above me.&quot;
But Gabriel ascended with him (the Prophet) for a distance above that, the distance of which only Allah knows, till he reached the Lote Tree (beyond which none may pass) and then the Irresistible, the Lord of Honor and Majesty approached and came closer till he (Gabriel) was about two bow lengths or (even) nearer. (It is said that it was Gabriel who approached and came closer to the Prophet. (Fate Al-Bari Page 263, 264, Vol. 17). Among the things which Allah revealed to him then, was: &quot;Fifty prayers were enjoined on his followers in a day and a night.&quot;
Then the Prophet descended till he met Moses, and then Moses stopped him and asked, &quot;O Muhammad ! What did your Lord en join upon you?&quot; The Prophet replied,&quot; He enjoined upon me to perform fifty prayers in a day and a night.&quot; Moses said, &quot;Your followers cannot do that; Go back so that your Lord may reduce it for you and for them.&quot; So the Prophet turned to Gabriel as if he wanted to consult him about that issue. Gabriel told him of his opinion, saying, &quot;Yes, if you wish.&quot; So Gabriel ascended with him to the Irresistible and said while he was in his place, &quot;O Lord, please lighten our burden as my followers cannot do that.&quot; So Allah deducted for him ten prayers where upon he returned to Moses who stopped him again and kept on sending him back to his Lord till the enjoined prayers were reduced to only five prayers.
Then Moses stopped him when the prayers had been reduced to five and said, &quot;O Muhammad! By Allah, I tried to persuade my nation, Bani Israel to do less than this, but they could not do it and gave it up. However, your followers are weaker in body, heart, sight and hearing, so return to your Lord so that He may lighten your burden.&quot;
The Prophet turned towards Gabriel for advice and Gabriel did not disapprove of that. So he ascended with him for the fifth time. The Prophet said, &quot;O Lord, my followers are weak in their bodies, hearts, hearing and constitution, so lighten our burden.&quot; On that the Irresistible said, &quot;O Muhammad!&quot; the Prophet replied, &quot;Labbaik and Sa&apos;daik.&quot; Allah said, &quot;The Word that comes from Me does not change, so it will be as I enjoined on you in the Mother of the Book.&quot; Allah added, &quot;Every good deed will be rewarded as ten times so it is fifty (prayers) in the Mother of the Book (in reward) but you are to perform only five (in practice).&quot;
The Prophet returned to Moses who asked, &quot;What have you done?&quot; He said, &quot;He has lightened our burden: He has given us for every good deed a tenfold reward.&quot; Moses said, &quot;By Allah! I tried to make Bani Israel observe less than that, but they gave it up. So go back to your Lord that He may lighten your burden further.&quot; Allah&apos;s Apostle said, &quot;O Moses! By Allah, I feel shy of returning too many times to my Lord.&quot; On that Gabriel said, &quot;Descend in Allah&apos;s Name.&quot; The Prophet then woke while he was in the Sacred Mosque (at Mecca).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="610">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Once the Prophet was preaching while a bedouin was sitting there. The Prophet said, &quot;A man from among the people of Paradise will request Allah to allow him to cultivate the land Allah will say to him, &apos;Haven&apos;t you got whatever you desire?&apos; He will reply, &apos;yes, but I like to cultivate the land (Allah will permit him and) he will sow the seeds, and within seconds the plants will grow and ripen and (the yield) will be harvested and piled in heaps like mountains. On that Allah will say (to him), &quot;Take, here you are, O son of Adam, for nothing satisfies you.&apos; &quot;On that the bedouin said, &quot;O Allah&apos;s Apostle! Such man must be either from Quraish or from Ansar, for they are farmers while we are not.&quot; On that Allah&apos;s Apostle smiled .</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="9" verse="101">
      <chapter_name></chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.itani</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Among the Desert-Arabs around you there are some hypocrites, and among the inhabitants of Medina too. They have become adamant in hypocrisy. You do not know them, but We know them. We will punish them twice; then they will be returned to a severe torment.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>