<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="ayyub" generated="2026-03-30T00:19:51.237Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story of Job (Ayyub)</title>
    <verses_count>15</verses_count>
    <translations_count>211</translations_count>
    <reordered>2026-03-30T00:19:51.250Z</reordered>
    <reorder_source>ayyub_reorder.csv</reorder_source>
  </metadata>
  <verses>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="84">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided them, as We had guided Noah before them, and of his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus We reward those who are upright and do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob); We guided all of them; and We guided Nooh before them and of his descendants, Dawud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Moosa and Haroon; and this is the way We reward the virtuous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave to him Isaac and Jacob -- each one We guided, And Noah We guided before; and of his seed David and Solomon, Job and Joseph, Moses and Aaron -- even so We recompense the good-doers --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Is-haq and Ya'qub: each one We guided. And Nuh We had guided afore, and of his progeny Da-ud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Musa and Harun. And thus We recompense the well-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob), each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh (Noah), and among his progeny Dawud (David), Sulaiman (Solomon), Ayub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses), and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob—each of them We guided. And We guided Noah previously; and from his descendants David, and Solomon, and Job, and Joseph, and Moses, and Aaron. Thus We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon Abraham (offspring) Ishaq (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob) and each of them did We guide to the right way as We had earlier guided Noah to the right way; and (of his descendants We guided) Da'ud (David) and Sulayman (Solomon), Ayyub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses) and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward those who do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq and Ya`qub, each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh and among his progeny Dawud, Sulayman, Ayyub, Yusuf, Musa, and Harun. Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Isaac and Jacob; each of them We guided; and Noah did We guide aforetime; and of his seed (We guided) David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided both; and We guided Noah before them, among his descendants were David and Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron as such, We recompense the gooddoers,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob - all [of them] We guided. And Noah, We guided before; and among his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave (Abraham) Isaac and Jacob. Both had received Our guidance. Noah received Our guidance before Abraham and so did his descendants: David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron. Thus is the reward for the righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave to him Ishaq and Yaqoub; each did We guide, and Nuh did We guide before, and of his descendants, Dawood and Sulaiman and Ayub and Yusuf and Musa and Haroun; and thus do We reward those who do good (to others).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob, each of whom We guided as We had guided Noah before. Among his descendants were David and Solomon, and Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob: all (three) guided: and before him, We guided Noah, and among his progeny, David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron: thus do We reward those who do good:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="163">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We have sent revelations to you as We sent revelations to Noah and the prophets (who came) after him; and We sent revelations to Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob, and their offspring, and to Jesus and Job, and to Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and to David We gave the Book of Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed We sent a divine revelation to you (Prophet Mohammed – peace and blessing be upon him) as We did send divine revelations to Nooh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; and We sent divine revelations to Ibrahim (Abraham) and Ismael (Ishmael) and Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob) and their offspring, and Eisa (Jesus) and Ayyub (Job) and Yunus (Jonah) and Haroon (Aaron) and Sulaiman (Solomon), and We bestowed the Zaboor (the Holy Book) upon Dawud (David).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We have revealed to thee as We revealed to Noah, and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, Jesus and Job, Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We have revealed unto thee even as We revealed unto Nuh and the prophets after him, and as We revealed unto Ibrahim and Isma'il and Is-haq and Ya'qub and the tribes, and 'Isa and Ayyub and Yunus and Harun and Sulaiman, and unto Daud We vouchsafed a Scripture.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, We have inspired you (O Muhammad SAW) as We inspired Nuh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; We (also) inspired Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma'il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya'qub (Jacob), and Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya'qub (Jacob)], 'Iesa (Jesus), Ayub (Job), Yunus (Jonah), Harun (Aaron), and Sulaiman (Solomon), and to Dawud (David) We gave the Zabur (Psalms).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We have inspired you, as We had inspired Noah and the prophets after him. And We inspired Abraham, and Ishmael, and Isaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs, and Jesus, and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron, and Solomon. And We gave David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(O Muhammad!) We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the offspring of Jacob, and Jesus and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, We have sent the revelation to you as We sent the revelation to Nuh and the Prophets after him; We (also) sent the revelation to Ibrahim, Isma`il, Ishaq, Ya`qub, and Al-Asbat, (the offspring of the twelve sons of Ya`qub) `Isa, Ayyub, Yunus, Harun, and Sulayman; and to Dawud We gave the Zabur.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! We inspire thee as We inspired Noah and the prophets after him, as We inspired Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob and the tribes, and Jesus and Job and Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and as We imparted unto David the Psalms;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and to the Prophets after him, and We revealed to (Prophets) Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the tribes, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and We gave to David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, We have revealed to you, [O Muhammad], as We revealed to Noah and the prophets after him. And we revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, the Descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and to David We gave the book [of Psalms].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), We have sent revelations to you just as were sent to Noah and the Prophets who lived after him and to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, his descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon. We gave the Psalms to David.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely We have revealed to you as We revealed to Nuh, and the prophets after him, and We revealed to Ibrahim and Ismail and Ishaq and Yaqoub and the tribes, and Isa and Ayub and Yunus and Haroun and Sulaiman and We gave to Dawood</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We have sent revelation to you [Prophet] as We did to Noah and the prophets who came after him, to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon and David, to whom We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We have sent thee inspiration, as We sent it to Noah and the Messengers after him: we sent inspiration to Abraham, Isma'il, Isaac, Jacob and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and solomon, and to David We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="41">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Remember Our votary Job because he called to his Lord: "Satan has afflicted me with disease and distress."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Our bondman Ayyub (Job); when he cried out* to his Lord, “The devil has struck me with hardship and pain.” (After seven years of patience.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Remember also Our servant Job; when he called to his Lord, 'Behold, Satan has visited me with weariness and chastisement.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And remember thou Our bondman Ayyub, what time he cried Unto his Lord: verily the Satan hath touched me with affliction and suffering.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And remember Our slave Ayub (Job), when he invoked his Lord (saying): "Verily! Shaitan (Satan) has touched me with distress (by losing my health) and torment (by losing my wealth)!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And mention Our servant Job, when he called out to his Lord, “Satan has afflicted me with hardship and pain.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And remember Our servant Job: when he cried to his Lord: “Behold, Satan has afflicted me with much hardship and suffering.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And remember Our servant Ayyub, when he invoked his Lord (saying): "Verily, Shaytan has afflicted me with distress and torment!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And make mention (O Muhammad) of Our bondman Job, when he cried unto his Lord (saying): Lo! the devil doth afflict me with distress and torment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Also, remember Our worshiper Job. He called out to his Lord, (saying): 'satan has afflicted me with harm and pain'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And remember Our servant Job, when he called to his Lord, "Indeed, Satan has touched me with hardship and torment."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), recall Our servant Job. When he prayed to his Lord saying, "Satan has afflicted me with hardship and torment,"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And remember Our servant Ayyub, when he called upon his Lord: The Shaitan has afflicted me with toil and torment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Bring to mind Our servant Job who cried to his Lord, "Satan has afflicted me with distress and suffering."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Commemorate Our Servant Job. Behold he cried to his Lord: "The Evil One has afflicted me with distress and suffering!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="83">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Remember) Job when he called to his Lord: "I am afflicted with distress, and You are the most compassionate of all."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Ayyub (Job), when he called his Lord that, “Hardship has afflicted me, and You are the Most Merciful of all those who have mercy.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Job -- when he called unto his Lord, 'Behold, affliction has visited me, and Thou art the most merciful of the merciful.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Ayyub! recall what time he cried unto his Lord: verily hurt hath touched me, and Thou art the Most Merciful of the mercifuls.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) Ayub (Job), when he cried to his Lord: "Verily, distress has seized me, and You are the Most Merciful of all those who show mercy."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Job, when he cried out to his Lord: “Great harm has afflicted me, and you are the Most Merciful of the merciful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We bestowed (the same wisdom, judgement and knowledge) upon Job. Recall, when he cried to his Lord: "Behold, disease has struck me and You are the Most Merciful of those that are merciful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) Ayyub, when he cried to his Lord: "Verily, distress has seized me, and You are the Most Merciful of all those who show mercy."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Job, when he cried unto his Lord, (saying): Lo! adversity afflicteth me, and Thou art Most Merciful of all who show mercy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And Job when he called to his Lord: 'Affliction has befallen me, and You are the Most Merciful of the merciful'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] Job, when he called to his Lord, "Indeed, adversity has touched me, and you are the Most Merciful of the merciful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When Job prayed, "Lord, I have been afflicted with hardships. Have mercy on me; You are the Most Merciful of those who have mercy,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Ayub, when he cried to his Lord, (saying): Harm has afflicted me, and Thou art the most Merciful of the merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Remember Job when he called on his Lord saying, "I have been afflicted with great distress: but You are the most merciful of the merciful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And (remember) Job, when He cried to his Lord, "Truly distress has seized me, but Thou art the Most Merciful of those that are merciful."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="85">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Remember) Ishmael, Edris and Dhu'l-Kifl. They were men of fortitude,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Ismail, and Idrees, and Zul-Kifl; they were all patiently enduring.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Ishmael, Idris, Dhul Kifl -- each was of the patient,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Isma'il and ldris and Zul-Kifl! each were of the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) Isma'il (Ishmael), and Idris (Enoch) and Dhul-Kifl (Isaiah), all were from among As-Sabirin (the patient ones, etc.).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Ishmael, and Enoch, and Ezekiel; each was one of the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And (We bestowed the same favour) upon Ishmael, Idris and Dhu al-Kifl, for they were all steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) Isma`il, Idris and Dhul-Kifl: All were from among the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (mention) Ishmael, and Idris, and Dhu'l-Kifl. All were of the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And Ishmael, Idris, and ThulKifl (the son of Job) each were patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] Ishmael and Idrees and Dhul-Kifl; all were of the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Ismael, Idris and Dhul Kifl all were people of great patience.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Ismail and Idris and Zulkifl; all were of the patient ones;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Remember Ishmael and Idris and Dhul Kifl: they were all patient and steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And (remember) Isma'il, Idris, and Zul-kifl, all (men) of constancy and patience;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="86">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And they were admitted to Our grace. Verily they were among the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy; indeed they are among those who deserve Our proximity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and We admitted them into Our mercy; they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We caused them to enter into our mercy, verily they are of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We admitted them to Our Mercy. Verily, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy. They were among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy, for they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We admitted them to Our mercy. Verily, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We brought them in unto Our mercy. Lo! they are among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We admitted them to Our Mercy, for they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy. Indeed, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We encompassed them in Our mercy; they were righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We caused them to enter into Our mercy, surely they were of the good ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We admitted them to Our mercy. They were all righteous men.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We admitted them to Our mercy: for they were of the righteous ones.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="42">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"Go swiftly to the spring," (We said). "This cold water is for bathing and for drinking."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>We said to him, “Strike the earth with your foot; this cool spring is for bathing and drinking.” (A spring of gushed forth when he struck the earth – this was a miracle.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>'Stamp thy foot! This is a laving-place cool, and a drink.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Stamp the ground with thy foot. yonder is water to wash in, cool, and water to drink.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>(Allah said to him): "Strike the ground with your foot: This is a spring of water to wash in, cool and a (refreshing) drink."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“Stamp with your foot—here is cool water to wash with, and to drink.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(We commanded him): “Stamp your foot on earth, and here is cool water to wash with and to drink.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>(Allah said to him): "Strike the ground with your foot. This is (a spring of) water to wash in, cool and a drink."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>(And it was said unto him): Strike the ground with thy foot. This (spring) is a cool bath and a refreshing drink.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>(We said): 'Stamp your foot on the ground, here is cool water with which to wash and a drink'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[So he was told], "Strike [the ground] with your foot; this is a [spring for] a cool bath and drink."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(We answered his prayer, healed his sickness, and told him), "Run on your feet. This is cool water (for you) to wash and drink".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Urge with your foot; here is a cool washing-place and a drink.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We said, "Stamp your foot! Here is cool water for you to wash in and drink,"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(The command was given:) "Strike with thy foot: here is (water) wherein to wash, cool and refreshing, and (water) to drink."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="84">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We heard his cry and relieved him of the misery he was in. We restored his family to him, and along with them gave him others similar to them as a grace from Us and reminder for those who are obedient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>We therefore heard his prayer and removed the adversity that had afflicted him, and We gave him his family and in addition bestowed along with them a similar number, by mercy from Ourselves – and an advice for the people who worship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So We answered him, and removed the affliction that was upon him, and We gave his people, and the like of them with them, mercy from Us, and a Reminder to those who serve.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>So We answered him and We removed that which was with him of the hurt, and We vouchsafed unto him his household and the like thereof along with them, as a mercy from us and a remembrance unto the worshippers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So We answered his call, and We removed the distress that was on him, and We restored his family to him (that he had lost), and the like thereof along with them, as a mercy from Ourselves and a Reminder for all who worship Us.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>So We answered him, lifted his suffering, and restored his family to him, and their like with them—a mercy from Us, and a reminder for the worshipers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We accepted his prayer and removed the affliction from him, and We not only restored to him his family but as many more with them as a mercy from Us and as a lesson to the worshippers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So We answered his call, and We removed the distress that was on him, and We restored his family to him, and the like thereof along with them as a mercy from Ourselves and a Reminder for all those who worship Us.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Then We heard his prayer and removed that adversity from which he suffered, and We gave him his household (that he had lost) and the like thereof along with them, a mercy from Our store, and a remembrance for the worshippers;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We answered him and removed his affliction, and We gave his people, and those like them that were with them, mercy from Us, as a reminder to those who worship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So We responded to him and removed what afflicted him of adversity. And We gave him [back] his family and the like thereof with them as mercy from Us and a reminder for the worshippers [of Allah].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>"We answered his prayer, relieved him from his hardships, brought his family (back to him) and gave him twice as much property as that (which was destroyed). It was a mercy from Us and a reminder for the worshippers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Therefore We responded to him and took off what harm he had, and We gave him his family and the like of them with them: a mercy from Us and a reminder to the worshippers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We heard his prayer and relieved his suffering, We restored to him his family, doubling their number as an act of Our grace, and as a reminder for the worshippers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So We listened to him: We removed the distress that was on him, and We restored his people to him, and doubled their number,- as a Grace from Ourselves, and a thing for commemoration, for all who serve Us.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="43">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We restored his family to him with others similar to them, as a blessing from Us and a reminder for men of wisdom. --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed his household to him and one more similar to it – as a mercy from Us, and as a remembrance for the people of intellect.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave to him his family, and the like of them with them, as a mercy from us, and a reminder unto men possessed of minds;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed on him his household and along with them the like thereof, out of mercy from us, and a remembrance Unto men of understanding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We gave him (back) his family, and along with them the like thereof, as a Mercy from Us, and a Reminder for those who understand.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We restored his family for him, and their like with them; as a mercy from Us, and a lesson for those who possess insight.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We granted to him his family and also the like of them, as a mercy from Us, and as a reminder to people of understanding,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We gave him (back) his family, and along with them the like thereof, as a mercy from Us, and a reminder for those who understand.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed on him (again) his household and therewith the like thereof, a mercy from Us, and a memorial for men of understanding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We restored to him to his family and like those with them, a mercy from Us and a reminder to a nation that understand.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We granted him his family and a like [number] with them as mercy from Us and a reminder for those of understanding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave him back his family and doubled their number as a blessing from Us and as a reminder to the people of understanding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave him his family and the like of them with them, as a mercy from Us, and as a reminder to those possessed of understanding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We restored his family to him, doubling their number as an act of grace from Us, and as a reminder to all who are endowed with insight.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We gave him (back) his people, and doubled their number,- as a Grace from Ourselves, and a thing for commemoration, for all who have Understanding.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="44">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"Take a handful of herbs," (We said to him), and apply and rub them, and do not make a mistake." We found him patient in adversity, an excellent devotee, always turning in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We said, “Take a broom in your hand and strike her with it, and do not break your vow”; We indeed found him patiently enduring; what an excellent bondman! He is indeed most inclined.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and, 'Take in thy hand a bundle of rushes, and strike therewith, and do not fail in thy oath.' Surely We found him a steadfast man. How excellent a servant he was! He was a penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And take in thine hand a handful of twigs, and strike therewith, and break not thine oath. Verily We! We found him patient. How excellent a bondman! Verily he was oft-returning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"And take in your hand a bundle of thin grass and strike therewith (your wife), and break not your oath. Truly! We found him patient. How excellent (a) slave! Verily, he was ever oft-returning in repentance (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“Take with your hand a bundle, and strike with it, and do not break your oath.” We found him patient. What an excellent servant! He was obedient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(and We said to him): “Take in your hand a bundle of rushes and strike with it, and do not break your oath.” Indeed We found him steadfast. How excellent a servant (of Ours) he was. Indeed he constantly turned (to his Lord).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"And take in your hand a bundle of thin grass and strike therewith (your wife), and break not your oath." Truly, We found him patient. How excellent a servant! Verily, he was ever oft-returning in repentance (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (it was said unto him): Take in thine hand a branch and smite therewith, and break not thine oath. Lo! We found him steadfast, how excellent a slave! Lo! he was ever turning in repentance (to his Lord).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>(We said to him): 'Take a bundle of rushes and strike with it; and do not break your oath' We found him to be patient, a good worshiper and he was penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[We said], "And take in your hand a bunch [of grass] and strike with it and do not break your oath." Indeed, We found him patient, an excellent servant. Indeed, he was one repeatedly turning back [to Allah].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We told him, "Take a handful of straw. Strike your wife with it to fulfill your oath." We found him to be patient. What an excellent servant he was. He was certainly most repenting.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And take in your hand a green branch and beat her with It and do not break your oath; surely We found him patient; most excellent the servant! Surely he was frequent in returning (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We said to Him, "Take a handful of twigs in your hand and strike with that but do not break your oath." We found him steadfast. What an excellent servant! He turned constantly to his Lord.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"And take in thy hand a little grass, and strike therewith: and break not (thy oath)." Truly We found him full of patience and constancy. How excellent in Our service! ever did he turn (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="585">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, "Once while Job (Aiyub) was taking a bath in a naked state. Suddenly a great number of gold locusts started falling upon him and he started collecting them in his clothes. His Lord called him, 'O Job! Didn't I make you rich enough to dispense with what you see now?' Job said, 'Yes, O Lord! But I cannot dispense with Your Blessings</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="94" verse="5">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Surely with hardship there is ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So indeed with hardship is ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So truly with hardship comes ease,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then verily along with every hardship is ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So verily, with the hardship, there is relief,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>With hardship comes ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Indeed, there is ease with hardship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, along with every hardship is relief,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>But lo! with hardship goeth ease,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Indeed, hardship is followed by ease,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>For indeed, with hardship [will be] ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>After every difficulty there is relief.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely with difficulty is ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>So, surely with every hardship there is ease;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So, verily, with every difficulty, there is relief:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="94" verse="6">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>With hardship indeed there is ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed with hardship is ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>truly with hardship comes ease.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily along with every hardship is ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, with the hardship, there is relief (i.e. there is one hardship with two reliefs, so one hardship cannot overcome two reliefs).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>With hardship comes ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Most certainly, there is ease with hardship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, along with every hardship is relief.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! with hardship goeth ease;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>indeed, hardship is followed by ease!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, with hardship [will be] ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Certainly, after every difficulty there comes relief.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>With difficulty is surely ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>surely, with every hardship there is ease.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Verily, with every difficulty there is relief.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="153">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>O you who believe, seek courage in fortitude and prayer, for God is with those who are patient and persevere.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>O People who Believe! Seek help from patience and prayer; indeed Allah is with those who patiently endure.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>O all you who believe, seek you help in patience and prayer; surely God is with the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>O O Ye who believe! seek help in patience and prayer; verily Allah is with the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>O you who believe! Seek help in patience and As-Salat (the prayer). Truly! Allah is with As-Sabirin (the patient ones, etc.).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>O you who believe! Seek help through patience and prayers. God is with the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>O Believers, seek help with fortitude and Salat, for Allah is with those who show fortitude.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>O you who believe! Seek help in patience and As-Salah (the prayer). Truly, Allah is with As-Sabirin (the patient).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>O ye who believe! Seek help in steadfastness and prayer. Lo! Allah is with the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Believers, seek assistance in patience and prayer, Allah is with those who are patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>O you who have believed, seek help through patience and prayer. Indeed, Allah is with the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Believers, help yourselves (in your affairs) through patience and prayer; God is with those who have patience.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>O you who believe! seek assistance through patience and prayer; surely Allah is with the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>You who believe, seek help through patience and prayer; surely, God is with the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>O ye who believe! seek help with patient perseverance and prayer; for Allah is with those who patiently persevere.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="39" verse="10">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Tell them: "O my creatures who have come to belief, have fear of displeasing your Lord. There is good for those who do good in this world, and productive is God's earth. Only those who persevere will get their reward measureless."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Proclaim (O dear Prophet Mohammed – peace and blessings be upon him), “O my slaves who have accepted faith! Fear your Lord; for those who do good deeds in this world is goodness (in return); and Allah’s earth is spacious; it is the steadfast who will be paid their full reward, without account.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Say: 'My servants who believe, fear your Lord. For those who do good in this world good, and God's earth is wide. Surely the patient will be paid their wages in full without reckoning.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Say thou: O Mine bondmen who believe! fear your Lord. For those who do good in this world there is good: and Allah's earth is spacious. Verily the patient shall be paid in full their hire without reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Say (O Muhammad SAW): "O My slaves who believe (in the Oneness of Allah Islamic Monotheism), be afraid of your Lord (Allah) and keep your duty to Him. Good is (the reward) for those who do good in this world, and Allah's earth is spacious (so if you cannot worship Allah at a place, then go to another)! Only those who are patient shall receive their rewards in full, without reckoning."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Say, “O My devotees who have believed, keep your duty to your Lord. For those who do good in this world, is goodness. And God’s earth is vast. The steadfast will be paid their wages in full, without reckoning.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Tell them (O Prophet): “O you servants of Mine who believe, have fear of your Lord. A good end awaits those who did good in this world. Allah's earth is spacious. Verily those who persevere shall be granted their reward beyond all reckoning.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Say: "O My servants who believe, have Taqwa of your Lord. Good is for those who do good in this world, and Allah's earth is spacious! Only those who are patient shall receive their reward in full, without reckoning."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Say: O My bondmen who believe! Observe your duty to your Lord. For those who do good in this world there is good, and Allah's earth is spacious. Verily the steadfast will be paid their wages without stint.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Say: 'My worshipers who believe, fear your Lord. For those who do good in this world there is good and the earth of Allah is wide surely, those who are patient will be recompensed in full without count'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Say, "O My servants who have believed, fear your Lord. For those who do good in this world is good, and the earth of Allah is spacious. Indeed, the patient will be given their reward without account."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Say to My believing servants, "Have fear of your Lord. Those who act righteously in this life will receive good reward. The land of God is vast. God will recompense the deeds of those who have exercised patience, without keeping an account".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Say: O my servants who believe! be careful of (your duty to) your Lord; for those who do good in this world is good, and Allah's earth is spacious; only the patient will be paid back their reward in full without measure.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Say, "[God says] O My servants who have believed, fear your Lord. For those who do good in this world will have a good reward -- and God's earth is spacious. Truly, those who persevere patiently will be requited without measure."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Say: "O ye my servants who believe! Fear your Lord, good is (the reward) for those who do good in this world. Spacious is Allah's earth! those who patiently persevere will truly receive a reward without measure!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>