<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="ismail ishaq" generated="2026-03-30T00:19:28.739Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story of Ishmael &amp; Isaac (Ismail &amp; Ishaq)</title>
    <verses_count>55</verses_count>
    <translations_count>783</translations_count>
    <reordered>2026-03-30T00:19:28.756Z</reordered>
    <reorder_source>ismail_ishaq_reorder.csv</reorder_source>
  </metadata>
  <verses>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="100">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(And he prayed:) "O Lord, grant me a righteous son."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“My Lord! Give me a meritorious child.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>My Lord, give me one of the righteous.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>My Lord! Bestow on me a son who will be of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"My Lord! Grant me (offspring) from the righteous."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“My Lord, give me one of the righteous.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Lord, grant me a righteous son.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"My Lord! Grant me (offspring) from the righteous."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>My Lord! Vouchsafe me of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>My Lord, grant me a righteous (son)'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>My Lord, grant me [a child] from among the righteous."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Abraham prayed, "Lord, grant me a righteous son".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>My Lord! grant me of the doers of good deeds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Lord, grant me a righteous son."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"O my Lord! Grant me a righteous (son)!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="35">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Remember when Abraham prayed: "O Lord, make this a city of peace, and preserve me and my progeny from worshipping idols:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember when Ibrahim prayed, “O my Lord! Make this town (Mecca) a safe one, and safeguard me and my sons from worshipping idols.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when Abraham said, 'My Lord, make this land secure, and turn me and my sons away from serving idols;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time Ibrahim said: my Lord! make this City secure and keep me and my sons away from worshipping the idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) said: "O my Lord! Make this city (Makkah) one of peace and security, and keep me and my sons away from worshipping idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Recall that Abraham said, “O my Lord, make this land peaceful, and keep me and my sons from worshiping idols.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And call to mind when Abraham prayed: "My Lord! Make this city secure, and keep me and my sons away from worshipping the idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim said: "O my Lord! Make this city (Makkah) one of peace and security, and keep me and my sons away from worshipping idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when Abraham said: My Lord! Make safe this territory, and preserve me and my sons from serving idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when Abraham said: 'My Lord, make this a land secure. Turn me and my children away from worshipping idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention, O Muhammad], when Abraham said, "My Lord, make this city [Makkah] secure and keep me and my sons away from worshipping idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), consider when Abraham prayed, "Lord, make this (Mecca) a peaceful territory and save me and my offspring from worshipping idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when Ibrahim said: My Lord! make this city secure, and save me and my sons from worshipping idols:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>[Remember] when Abraham said, "My Lord, make this a city of peace and help me and my children to keep away from worshipping idols.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Remember Abraham said: "O my Lord! make this city one of peace and security: and preserve me and my sons from worshipping idols.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="36">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Many a man have they led astray, O Lord. So he who follows me is truly of me; but as for him who disobeys me, surely You are forgiving and kind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“O my Lord! The idols have led many people astray; so whoever followed me, is indeed mine; and whoever disobeyed me – then indeed You are Oft Forgiving, Most Merciful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>my Lord, they have led astray many men. Then whoso follows me belongs to me; and whoso rebels against me, surely Thou art All-forgiving, All-compassionate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>My Lord! they have sent astray many among mankind; whosoever followeth me, verily he is of me; and whosoever disobeyeth me, then verily Thou art Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"O my Lord! They have indeed led astray many among mankind. But whoso follows me, he verily is of me. And whoso disobeys me, - still You are indeed Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“My Lord, they have led many people astray. Whoever follows me belongs with me; and whoever disobeys me—You are Forgiving and Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>My Lord! They have caused many people to go astray. Now, if anyone follows my way, he is from me; and if anyone follows a way opposed to mine, then surely You are Ever-Forgiving, Most Merciful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"O my Lord! They have indeed led astray many among mankind. But whoso follows me, he verily, is of me. And whoso disobeys me, still You are indeed Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>My Lord! Lo! they have led many of mankind astray. But whoso followeth me, he verily is of me. And whoso disobeyeth me - Still Thou art Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>My Lord they have led many people astray. Whosoever follows me belongs to me. Whosoever rebels against me, You are surely Forgiving, the MostMerciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>My Lord, indeed they have led astray many among the people. So whoever follows me - then he is of me; and whoever disobeys me - indeed, You are [yet] Forgiving and Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Lord, the idols have misled many people. Whoever follows me is my friend. As for those who disobey, You are certainly All-forgiving and All-merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>My Lord! surely they have led many men astray; then whoever follows me, he is surely of me, and whoever disobeys me, Thou surely art Forgiving, Merciful:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>My Lord, they have led so many men astray! Anyone who follows me is with me, but if anyone turns against me, You are surely forgiving and merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"O my Lord! they have indeed led astray many among mankind; He then who follows my (ways) is of me, and he that disobeys me,- but Thou art indeed Oft-forgiving, Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="101">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We gave him the good news of a clement son.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>We therefore gave him the glad tidings of an intelligent son.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Then We gave him the good tidings of a prudent boy;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Wherefore We gave him the glad tidings of a boy gentle.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So We gave him the glad tidings of a forbearing boy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>So We gave him good news of a clement boy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(In response to this prayer) We gave him the good news of a prudent boy;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So, We gave him the glad tidings of a forbearing boy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>So We gave him tidings of a gentle son.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And We gave him the glad tidings of a very gentle son (Ishmael).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So We gave him good tidings of a forbearing boy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave him the glad news of the birth of a forbearing son.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So We gave him the good news of a boy, possessing forbearance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave him the good news that he would have a patient, forbearing son.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So We gave him the good news of a boy ready to suffer and forbear.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="53">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"Have no fear," they said. "We bring you news of a son full of wisdom."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>They said, “Do not fear – we convey to you the glad tidings of a knowledgeable boy.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>They said, 'Be not afraid; behold, we give thee good tidings of a cunning boy.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>They said: be not afraid; verily we bear thou the glad tidings of a boy knowing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They (the angels) said: "Do not be afraid! We give you glad tidings of a boy (son) possessing much knowledge and wisdom."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>They said, “Do not fear; we bring you good news of a boy endowed with knowledge.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>They said: "Do not feel afraid, for we give you the good news of a wise boy."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They said: "Do not be afraid! We bring you the good news of a boy possessing much knowledge and wisdom."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>They said: Be not afraid! Lo! we bring thee good tidings of a boy possessing wisdom.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>'Do not be afraid' they answered. 'We come to give you glad tidings of a knowledgeable child'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[The angels] said, "Fear not. Indeed, we give you good tidings of a learned boy."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They replied, "Do not be afraid. We have brought you the glad news of (the birth) of a learned son".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>They said: Be not afraid, surely we give you the good news of a boy, possessing knowledge.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They said, "Do not be afraid. We come to you with good news. You shall have a son who shall be endowed with great knowledge."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They said: "Fear not! We give thee glad tidings of a son endowed with wisdom."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="54">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"You bring me the good news now," he said, "when old age has come upon me. What good news are you giving me then?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He said, “Do you convey to me the glad tidings upon old age reaching me? So upon what do you convey glad tidings?” (* Prophet Ibrahim said this out of surprise.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>He said, 'What, do you give me good tidings, though old age has smitten me? Of what do you</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He said: bear ye me glad tidings when old age hath touched me? of what then ye bear me glad tidings?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>[Ibrahim (Abraham)] said: "Do you give me glad tidings (of a son) when old age has overtaken me? Of what then is your news?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “Do you bring me good news, when old age has overtaken me? What good news do you bring?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Abraham said: "What, do you give me this tiding though old age has smitten me? Just consider what tiding do you give me!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He said: "Do you give me this good news while old age has overtaken me Of what then is your news about"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He said: Bring ye me good tidings (of a son) when old age hath overtaken me? Of what then can ye bring good tidings?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He said: 'What is this, do you bring me glad tidings even though I am old' Of what do you give me glad tidings'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>He said, "Have you given me good tidings although old age has come upon me? Then of what [wonder] do you inform?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Abraham asked, "Are you giving me the glad news of a son in my old age? What reason can you give for such glad news?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: Do you give me good news (of a son) when old age has come upon me?-- Of what then do you give me good news!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>He said, "Do you bring me such news despite my old age? What kind of good news are you bringing me?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He said: "Do ye give me glad tidings that old age has seized me? Of what, then, is your good news?"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="15" verse="55">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"We have given you the happy tidings of a truth," they replied. "So do not be one of those who despair."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>They said, “We have given you true tidings, therefore do not lose hope.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>give me good tidings?' They said, 'We give thee good tidings of truth. Be not of those that despair.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>They said: we bear tidings of a truth; be then thou not of the desponding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They (the angels) said: "We give you glad tidings in truth. So be not of the despairing ones."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>They said, “We bring you good news in truth, so do not despair.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>They said: "The good tiding we give you is of truth. Do not, therefore, be of those who despair."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They said: "We give you good news in truth. So do not be of those who despair."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>They said: We bring thee good tidings in truth. So be not thou of the despairing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>They replied: 'In truth we have given you glad tidings, do not be one of those who despair'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>They said, "We have given you good tidings in truth, so do not be of the despairing."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They said, "We have given you the glad news for a true reason so do not despair".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>They said: We give you good news with truth, therefore be not of the despairing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They said, "We have, indeed, given you glad tidings in truth; do not therefore despair."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They said: "We give thee glad tidings in truth: be not then in despair!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="37">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>I have settled some of my children, O Lord, in a barren valley near Your sacred House, so that, O our Lord, they may be constant in devotion. So put in the hearts of men some kindness for them, and provide fruits for them: They may haply be grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“O our Lord! I have settled some of my descendants in a valley having no cultivation, near Your Sacred House – O our Lord! So that they may keep the prayer established, therefore incline some hearts of men towards them, and provide them fruits to eat – perhaps they may be thankful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Our Lord, I have made some of my seed to dwell in a valley where is no sown land by Thy Holy House; Our Lord, let them perform the prayer, and make hearts of men yearn towards them, and provide them with fruits; haply they will be thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Our Lord! verily have caused some of my progeny to dwell in a valley uncultivable near Thy Sacred House, Our Lord! in order that they may establish prayer; make Thou therefore the hearts of some of mankind to Yearn toward them, and provide them Thou With fruits, haply they may give thanks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"O our Lord! I have made some of my offspring to dwell in an uncultivable valley by Your Sacred House (the Ka'bah at Makkah); in order, O our Lord, that they may perform As-Salat (Iqamat-as-Salat), so fill some hearts among men with love towards them, and (O Allah) provide them with fruits so that they may give thanks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“Our Lord, I have settled some of my offspring in a valley of no vegetation, by Your Sacred House, our Lord, so that they may perform the prayers. So make the hearts of some people incline towards them, and provide them with fruits, that they may be thankful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>"Our Lord! I have made some of my offspring settle in a barren valley near Your Sacred House! Our Lord! I did so that they may establish Prayer. So make the hearts of people affectionately inclined to them, and provide them with fruits for their sustenance that they may give thanks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"O our Lord! I have made some of my offspring dwell in an uncultivable valley by Your Sacred House in order, O our Lord, that they may perform Salah. So fill some hearts among men with love towards them, and (O Allah) provide them with fruits so that they may give thanks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Our Lord! Lo! I have settled some of my posterity in an uncultivable valley near unto Thy holy House, our Lord! that they may establish proper worship; so incline some hearts of men that they may yearn toward them, and provide Thou them with fruits in order that they may be thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>'Our Lord, I have settled some of my offspring in a barren valley near Your Holy House; our Lord, in order that they establish the prayer. Make the hearts of people yearn towards them, and provide them with fruits, in order that they are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Our Lord, I have settled some of my descendants in an uncultivated valley near Your sacred House, our Lord, that they may establish prayer. So make hearts among the people incline toward them and provide for them from the fruits that they might be grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>"Lord, I have settled some of my offspring in a barren valley near your Sacred House so that they could be steadfast in prayer. Lord, fill the hearts of the people with love for them and produce fruits for their sustenance so that they may give thanks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>O our Lord! surely I have settled a part of my offspring in a valley unproductive of fruit near Thy Sacred House, our Lord! that they may keep up prayer; therefore make the hearts of some people yearn towards them and provide them with fruits; haply they may be grateful:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>O Lord! I have settled some of my offspring in an uncultivable valley near Your Sacred House, Lord, so that they might establish their prayers. So, make people's hearts incline towards them and provide them with fruits so that they may be grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"O our Lord! I have made some of my offspring to dwell in a valley without cultivation, by Thy Sacred House; in order, O our Lord, that they may establish regular Prayer: so fill the hearts of some among men with love towards them, and feed them with fruits: so that they may give thanks.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="38">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>O Lord, You have knowledge of what we hide and what we reveal, for nothing on the earth or in the skies is hidden from God.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“O our Lord! You know what we hide and what we disclose; and nothing is hidden from Allah, neither in the earth nor in the heavens.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Our Lord, Thou knowest what we keep secret and what we publish; from God nothing whatever is hidden in earth and heaven.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Our Lord! verily Thou knowest that which We conceal and that which We make known; and not of aught is concealed from Allah in the earth or in the heaven.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"O our Lord! Certainly, You know what we conceal and what we reveal. Nothing on the earth or in the heaven is hidden from Allah.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“Our Lord, You know what we conceal and what we reveal. And nothing is hidden from God, on earth or in the heaven.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Our Lord! Surely You know all that we conceal and all that we reveal, and nothing in the earth or in the heaven is hidden from Allah.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"O our Lord! Certainly, You know what we conceal and what we reveal. Nothing on the earth or in the heaven is hidden from Allah."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Our Lord! Lo! Thou knowest that which we hide and that which we proclaim. Nothing in the earth or in the heaven is hidden from Allah.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Our Lord, You have knowledge of all that we hide and all that we reveal; nothing in heaven or earth is hidden from Allah.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Our Lord, indeed You know what we conceal and what we declare, and nothing is hidden from Allah on the earth or in the heaven.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Lord, You know all that we conceal or reveal. Nothing in the heavens or the earth is hidden from God.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>O our Lord! Surely Thou knowest what we hide and what we make public, and nothing in the earth nor any thing in heaven is hidden from Allah:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Lord, You have knowledge of all that we hide and all that we reveal: nothing in heaven or on earth is hidden from God.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"O our Lord! truly Thou dost know what we conceal and what we reveal: for nothing whatever is hidden from Allah, whether on earth or in heaven.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="39">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>All praise be to God who bestowed on me Ishmael and Isaac in old age. Verily my Lord listens to prayer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“All praise is to Allah Who gave me Ismail and Ishaq, in my old age; indeed my Lord is the Listener of Prayer.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Praise be to God, who has given me, though I am old, Ishmael and Isaac; surely my Lord hears the petition.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>All praise be unto Allah who hath bestowed upon me, despite old age lsma'il and ls-haq; verily my Lord is the Hearer of supplication.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"All the praises and thanks be to Allah, Who has given me in old age Isma'il (Ishmael) and Ishaque (Isaac). Verily! My Lord is indeed the All-Hearer of invocations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“Praise be to God, Who has given me, in my old age, Ishmael and Isaac. My Lord is the Hearer of Prayers.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>All praise be to Allah Who, despite my old age, has given me Ishmael and Isaac. Surely my Lord hears all prayers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"All praise is due to Allah, Who has given me in old age Isma'il and Ishaq. Verily, my Lord is indeed the All-Hearer of invocations."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Praise be to Allah Who hath given me, in my old age, Ishmael and Isaac! Lo! my Lord is indeed the Hearer of Prayer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Praise be to Allah who has given me Ishmael and Isaac in my old age! Indeed, my Lord is the Hearer of the supplication.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Praise to Allah, who has granted to me in old age Ishmael and Isaac. Indeed, my Lord is the Hearer of supplication.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>It is only God who deserves all praise. I praise Him for His giving me my sons Ishmael and Isaac during my old age. My Lord, certainly, hears all prayers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Praise be to Allah, Who has given me in old age Ismail and Ishaq; most surely my Lord is the Hearer of prayer:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Praise be to God who has bestowed upon me, despite my old age, Ishmael and Isaac. Surely my Lord is the hearer of prayer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Praise be to Allah, Who hath granted unto me in old age Isma'il and Isaac: for truly my Lord is He, the Hearer of Prayer!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="40">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Grant, O Lord, that I and my offspring may remain constant in devotion. Grant, O Lord, my supplication.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“O my Lord! Maintain me as one who establishes prayer, and some of my descendants; O our Lord! and accept my prayer.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>My Lord, make me a performer of the prayer, and of my seed. Our Lord, and receive my petition.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>My Lord! make me establisher of prayer and also from my progeny, our Lord! and accept Thou my supplication.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"O my Lord! Make me one who performs As-Salat (Iqamat-as-Salat), and (also) from my offspring, our Lord! And accept my invocation.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“My Lord, make me one who performs the prayer, and from my offspring. Our Lord, accept my supplication.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>My Lord! Enable me and my offspring to establish Prayer, and do accept, our Lord, this prayer of mine.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"O my Lord! Make me one who performs Salah, and (also) from my offspring, our Lord! And accept my invocation."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>My Lord! Make me to establish proper worship, and some of my posterity (also); our Lord! and accept my prayer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>My Lord, make me and my descendants establishers of prayer. Our Lord, accept my prayer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>My Lord, make me an establisher of prayer, and [many] from my descendants. Our Lord, and accept my supplication.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Lord, make me and my offspring steadfast in prayer and accept our worship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>My Lord! make me keep up prayer and from my offspring (too), O our Lord, and accept my prayer:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Lord, grant that I may keep up the prayer, and so may my offspring. My Lord, accept my prayer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>O my Lord! make me one who establishes regular Prayer, and also (raise such) among my offspring O our Lord! and accept Thou my Prayer.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="41">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>O Lord, forgive me, my parents and the faithful on the Day the reckoning is done."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“O our Lord! And forgive me, and my parents, and all the Muslims on the day when the account will be established.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Our Lord, forgive Thou me and my parents, and the believers, upon the day when the reckoning shall come to pass.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Our Lord! forgive me and my parents and the believers on the Day whereon will be set up the reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"Our Lord! Forgive me and my parents, and (all) the believers on the Day when the reckoning will be established."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“Our Lord, forgive me, and my parents, and the believers, on the Day the Reckoning takes place.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Our Lord! Forgive me and my parents and the believers on the Day when the reckoning will take place."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Our Lord! Forgive me and my parents, and (all) the believers on the Day when the reckoning will be established."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Our Lord! Forgive me and my parents and believers on the day when the account is cast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Forgive me, our Lord, and forgive my parents and all the believers on the Day of Reckoning'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Our Lord, forgive me and my parents and the believers the Day the account is established."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Lord, on the Day of Judgment, forgive me and my parents and all the believers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>O our Lord! grant me protection and my parents and the believers on the day when the reckoning shall come to pass!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Forgive me, Lord, and forgive my parents and all the believers on the Day of Reckoning."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"O our Lord! cover (us) with Thy Forgiveness - me, my parents, and (all) Believers, on the Day that the Reckoning will be established!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="583">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The first lady to use a girdle was the mother of Ishmael. She used a girdle so that she might hide her tracks from Sarah. Abraham brought her and her son Ishmael while she was suckling him, to a place near the Ka'ba under a tree on the spot of Zam-zam, at the highest place in the mosque. During those days there was nobody in Mecca, nor was there any water So he made them sit over there and placed near them a leather bag containing some dates, and a small water-skin containing some water, and set out homeward. Ishmael's mother followed him saying, "O Abraham! Where are you going, leaving us in this valley where there is no person whose company we may enjoy, nor is there anything (to enjoy)?" She repeated that to him many times, but he did not look back at her Then she asked him, "Has Allah ordered you to do so?" He said, "Yes." She said, "Then He will not neglect us," and returned while Abraham proceeded onwards, and on reaching the Thaniya where they could not see him, he faced the Ka'ba, and raising both hands, invoked Allah saying the following prayers:
'O our Lord! I have made some of my offspring dwell in a valley without cultivation, by Your Sacred House (Kaba at Mecca) in order, O our Lord, that they may offer prayer perfectly. So fill some hearts among men with love towards them, and (O Allah) provide them with fruits, so that they may give thanks.' (14.37) Ishmael's mother went on suckling Ishmael and drinking from the water (she had).
When the water in the water-skin had all been used up, she became thirsty and her child also became thirsty. She started looking at him (i.e. Ishmael) tossing in agony; She left him, for she could not endure looking at him, and found that the mountain of Safa was the nearest mountain to her on that land. She stood on it and started looking at the valley keenly so that she might see somebody, but she could not see anybody. Then she descended from Safa and when she reached the valley, she tucked up her robe and ran in the valley like a person in distress and trouble, till she crossed the valley and reached the Marwa mountain where she stood and started looking, expecting to see somebody, but she could not see anybody. She repeated that (running between Safa and Marwa) seven times."
The Prophet said, "This is the source of the tradition of the walking of people between them (i.e. Safa and Marwa). When she reached the Marwa (for the last time) she heard a voice and she asked herself to be quiet and listened attentively. She heard the voice again and said, 'O, (whoever you may be)! You have made me hear your voice; have you got something to help me?" And behold! She saw an angel at the place of Zam-zam, digging the earth with his heel (or his wing), till water flowed from that place. She started to make something like a basin around it, using her hand in this way, and started filling her water-skin with water with her hands, and the water was flowing out after she had scooped some of it."
The Prophet added, "May Allah bestow Mercy on Ishmael's mother! Had she let the Zam-zam (flow without trying to control it) (or had she not scooped from that water) (to fill her water-skin), Zam-zam would have been a stream flowing on the surface of the earth." The Prophet further added, "Then she drank (water) and suckled her child. The angel said to her, 'Don't be afraid of being neglected, for this is the House of Allah which will be built by this boy and his father, and Allah never neglects His people.' The House (i.e. Kaba) at that time was on a high place resembling a hillock, and when torrents came, they flowed to its right and left. She lived in that way till some people from the tribe of Jurhum or a family from Jurhum passed by her and her child, as they (i.e. the Jurhum people) were coming through the way of Kada'. They landed in the lower part of Mecca where they saw a bird that had the habit of flying around water and not leaving it. They said, 'This bird must be flying around water, though we know that there is no water in this valley.' They sent one or two messengers who discovered the source of water, and returned to inform them of the water. So, they all came (towards the water)." The Prophet added, "Ishmael's mother was sitting near the water. They asked her, 'Do you allow us to stay with you?" She replied, 'Yes, but you will have no right to possess the water.' They agreed to that." The Prophet further said, "Ishmael's mother was pleased with the whole situation as she used to love to enjoy the company of the people. So, they settled there, and later on they sent for their families who came and settled with them so that some families became permanent residents there. The child (i.e. Ishmael) grew up and learnt Arabic from them and (his virtues) caused them to love and admire him as he grew up, and when he reached the age of puberty they made him marry a woman from amongst them.
After Ishmael's mother had died, Abraham came after Ishmael's marriage in order to see his family that he had left before, but he did not find Ishmael there. When he asked Ishmael's wife about him, she replied, 'He has gone in search of our livelihood.' Then he asked her about their way of living and their condition, and she replied, 'We are living in misery; we are living in hardship and destitution,' complaining to him. He said, 'When your husband returns, convey my salutation to him and tell him to change the threshold of the gate (of his house).' When Ishmael came, he seemed to have felt something unusual, so he asked his wife, 'Has anyone visited you?' She replied, 'Yes, an old man of so-and-so description came and asked me about you and I informed him, and he asked about our state of living, and I told him that we were living in a hardship and poverty.' On that Ishmael said, 'Did he advise you anything?' She replied, 'Yes, he told me to convey his salutation to you and to tell you to change the threshold of your gate.' Ishmael said, 'It was my father, and he has ordered me to divorce you. Go back to your family.' So, Ishmael divorced her and married another woman from amongst them (i.e. Jurhum).
Then Abraham stayed away from them for a period as long as Allah wished and called on them again but did not find Ishmael. So he came to Ishmael's wife and asked her about Ishmael. She said, 'He has gone in search of our livelihood.' Abraham asked her, 'How are you getting on?' asking her about their sustenance and living. She replied, 'We are prosperous and well-off (i.e. we have everything in abundance).' Then she thanked Allah' Abraham said, 'What kind of food do you eat?' She said. 'Meat.' He said, 'What do you drink?' She said, 'Water." He said, "O Allah! Bless their meat and water." The Prophet added, "At that time they did not have grain, and if they had grain, he would have also invoked Allah to bless it." The Prophet added, "If somebody has only these two things as his sustenance, his health and disposition will be badly affected, unless he lives in Mecca." The Prophet added," Then Abraham said Ishmael's wife, "When your husband comes, give my regards to him and tell him that he should keep firm the threshold of his gate.' When Ishmael came back, he asked his wife, 'Did anyone call on you?' She replied, 'Yes, a good-looking old man came to me,' so she praised him and added. 'He asked about you, and I informed him, and he asked about our livelihood and I told him that we were in a good condition.' Ishmael asked her, 'Did he give you any piece of advice?' She said, 'Yes, he told me to give his regards to you and ordered that you should keep firm the threshold of your gate.' On that Ishmael said, 'It was my father, and you are the threshold (of the gate). He has ordered me to keep you with me.'
Then Abraham stayed away from them for a period as long as Allah wished, and called on them afterwards. He saw Ishmael under a tree near Zamzam, sharpening his arrows. When he saw Abraham, he rose up to welcome him (and they greeted each other as a father does with his son or a son does with his father). Abraham said, 'O Ishmael! Allah has given me an order.' Ishmael said, 'Do what your Lord has ordered you to do.' Abraham asked, 'Will you help me?' Ishmael said, 'I will help you.' Abraham said, Allah has ordered me to build a house here,' pointing to a hillock higher than the land surrounding it." The Prophet added, "Then they raised the foundations of the House (i.e. the Ka'ba). Ishmael brought the stones and Abraham was building, and when the walls became high, Ishmael brought this stone and put it for Abraham who stood over it and carried on building, while Ishmael was handing him the stones, and both of them were saying, 'O our Lord! Accept (this service) from us, Verily, You are the All-Hearing, the All-Knowing.' The Prophet added, "Then both of them went on building and going round the Ka'ba saying: O our Lord ! Accept (this service) from us, Verily, You are the All-Hearing, the All-Knowing." (2.127)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="582">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas:
The Prophet said, "May Allah bestow His Mercy on the mother of Ishmael! Had she not hastened (to fill her water-skin with water from the Zam-zam well). Zam-zam would have been a stream flowing on the surface of the earth." Ibn 'Abbas further added, "(The Prophet) Abraham brought Ishmael and his mother (to Mecca) and she was suckling Ishmael and she had a water-skin with her.'</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="102">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When he was old enough to go about with him, he said: "O my son, I dreamt that I was sacrificing you. Consider, what you think?" He replied: "Father, do as you are commanded. If God pleases you will find me firm."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And when he became capable of working with him, Ibrahim said, “O my son, I dreamt that I am sacrificing you – therefore now consider what is your opinion”; he said, “O my father! Do what you are commanded! Allah willing, you will soon find me patiently enduring!”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and when he had reached the age of running with him, he said, 'My son, I see in a dream that I shall sacrifice thee; consider, what thinkest thou?' He said, 'My father, do as thou art bidden; thou shalt find me, God willing, one of the steadfast.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And when he attained the age of, running with him, he said: O my son! verily I have seen in a dream that I am slaughtering thee; so look, what considerest thou? He said: O my father! do that which thou art commanded; thou shalt find me, Allah willing, of the patients.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And, when he (his son) was old enough to walk with him, he said: "O my son! I have seen in a dream that I am slaughtering you (offer you in sacrifice to Allah), so look what you think!" He said: "O my father! Do that which you are commanded, Insha' Allah (if Allah will), you shall find me of As-Sabirin (the patient ones, etc.)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then, when he was old enough to accompany him, he said, “O My son, I see in a dream that I am sacrificing you; see what you think.” He said, “O my Father, do as you are commanded; you will find me, God willing, one of the steadfast.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and when he was old enough to go about and work with him, (one day) Abraham said to him: “My son, I see in my dream that I am slaughtering you. So consider (and tell me) what you think.” He said: “Do as you are bidden. You will find me, if Allah so wills, among the steadfast.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And, when he (his son) was old enough to walk with him, he said: "O my son! I have seen in a dream that I am slaughtering you. So look what you think!" He said: "O my father! Do that which you are commanded, if Allah wills, you shall find me of the patient."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when (his son) was old enough to walk with him, (Abraham) said: O my dear son, I have seen in a dream that I must sacrifice thee. So look, what thinkest thou? He said: O my father! Do that which thou art commanded. Allah willing, thou shalt find me of the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when he reached the age of traveling with him, he said: 'My son, while I was sleeping I saw that I shall slaughter (sacrifice) you, tell me what is your opinion' He replied: 'Father, do as you are ordered (by Allah). Allah willing, you shall find me one of those who are steadfast'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And when he reached with him [the age of] exertion, he said, "O my son, indeed I have seen in a dream that I [must] sacrifice you, so see what you think." He said, "O my father, do as you are commanded. You will find me, if Allah wills, of the steadfast."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When his son was old enough to work with him, he said, "My son, I have had a dream that I must sacrifice you. What do you think of this?" He replied, "Father, fulfill whatever you are commanded to do and you will find me patient, by the will of God".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when he attained to working with him, he said: O my son! surely I have seen in a dream that I should sacrifice you; consider then what you see. He said: O my father! do what you are commanded; if Allah please, you will find me of the patient ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>And when he reached the age when he could work with him, he said, "O my son, I have seen in a dream that I am sacrificing you. So tell me what you think of it!" He replied, "O my father, do as you are commanded; and God willing, you will find me steadfast."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Then, when (the son) reached (the age of) (serious) work with him, he said: "O my son! I see in vision that I offer thee in sacrifice: Now see what is thy view!" (The son) said: "O my father! Do as thou art commanded: thou will find me, if Allah so wills one practising Patience and Constancy!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="103">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When they submitted to the will of God, and (Abraham) laid (his son) down prostrate on his temple,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Then (remember) when they both submitted to Allah’s command, and Ibrahim lay his son facing downwards. (The knife did not hurt Ismail)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>When they had surrendered, and he flung him upon his brow,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then when the twain had submitted themselves and he had prostrated him upon his temple.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Then, when they had both submitted themselves (to the Will of Allah), and he had laid him prostrate on his forehead (or on the side of his forehead for slaughtering);</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then, when they had submitted, and he put his forehead down.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>When both surrendered (to Allah's command) and Abraham flung the son down on his forehead,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then, when they had both submitted themselves, and he had laid him prostrate on his forehead;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Then, when they had both surrendered (to Allah), and he had flung him down upon his face,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when they had both submitted, and his son had laid down prostrate upon his forehead,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And when they had both submitted and he put him down upon his forehead,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When they both agreed and Abraham had lain down his son on the side of his face (for slaughtering),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So when they both submitted and he threw him down upon his forehead,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When they had both submitted to God, and he had laid his son down on his face,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So when they had both submitted their wills (to Allah), and he had laid him prostrate on his forehead (for sacrifice),</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="104">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We called out: "O Abraham,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We called out to him, “O Ibrahim!”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We called unto him, 'Abraham,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>We cried Unto him: O Ibrahim</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We called out to him: "O Abraham!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We called out to him, “O Abraham!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We cried out: “O Abraham,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>We called out to him: "O Ibrahim!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>We called unto him: O Abraham!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We called to him, saying: 'O Abraham,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>We called to him, "O Abraham,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We called to him, "Abraham,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We called out to him saying: O Ibrahim!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We called out to him, "Abraham,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We called out to him "O Abraham!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="105">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>You have fulfilled your dream." Thus do We reward the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“You have indeed made the dream come true”; and this is how We reward the virtuous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>thou hast confirmed the vision; even so We recompense the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Of a surety thou hast fulfilled the vision. Verily We! thus We recompense the well-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>You have fulfilled the dream (vision)!" Verily! Thus do We reward the Muhsinun (good-doers - see V. 2:112).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>You have fulfilled the vision.” Thus We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>you have indeed fulfilled your dream. Thus do We reward the good-doers.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"You have fulfilled the dream!" Verily, thus do We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Thou hast already fulfilled the vision. Lo! thus do We reward the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>you have confirmed your vision' As such We recompense the gooddoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>You have fulfilled the vision." Indeed, We thus reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>you have fulfilled what you were commanded to do in your dream." Thus do We reward the righteous ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>You have indeed shown the truth of the vision; surely thus do We reward the doers of good:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>you have fulfilled the dream." It is thus indeed that We reward those who do good,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Thou hast already fulfilled the vision!" - thus indeed do We reward those who do right.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="106">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>That was indeed a trying test.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed this was a clear test.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>This is indeed the manifest trial.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily that! that was a trial manifest.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, that indeed was a manifest trial</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>This was certainly an evident test.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>This was indeed a plain trial.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, that indeed was a manifest trial.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! that verily was a clear test.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>That was indeed a clear trial.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, this was the clear trial.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>It was certainly an open trial.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Most surely this is a manifest trial.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>that surely was a manifest trial,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>For this was obviously a trial-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="107">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We ransomed him for a great sacrifice,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We rescued him in exchange of a great sacrifice. (The sacrifice of Ibrahim and Ismail – peace be upon them – is commemorated every year on 10, 11 and 12 Zil Haj).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We ransomed him with a mighty sacrifice,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We ransomed him with a mighty victim.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We ransomed him with a great sacrifice (i.e. a ram);</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We redeemed him with a great sacrifice.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We ransomed him with a mighty sacrifice,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We ransomed him with a great sacrifice;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Then We ransomed him with a tremendous victim.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>So, We ransomed him with a mighty sacrifice,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We ransomed him with a great sacrifice,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We ransomed his son with a great sacrifice</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We ransomed him with a Feat sacrifice.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We ransomed him with a great sacrifice,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We ransomed him with a momentous sacrifice:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="108">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And left (his hallowed memory) for posterity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We kept his praise among the latter generations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and left for him among the later folk</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We left for him among the posterity:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We left for him (a goodly remembrance) among generations (to come) in later times.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We left with him for later generations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and We preserved for him a good name among posterity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We left for him among the later generations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We left for him among the later folk (the salutation):</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and We let it (the beautiful praise) remain upon him in the latter (generations),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We left for him [favorable mention] among later generations:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>and perpetuated his praise in later generations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We perpetuated (praise) to him among the later generations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and left him thus to be succeeded by a group [of followers] among later generations:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We left (this blessing) for him among generations (to come) in later times:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="109">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Peace be on Abraham.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Peace be upon Ibrahim!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>'Peace be upon Abraham!'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Peace be Unto Ibrahim:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Salamun (peace) be upon Ibrahim (Abraham)!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Peace be upon Abraham.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Peace be upon Abraham.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Salam (peace!) be upon Ibrahim!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Peace be unto Abraham!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>'Peace be upon Abraham'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>"Peace upon Abraham."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Peace be with Abraham.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Peace be on Ibrahim.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>"Peace and salutation to Abraham!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Peace and salutation to Abraham!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="110">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>That is how We reward those who do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>This is how We reward the virtuous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Even so We recompense the good-doers;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We! thus We compense the well-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Thus indeed do We reward the Muhsinun (good-doers - see V. 2:112).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Thus We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Thus indeed do We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Thus do We reward the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>As such We recompense the gooddoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, We thus reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Thus, do We reward the righteous ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Thus do We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>That is how We recompense the righteous:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Thus indeed do We reward those who do right.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="111">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>He is truly among Our faithful creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He is indeed one of Our high ranking, firmly believing bondmen.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>he was among Our believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily he was one of Our believing bondmen.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, he was one of Our believing slaves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He was one of Our believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Surely he was one of Our believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, he was one of Our believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! he is one of Our believing slaves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He was one of Our believing worshipers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, he was of Our believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>He was one of Our believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely he was one of Our believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>truly, he was one of Our faithful servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>For he was one of our believing Servants.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="124">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Remember, when his Lord tried Abraham by a number of commands which he fulfilled, God said to him: "I will make you a leader among men." And when Abraham asked: "From my progeny too?" the Lord said: "My pledge does not include transgressors."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim’s (Abraham’s) Lord tested him in some matters and he fulfilled them; He said, “I am going to appoint you as a leader for mankind”; invoked Ibrahim, “And of my offspring”; He said, “My covenant does not include the unjust (wrong-doers).”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when his Lord tested Abraham with certain words, and he fulfilled them. He said, 'Behold, I make you a leader for the people.' Said he, 'And of my seed?' He said 'My covenant shall not reach the evildoers.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time his Lord Proved Ibrahim with certain words then he performed them. He said: verily I am going to make thee a leader unto mankind. Ibrahim said: and also of my progeny? Allah said: My covenant shall not reach the wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when the Lord of Ibrahim (Abraham) [i.e., Allah] tried him with (certain) Commands, which he fulfilled. He (Allah) said (to him), "Verily, I am going to make you a leader (Prophet) of mankind." [Ibrahim (Abraham)] said, "And of my offspring (to make leaders)." (Allah) said, "My Covenant (Prophethood, etc.) includes not Zalimun (polytheists and wrong-doers)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And when his Lord tested Abraham with certain words, and he fulfilled them. He said, “I am making you a leader of humanity.” He said, “And my descendants?” He said, “My pledge does not include the wrongdoers.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Recall to mind that when his Lord put Abraham to test in certain things and he fulfilled all of them, He said, "I am going to make you the leader of mankind." Abraham humbly asked, "Does this promise apply to my descendants also?" He replied, "My promise does not apply to the transgressors."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when the Lord of Ibrahim (Abraham) tried him with (certain) commands, which he fulfilled. He (Allah) said (to him), "Verily, I am going to make you an Imam (a leader) for mankind (to follow you)." (Ibrahim) said, "And of my offspring (to make leaders)." (Allah) said, "My covenant (prophethood) includes not Zalimin (polytheists and wrongdoers)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (remember) when his Lord tried Abraham with (His) commands, and he fulfilled them, He said: Lo! I have appointed thee a leader for mankind. (Abraham) said: And of my offspring (will there be leaders)? He said: My covenant includeth not wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when Abraham was tested by His Lord with certain words and he fulfilled them, He said: 'I have appointed you as a leader for the nation' (Abraham) asked: 'And of my descendants' 'My covenant' said He, 'the harmdoers shall not receive it'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention, O Muhammad], when Abraham was tried by his Lord with commands and he fulfilled them. [Allah] said, "Indeed, I will make you a leader for the people." [Abraham] said, "And of my descendants?" [Allah] said, "My covenant does not include the wrongdoers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When his Lord tested Abraham's faith, (by His words) and he satisfied the test, He said, "I am appointing you as the leader of mankind." Abraham asked, "Will this leadership also continue through my descendants?" The Lord replied, "The unjust do not have the right to exercise My authority."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when his Lord tried Ibrahim with certain words, he fulfilled them. He said: Surely I will make you an Imam of men. Ibrahim said: And of my offspring? My covenant does not include the unjust, said He.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When his Lord tested Abraham with certain commands and he fulfilled them, He said, "I will make you a leader of men." Abraham asked, "And what of my descendants?" He answered, "My covenant does not extend to the transgressors."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And remember that Abraham was tried by his Lord with certain commands, which he fulfilled: He said: "I will make thee an Imam to the Nations." He pleaded: "And also (Imams) from my offspring!" He answered: "But My Promise is not within the reach of evil-doers."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="125">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Remember, We made the House (of Ka'bah) a place of congregation and safe retreat, and said: "Make the spot where Abraham stood the place of worship;" and enjoined upon Abraham and Ishmael to keep Our House immaculate for those who shall walk around it and stay in it for contemplation and prayer, and for bowing in adoration.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember when We made this House (at Mecca) a recourse for mankind and a sanctuary; and take the place where Ibrahim stood, as your place of prayer; and We imposed a duty upon Ibrahim and Ismail (Ishmael), to fully purify My house for those who go around it, and those who stay in it (for worship), and those who bow down and prostrate themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when We appointed the House to be a place of visitation for the people, and a sanctuary, and: 'Take to yourselves Abraham's station for a place of prayer.' And We made covenant with Abraham and Ishmael: 'Purify My House for those that shall go about it and those that cleave to it, to those who bow and prostrate themselves.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time We appointed the House a resort unto man kind and a place of security and said: take the station of Ibrahim for a place of prayer. And We covenanted with Ibrahim and Ismai'l, saying: purify ye twain My Houses for those who shall circumambulate it and those who shall stay, and those who shall bow down and prostrate themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when We made the House (the Ka'bah at Makkah) a place of resort for mankind and a place of safety. And take you (people) the Maqam (place) of Ibrahim (Abraham) [or the stone on which Ibrahim (Abraham) stood while he was building the Ka'bah] as a place of prayer (for some of your prayers, e.g. two Rak'at after the Tawaf of the Ka'bah at Makkah), and We commanded Ibrahim (Abraham) and Isma'il (Ishmael) that they should purify My House (the Ka'bah at Makkah) for those who are circumambulating it, or staying (I'tikaf), or bowing or prostrating themselves (there, in prayer).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We made the House a focal point for the people, and a sanctuary. Use the shrine of Abraham as a place of prayer. And We commissioned Abraham and Ishmael, “Sanctify My House for those who circle around it, and those who seclude themselves in it, and those who kneel and prostrate.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And remember that We made this House (the Ka'bah) the centre and sanctuary for mankind and enjoined the people to dedicate to worship the place where Abraham used to stand for prayer, and We urged Abraham and Ismail to keep My House pure for those who would go round it and those who would retire to it for devotion and prayer and for those who would bow down and prostrate themselves there in worhsip.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when We made the House (the Ka`bah at Makkah) a place of resort for mankind and a place of safety. And take you (people) the Maqam (place) of Ibrahim as a place of prayer. And We commanded Ibrahim (Abraham) and Isma`il (Ishmael) that they should purify My House (the Ka`bah at Makkah) for those who are circumambulating it, or staying (I`tikaf), or bowing or prostrating themselves (there, in prayer).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when We made the House (at Makka) a resort for mankind and sanctuary, (saying): Take as your place of worship the place where Abraham stood (to pray). And We imposed a duty upon Abraham and Ishmael, (saying): Purify My house for those who go around and those who meditate therein and those who bow down and prostrate themselves (in worship).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when We made the House (Ka'bah) a visitation and a sanctuary for the people (saying:) 'Make the place where Abraham stood a place of prayer. 'And We made a covenant with Abraham and Ishmael: 'Purify My House for those who circumambulate around it, and those who cleave to it, to those who bow and prostrate'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] when We made the House a place of return for the people and [a place of] security. And take, [O believers], from the standing place of Abraham a place of prayer. And We charged Abraham and Ishmael, [saying], "Purify My House for those who perform Tawaf and those who are staying [there] for worship and those who bow and prostrate [in prayer]."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made the house (in Mecca) as a place of refuge and sanctuary for men. Adopt the place where Abraham stood as a place for prayer. We advised Abraham and Ishmael to keep My house clean for the pilgrims, the worshippers and for those who bow down and prostrate themselves in worship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when We made the House a pilgrimage for men and a (place of) security, and: Appoint for yourselves a place of prayer on the standing-place of Ibrahim. And We enjoined Ibrahim and Ismail saying: Purify My House for those who visit (it) and those who abide (in it) for devotion and those who bow down (and) those who prostrate themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>And We made the House [the Ka'bah] a place of assembly and a sanctuary for mankind, [saying], "Make the place where Abraham stood a place of worship." We commanded Abraham and Ishmael, "Purify My House for those who walk round it, those who stay there for devotion, and those who bow down and prostrate themselves."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Remember We made the House a place of assembly for men and a place of safety; and take ye the station of Abraham as a place of prayer; and We covenanted with Abraham and Isma'il, that they should sanctify My House for those who compass it round, or use it as a retreat, or bow, or prostrate themselves (therein in prayer).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="126">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And when Abraham said: "O Lord, make this a city of peace, and give those of its citizens who believe in God and the Last Day fruits for food," He answered: "To those will I also give a little who believe not, for a time, then drag them to Hell, a dreadful destination!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim prayed, “My Lord! Make this city a place of security and bestow upon its people various fruits as providence – for those among them who believe in Allah and the Last Day (of Resurrection)”; He answered, “And whoever disbelieves, I shall provide him also some subsistence and then compel him towards the punishment of fire (hell); and that is a wretched place to return.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when Abraham said, 'My Lord, make this a land secure, and provide its people with fruits, such of them as believe in God and the Last Day.' He said, 'And whoso disbelieves, to him I shall give enjoyment a little, then I shall compel him to the chastisement of the Fire -- how evil a homecoming!'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time Ibrahim said: my Lord! make this city a place of security, and provide the People thereof with fruits, - such of them as will believe in Allah and the last Day. Allah said: and whosoever will disbelieve, him also shall give enjoyment for a while; thereafter I shall drive him to the torment of the Fire, - an ill abode!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) said, "My Lord, make this city (Makkah) a place of security and provide its people with fruits, such of them as believe in Allah and the Last Day." He (Allah) answered: "As for him who disbelieves, I shall leave him in contentment for a while, then I shall compel him to the torment of the Fire, and worst indeed is that destination!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When Abraham said, “O My Lord, make this a peaceful land, and provide its people with fruits—whoever of them believes in God and the Last Day.” He said, “And whoever disbelieves, I will give him a little enjoyment, then I will consign him to the punishment of the Fire; how miserable the destiny!”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And remember that Abraham prayed, "Lord, make this city a city of peace and security, and provide with every kind of fruit those of its people, who believe in Allah and the Last Day'. Allah answered, "As for the disbelievers, I will also provide them with the necessities of life in this world, though in the Next World I will drag them to the torment of Hell, and that is the worst abode."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim said, "My Lord, make this city (Makkah) a place of security and provide its people with fruits, such of them as believe in Allah and the Last Day." He (Allah) answered: "As for him who disbelieves, I shall leave him in contentment for a while, then I shall compel him to the torment of the Fire, and worst indeed is that destination!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when Abraham prayed: My Lord! Make this a region of security and bestow upon its people fruits, such of them as believe in Allah and the Last Day, He answered: As for him who disbelieveth, I shall leave him in contentment for a while, then I shall compel him to the doom of Fire - a hapless journey's end!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when Abraham said: 'My Lord, make this country safe and provide its inhabitants whosoever of them believes in Allah and the Last Day with fruits' He said: 'And whosoever disbelieves, to him I shall give enjoyment for a while. Then I shall compel him to the punishment of the Fire, how evil an arrival'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] when Abraham said, "My Lord, make this a secure city and provide its people with fruits - whoever of them believes in Allah and the Last Day." [Allah] said. "And whoever disbelieves - I will grant him enjoyment for a little; then I will force him to the punishment of the Fire, and wretched is the destination."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When Abraham prayed to the Lord saying, "Lord, make this town a place of security and provide those in the town who believe in God and the Day of Judgement, with plenty," God replied, "I shall allow those who hide the truth to enjoy themselves for a while. Then I shall drive them into the torment of hell fire, a terrible destination!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when Ibrahim said: My Lord, make it a secure town and provide its people with fruits, such of them as believe in Allah and the last day. He said: And whoever disbelieves, I will grant him enjoyment for a short while, then I will drive him to the chastisement of the fire; and it is an evil destination.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>And when Abraham prayed, "My Lord, make this city a city of peace, and provide its inhabitants with fruits, such of them as believe in God and the Last Day." God said, "As for those who deny the truth, I will grant them benefits for a short while and then subject them to the punishment of the Fire -- an evil destination."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And remember Abraham said: "My Lord, make this a City of Peace, and feed its people with fruits,-such of them as believe in Allah and the Last Day." He said: "(Yea), and such as reject Faith,-for a while will I grant them their pleasure, but will soon drive them to the torment of Fire,- an evil destination (indeed)!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="127">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And when Abraham was raising the plinth of the House with Ishmael, (he prayed): "Accept this from us, O Lord, for You hear and know everything;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim was raising the foundations of the House, along with Ismail; (saying), “Our Lord! Accept it from us; indeed You only are the All Hearing, the All Knowing.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when Abraham, and Ishmael with him, raised up the foundations of the House: 'Our Lord, receive this from us; Thou art the All-hearing, the All-knowing;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time Ibrahim was raising the foundation of the House and also Ismai'l, praying: our Lord! accept of us; verily Thou! Thou art the Hearer, the Knower!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim (Abraham) and (his son) Isma'il (Ishmael) were raising the foundations of the House (the Ka'bah at Makkah), (saying), "Our Lord! Accept (this service) from us. Verily! You are the All-Hearer, the All-Knower."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>As Abraham raises the foundations of the House, together with Ishmael, “Our Lord, accept it from us, You are the Hearer, the Knower.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And remember that when Abraham and Ishmael were raising the walls of the House, they prayed, "Lord, accept this service from us; You are All-Hearing and All-Knowing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when Ibrahim and (his son) Isma`il were raising the foundations of the House (the Ka`bah at Makkah), (saying), "Our Lord! Accept (this service) from us. Verily, You are the Hearer, the Knower."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when Abraham and Ishmael were raising the foundations of the House, (Abraham prayed): Our Lord! Accept from us (this duty). Lo! Thou, only Thou, art the Hearer, the Knower.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when Abraham and Ishmael raised the foundations of the House (supplicating): 'O our Lord, accept this from us, You are the Hearer, the Knower.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] when Abraham was raising the foundations of the House and [with him] Ishmael, [saying], "Our Lord, accept [this] from us. Indeed You are the Hearing, the Knowing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>While Abraham and Ishmael were raising the foundation of the house, they prayed, "Lord, accept our labor. You are All-hearing and All-knowing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when Ibrahim and Ismail raised the foundations of the House: Our Lord! accept from us; surely Thou art the Hearing, the Knowing:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>And when Abraham and Ishmael were laying the foundations of the House, [they prayed], "Our Lord, accept this from us; for You are All Hearing, All Knowing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And remember Abraham and Isma'il raised the foundations of the House (With this prayer): "Our Lord! Accept (this service) from us: For Thou art the All-Hearing, the All-knowing.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="128">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And make us submit, O Lord, to Your will, and our progeny a people submissive to You. Teach us the way of worship and forgive our trespasses, for You are compassionate and merciful;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“Our Lord! And make us submissive towards you and from our offspring a nation obedient to You – and show us the ways of our worship, and incline towards us with Your mercy; indeed You only are the Most Acceptor of Repentance, the Most Merciful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and, our Lord, make us submissive to Thee, and of our seed a nation submissive to Thee; and show us our holy rites, and turn towards us; surely Thou turnest, and art All-compassionate;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Our Lord! make us twain submissive unto Thee, and of our progeny community submissive unto Thee, and show us our rites, and relent toward us! verily Thou! Thou art the Relentant, the Merciful!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"Our Lord! And make us submissive unto You and of our offspring a nation submissive unto You, and show us our Manasik (all the ceremonies of pilgrimage - Hajj and 'Umrah, etc.), and accept our repentance. Truly, You are the One Who accepts repentance, the Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Our Lord, and make us submissive to You, and from our descendants a community submissive to You. And show us our rites, and accept our repentance. You are the Acceptor of Repentance, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Lord, make us Your Muslims (submissive servants) and also raise from our offspring a community which should be Muslim (submissive to Your Will). Show us the ways of Your worship and forbear our shortcomings: You are Forgiving and Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Our Lord! And make us submissive unto You and of our offspring a nation submissive unto You, and show us our Manasik, and accept our repentance. Truly, You are the One Who accepts repentance, the Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Our Lord! And make us submissive unto Thee and of our seed a nation submissive unto Thee, and show us our ways of worship, and relent toward us. Lo! Thou, only Thou, art the Relenting, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Our Lord, make us both submissive to You, and of our descendants a submissive nation to You. Show us our rites and accept us; You are the Receiver of Repentance, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Our Lord, and make us Muslims [in submission] to You and from our descendants a Muslim nation [in submission] to You. And show us our rites and accept our repentance. Indeed, You are the Accepting of repentance, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Lord, make us good Muslims (one who submits himself to God) and from our descendants make a good Muslim nation. Teach us the rules of worship and accept our repentance; You are All-forgiving and All-merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Our Lord! and make us both submissive to Thee and (raise) from our offspring a nation submitting to Thee, and show us our ways of devotion and turn to us (mercifully), surely Thou art the Oft-returning (to mercy), the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Lord, make us submissive to You; make of our descendants a nation that will submit to You. Teach us our rites of worship and turn to us with mercy; You are the Forgiving One and the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Our Lord! make of us Muslims, bowing to Thy (Will), and of our progeny a people Muslim, bowing to Thy (will); and show us our place for the celebration of (due) rites; and turn unto us (in Mercy); for Thou art the Oft-Returning, Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="129">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And send to them, O Lord, an apostle from among them to impart Your messages to them, and teach them the Book and the wisdom, and correct them in every way; for indeed You are mighty and wise.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“Our Lord! And send towards them a Noble Messenger, from amongst them, to recite to them Your verses, and to instruct them in Your Book and sound wisdom*, and to fully purify them; indeed You only are the Almighty, the Wise.” (The traditions of the Holy Prophet – sunnah and hadith – are called wisdom.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and, our Lord, do Thou send among them a Messenger, one of them, who shall recite to them Thy signs, and teach them the Book and the Wisdom, and purify them; Thou art the All-mighty, the All-wise.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Our Lord! raise up unto them an apostle from among them, who shall recite unto them Thy revelations, and shall teach them the Book and wisdom, and shall cleanse them. Verily Thou! Thou art the Mighty, the Wise.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"Our Lord! Send amongst them a Messenger of their own (and indeed Allah answered their invocation by sending Muhammad Peace be upon him), who shall recite unto them Your Verses and instruct them in the Book (this Quran) and Al-Hikmah (full knowledge of the Islamic laws and jurisprudence or wisdom or Prophethood, etc.), and sanctify them. Verily! You are the All-Mighty, the All-Wise."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Our Lord, and raise up among them a messenger, of themselves, who will recite to them Your revelations, and teach them the Book and wisdom, and purify them. You are the Almighty, the Wise.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Lord, raise up from among them a Messenger who shall recite Your Revelations to them and teach them the Book and Wisdom and purify their lives. You art All-Powerful and AllWise".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Our Lord! Send amongst them a Messenger of their own, who shall recite unto them Your verses and instruct them in the Book (this Qur'an), and purify them. Verily, You are the Mighty, the Wise."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Our Lord! And raise up in their midst a messenger from among them who shall recite unto them Thy revelations, and shall instruct them in the Scripture and in wisdom and shall make them grow. Lo! Thou, only Thou, art the Mighty, Wise.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Our Lord, send among them a Messenger from them who shall recite to them Your verses and teach them the Book and wisdom, and purify them; You are the Mighty, the Wise'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Our Lord, and send among them a messenger from themselves who will recite to them Your verses and teach them the Book and wisdom and purify them. Indeed, You are the Exalted in Might, the Wise."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Lord, send to them (our descendants) a Messenger of their own who will recite to them Your revelations, teach them the Book, give them wisdom, and purify them. You alone are the Majestic and the Most Wise."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Our Lord! and raise up in them an Apostle from among them who shall recite to them Thy communications and teach them the Book and the wisdom, and purify them; surely Thou art the Mighty, the Wise.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Our Lord, send forth to them a messenger of their own to recite Your revelations to them, to teach them the Scripture and wisdom, and purify them. You are the Mighty, the Wise One."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Our Lord! send amongst them a Messenger of their own, who shall rehearse Thy Signs to them and instruct them in scripture and wisdom, and sanctify them: For Thou art the Exalted in Might, the Wise."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="22" verse="26">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When We chose the site of the House for Abraham (We said:) "Associate no one with Me, and clean My House for those who will circumambulate it, stand (in reverence), and bow in homage.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember when We showed Ibrahim the right place of the Sacred House (mosque) and commanded that, “Do not ascribe anything as a partner to Me, and keep My House clean for those who encircle it and those who stay in it (for worship) and those who bow and prostrate.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when We settled for Abraham the place of the House: 'Thou shall not associate with Me anything. And do thou purify My House for those that shall go about it and those that stand, for those that bow and prostrate themselves;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time We settled Ibrahim in the place of the House, Saying: associate not thou with Me aught, and purify My House for these who circumambulate and those who stand up and those who bow and make prostration.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when We showed Ibrahim (Abraham) the site of the (Sacred) House (the Ka'bah at Makkah) (saying): "Associate not anything (in worship) with Me, [La ilaha ill-Allah (none has the right to be worshipped but Allah Islamic Monotheism], and sanctify My House for those who circumambulate it, and those who stand up for prayer, and those who bow (submit themselves with humility and obedience to Allah), and make prostration (in prayer, etc.);"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We showed Abraham the location of the House: “Do not associate anything with Me; and purify My House for those who circle around, and those who stand to pray, and those who kneel and prostrate.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Call to mind when We assigned to Abraham the site of the House (Kabah), directing him: "Do not associate aught with Me" and "Keep My House pure for those who walk around it, and for those who stand and who bow down and who prostrate themselves (in worship),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) when We showed Ibrahim the site of the House (saying): "Associate not anything with Me, and sanctify My House for those who circumambulate it, and those who stand up (for prayer), and those who bow and make prostration (in prayer);"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (remember) when We prepared for Abraham the place of the (holy) House, saying: Ascribe thou no thing as partner unto Me, and purify My House for those who make the round (thereof) and those who stand and those who bow and make prostration.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when We settled for Abraham (and Ishmael) the place of the Holy Mosque, (We said): 'You shall not associate with Me anything. Purify My House for those who circumambulate it and those who stand, for those who bow and prostrate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention, O Muhammad], when We designated for Abraham the site of the House, [saying], "Do not associate anything with Me and purify My House for those who perform Tawaf and those who stand [in prayer] and those who bow and prostrate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When We prepared for Abraham the place to build the Sacred House, We told him not to consider anything equal to Me and to keep the House clean for those walking around it, those standing, bowing down, and prostrating in prayer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when We assigned to Ibrahim the place of the House, saying: Do not associate with Me aught, and purify My House for those who make the circuit and stand to pray and bow and prostrate themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We assigned to Abraham the site of the House, saying, "Do not associate with Me anything and purify My House for those who circumambulate [the Kabah] and those who stand upright, and those who bow and prostrate themselves."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Behold! We gave the site, to Abraham, of the (Sacred) House, (saying): "Associate not anything (in worship) with Me; and sanctify My House for those who compass it round, or stand up, or bow, or prostrate themselves (therein in prayer).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="22" verse="27">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Announce the Pilgrimage to the people. They will come to you on foot and riding along distant roads on lean and slender beasts,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“And publicly announce the pilgrimage to all people – they will come to you, on foot and on every lean she-camel, coming from every far distant journey.” (The announcement by Prophet Ibrahim reached each and every soul.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and proclaim among men the Pilgrimage, and they shall come unto thee on foot and upon every lean beast, they shall come from every deep ravine</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And proclaim thou among mankind the pilgrimage; they shall come unto thee on foot and on any lean mount, coming from every deep defile.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And proclaim to mankind the Hajj (pilgrimage). They will come to you on foot and on every lean camel, they will come from every deep and distant (wide) mountain highway (to perform Hajj).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And announce the pilgrimage to humanity. They will come to you on foot, and on every transport. They will come from every distant point.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and publicly proclaim Pilgrimage for all mankind so that they come to you on foot and mounted on lean camels from every distant point</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And proclaim to mankind the Hajj (pilgrimage). They will come to you on foot and on every lean camel, they will come from every Fajj `Amiq.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And proclaim unto mankind the pilgrimage. They will come unto thee on foot and on every lean camel; they will come from every deep ravine,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Proclaim the pilgrimage to the people. They will come to you on foot and on every lean camel, they shall come from every deep ravine;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And proclaim to the people the Hajj [pilgrimage]; they will come to you on foot and on every lean camel; they will come from every distant pass -</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(We commanded Abraham), "Call people for hajj - an act of worship accomplished by visiting the sacred sites in Mecca." They will come on foot and on lean camels from all the distant quarters</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And proclaim among men the Pilgrimage: they will come to you on foot and on every lean camel, coming from every remote path,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Call mankind to the Pilgrimage. They will come to you, on foot, and on every kind of lean camel, by every distant track</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"And proclaim the Pilgrimage among men: they will come to thee on foot and (mounted) on every kind of camel, lean on account of journeys through deep and distant mountain highways;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="584">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
When Abraham had differences with his wife), (because of her jealousy of Hajar, Ishmael's mother), he took Ishmael and his mother and went away. They had a water-skin with them containing some water, Ishmael's mother used to drink water from the water-skin so that her milk would increase for her child. When Abraham reached Mecca, he made her sit under a tree and afterwards returned home. Ishmael's mother followed him, and when they reached Kada', she called him from behind, 'O Abraham! To whom are you leaving us?' He replied, '(I am leaving you) to Allah's (Care).' She said, 'I am satisfied to be with Allah.' She returned to her place and started drinking water from the water-skin, and her milk increased for her child. When the water had all been used up, she said to herself, 'I'd better go and look so that I may see somebody.' She ascended the Safa mountain and looked, hoping to see somebody, but in vain. When she came down to the valley, she ran till she reached the Marwa mountain. She ran to and fro (between the two mountains) many times. They she said to herself, 'i'd better go and see the state of the child,' she went and found it in a state of one on the point of dying. She could not endure to watch it dying and said (to herself), 'If I go and look, I may find somebody.' She went and ascended the Safa mountain and looked for a long while but could not find anybody. Thus she completed seven rounds (of running) between Safa and Marwa. Again she said (to herself), 'I'd better go back and see the state of the child.' But suddenly she heard a voice, and she said to that strange voice, 'Help us if you can offer any help.' Lo! It was Gabriel (who had made the voice). Gabriel hit the earth with his heel like this (Ibn 'Abbas hit the earth with his heel to Illustrate it), and so the water gushed out. Ishmael's mother was astonished and started digging. (Abu Al-Qasim) (i.e. the Prophet) said, "If she had left the water, (flow naturally without her intervention), it would have been flowing on the surface of the earth.") Ishmael's mother started drinking from the water and her milk increased for her child . Afterwards some people of the tribe of Jurhum, while passing through the bottom of the valley, saw some birds, and that astonished them, and they said, 'Birds can only be found at a place where there is water.' They sent a messenger who searched the place and found the water, and returned to inform them about it. Then they all went to her and said, 'O ishmael's mother! Will you allow us to be with you (or dwell with you)?' (And thus they stayed there.) Later on her boy reached the age of puberty and married a lady from them. Then an idea occurred to Abraham which he disclosed to his wife (Sarah), 'I want to call on my dependents I left (at Mecca).' When he went there, he greeted (Ishmael's wife) and said, 'Where is Ishmael?' She replied, 'He has gone out hunting.' Abraham said (to her), 'When he comes, tell him to change the threshold of his gate.' When he came, she told him the same whereupon Ishmael said to her, 'You are the threshold, so go to your family (i.e. you are divorced).' Again Abraham thought of visiting his dependents whom he had left (at Mecca), and he told his wife (Sarah) of his intentions. Abraham came to Ishmael's house and asked. "Where is Ishmael?" Ishmael's wife replied, "He has gone out hunting," and added, "Will you stay (for some time) and have something to eat and drink?' Abraham asked, 'What is your food and what is your drink?' She replied, 'Our food is meat and our drink is water.' He said, 'O Allah! Bless their meals and their drink." Abu Al-Qa-sim (i.e. Prophet) said, "Because of Abraham's invocation there are blessings (in Mecca)." Once more Abraham thought of visiting his family he had left (at Mecca), so he told his wife (Sarah) of his decision. He went and found Ishmael behind the Zam-zam well, mending his arrows. He said, "O Ishmael, Your Lord has ordered me to build a house for Him." Ishmael said, "Obey (the order of) your Lord." Abraham said, "Allah has also ordered me that you should help me therein." Ishmael said, "Then I will do." So, both of them rose and Abraham started building (the Ka'ba) while Ishmael went on handing him the stones, and both of them were saying, "O our Lord ! Accept (this service) from us, Verily, You are the All-Hearing, the All-Knowing." (2.127). When the building became high and the old man (i.e. Abraham) could no longer lift the stones (to such a high position), he stood over the stone of Al-Maqam and Ishmael carried on handing him the stones, and both of them were saying, 'O our Lord! Accept (this service) from us, Verily You are All-Hearing, All-Knowing." (2.127)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="54">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Commemorate Ishmael in the Book. He was true of his promise, and a messenger, a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Ismail in the Book; he was indeed true to his promise and was a Noble Messenger, a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And mention in the Book Ishmael; he was true to his promise, and he was a Messenger, a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And mention thou in the Book lsma'i; verily he was true in promise, and was apostle, prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And mention in the Book (the Quran) Isma'il (Ishmael). Verily! He was true to what he promised, and he was a Messenger, (and) a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And mention in the Scripture Ishmael. He was true to his promise, and was a messenger, a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And recite in the Book the account of Ishmael. He was ever true to his promise, and was a Messenger, a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And mention in the Book, Isma`il. Verily, he was true to what he promised, and he was a Messenger, (and) a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And make mention in the Scripture of Ishmael. Lo! he was a keeper of his promise, and he was a messenger (of Allah), a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And mention in the Book, Ishmael; he too was true to his promise, a Messenger and a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And mention in the Book, Ishmael. Indeed, he was true to his promise, and he was a messenger and a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Mention in the Book (the Quran) the story of Ishmael; he was true to his promise, a Messengers and a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And mention Ismail in the Book; surely he was truthful in (his) promise, and he was an apostle, a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Tell also of Ishmael in the Book. He was true to his promise and was a messenger and a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Also mention in the Book (the story of) Isma'il: He was (strictly) true to what he promised, and he was a messenger (and) a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="55">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>He enjoined on his household worship and zakat, and he was obedient to his Lord.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He used to command his people to offer prayer and give charity, and was liked by his Lord.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>He bade his people to pray and to give the alms, and he was pleasing to his Lord.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And he was wont to command his household to the Prayer and the poor-rate, and he was with his Lord an approved one. *Chapter: 19</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And he used to enjoin on his family and his people As-Salat (the prayers) and the Zakat, and his Lord was pleased with him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And he used to enjoin on his people prayer and charity, and he was pleasing to his Lord.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>He enjoined his household to observe Prayer and to give Zakah (purifying alms); and his Lord was well pleased with him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And he would enjoin on his family and his people the Salah and the Zakah, and his Lord was pleased with him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He enjoined upon his people worship and almsgiving, and was acceptable in the sight of his Lord.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And he ordered his people to pray and to give charity and his Lord was pleased with him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And he used to enjoin on his people prayer and zakah and was to his Lord pleasing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>He would order his people to worship God and pay the religious tax. His Lord was pleased with him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And he enjoined on his family prayer and almsgiving, and was one in whom his Lord was well pleased.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>He exhorted his people to prayer and almsgiving, and his Lord was pleased with him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He used to enjoin on his people Prayer and Charity, and he was most acceptable in the sight of his Lord.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="136">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Say: "We believe in God and what has been sent down to us, and what had been revealed to Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob and their progeny, and that which was given to Moses and Christ, and to all other prophets by the Lord. We make no distinction among them, and we submit to Him."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Say, “We believe in Allah and what is sent down to us and what was sent down to Ibrahim, and Ismael, and Ishaq, and Yaqub, and to their offspring, and what was bestowed upon Moosa and Eisa (Jesus), and what was bestowed upon other Prophets – from their Lord; we do not make any distinction, in belief, between any of them; and to Allah we have submitted ourselves.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Say you: 'We believe in God, and in that which has been sent down on us and sent down on Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac and Jacob, and the Tribes, and that which was given to Moses and Jesus and the Prophets, of their Lord; we make no division between any of them, and to Him we surrender.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Say: we believe in Allah and that which hath been sent down unto us and that which was sent down unto Ibrahim and Ismai'l and Ishaq and Ya'qub and the tribes, and that which was vouchsafed unto Musa and lsa, and that which was vouchsafed unto the prophets from their Lord; we differentiate not between any of them, and unto Him are submissive.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Say (O Muslims), "We believe in Allah and that which has been sent down to us and that which has been sent down to Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma'il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya'qub (Jacob), and to Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya'qub (Jacob)], and that which has been given to Musa (Moses) and 'Iesa (Jesus), and that which has been given to the Prophets from their Lord. We make no distinction between any of them, and to Him we have submitted (in Islam)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Say, “We believe in God; and in what was revealed to us; and in what was revealed to Abraham, and Ishmael, and Isaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs; and in what was given to Moses and Jesus; and in what was given to the prophets—from their Lord. We make no distinction between any of them, and to Him we surrender.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>O Muslims, say to them, "We believe in Allah and the Guidance which has been sent down to us and which was sent to Abraham, Ismail, Isaac and Jacob and his descendants and which was given by their Lord to Moses and Jesus and to all other Prophets. We do not discriminate against any of them and we have completely surrendered to Allah as Muslims."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Say (O Muslims): "We believe in Allah and that which has been sent down to us and that which has been sent down to Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma`il (Ishmael), Ishaq (Isaac), Ya`qub (Jacob), and to Al-Asbat (the offspring of the twelve sons of Ya`qub), and that which has been given to Musa (Moses) and `Isa (Jesus), and that which has been given to the Prophets from their Lord. We make no distinction between any of them, and to Him we have submitted (in Islam)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Say (O Muslims): We believe in Allah and that which is revealed unto us and that which was revealed unto Abraham, and Ishmael, and Isaac, and Jacob, and the tribes, and that which Moses and Jesus received, and that which the prophets received from their Lord. We make no distinction between any of them, and unto Him we have surrendered.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Say: 'We believe in Allah and that which is sent down to us, and in what was sent down to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the tribes; to Moses and Jesus and the Prophets from their Lord. We do not differentiate between any of them, and to Him we are submissive (Muslims)'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Say, [O believers], "We have believed in Allah and what has been revealed to us and what has been revealed to Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob and the Descendants and what was given to Moses and Jesus and what was given to the prophets from their Lord. We make no distinction between any of them, and we are Muslims [in submission] to Him."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muslims), say, "We believe in God and what He has revealed to us and to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, and their descendants, and what was revealed to Moses, Jesus, and the Prophets from their Lord. We make no distinction among them and to God we have submitted ourselves."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Say: We believe in Allah and (in) that which had been revealed to us, and (in) that which was revealed to Ibrahim and Ismail and Ishaq and Yaqoub and the tribes, and (in) that which was given to Musa and Isa, and (in) that which was given to the prophets from their Lord, we do not make any distinction between any of them, and to Him do we submit.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Say, "We believe in God and what was revealed to us; and what was revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and their descendants, and what was given to Moses and Jesus and what was given to the [other] prophets by their Lord. We make no distinction between any of them. It is to Him that we surrender ourselves."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Say ye: "We believe in Allah, and the revelation given to us, and to Abraham, Isma'il, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, and that given to Moses and Jesus, and that given to (all) prophets from their Lord: We make no difference between one and another of them: And we bow to Allah (in Islam)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="85">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Remember) Ishmael, Edris and Dhu'l-Kifl. They were men of fortitude,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Ismail, and Idrees, and Zul-Kifl; they were all patiently enduring.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Ishmael, Idris, Dhul Kifl -- each was of the patient,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Isma'il and ldris and Zul-Kifl! each were of the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) Isma'il (Ishmael), and Idris (Enoch) and Dhul-Kifl (Isaiah), all were from among As-Sabirin (the patient ones, etc.).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Ishmael, and Enoch, and Ezekiel; each was one of the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And (We bestowed the same favour) upon Ishmael, Idris and Dhu al-Kifl, for they were all steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) Isma`il, Idris and Dhul-Kifl: All were from among the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (mention) Ishmael, and Idris, and Dhu'l-Kifl. All were of the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And Ishmael, Idris, and ThulKifl (the son of Job) each were patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] Ishmael and Idrees and Dhul-Kifl; all were of the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Ismael, Idris and Dhul Kifl all were people of great patience.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Ismail and Idris and Zulkifl; all were of the patient ones;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Remember Ishmael and Idris and Dhul Kifl: they were all patient and steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And (remember) Isma'il, Idris, and Zul-kifl, all (men) of constancy and patience;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="86">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And they were admitted to Our grace. Verily they were among the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy; indeed they are among those who deserve Our proximity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and We admitted them into Our mercy; they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We caused them to enter into our mercy, verily they are of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We admitted them to Our Mercy. Verily, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy. They were among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy, for they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We admitted them to Our mercy. Verily, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We brought them in unto Our mercy. Lo! they are among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We admitted them to Our Mercy, for they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy. Indeed, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We encompassed them in Our mercy; they were righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We caused them to enter into Our mercy, surely they were of the good ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We admitted them to Our mercy. They were all righteous men.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We admitted them to Our mercy: for they were of the righteous ones.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="69">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Our angels came to Abraham with good news, and said: "Peace on you. "Peace on you too," said Abraham, and hastened to bring a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And indeed Our angels came to Ibrahim with glad tidings – they said, “Peace”; he answered, “Peace” and without delay brought a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Our messengers came to Abraham with the good tidings; they said, 'Peace!' 'Peace,' he said; and presently he brought a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly Our messengers came unto Ibrahim with the glad tidings. The said: peace! He said: peace! And he tarried not till he brougt a calf roasted.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And verily, there came Our Messengers to Ibrahim (Abraham) with glad tidings. They said: Salam (greetings or peace!) He answered, Salam (greetings or peace!) and he hastened to entertain them with a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Our messengers came to Abraham with good news. They said, “Peace.” He said, “Peace.” Soon after, he came with a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Indeed Our messengers came to Abraham, bearing glad tidings. They greeted him with 'peace', and Abraham answered back to them 'peace', and hurriedly brought to them a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And verily, there came Our messengers to Ibrahim with the glad tidings. They said: "Salaman (greetings or peace!)" He answered, "Salamun (greetings or peace!)," and he hastened to entertain them with a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Our messengers cam unto Abraham with good news. They said: Peace! He answered: Peace! and delayed not to bring a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Our Messengers came to Abraham with glad tidings. They said: 'Peace' He replied 'Peace' and in a while brought them a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And certainly did Our messengers come to Abraham with good tidings; they said, "Peace." He said, "Peace," and did not delay in bringing [them] a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Our Messengers came to Abraham with glad news. They said, "Peace be with you." He replied similarly. After a short time he presented them with a roasted calf</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly Our apostles came to Ibrahim with good news. They said: Peace. Peace, said he, and he made no delay in bringing a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Our messengers came to Abraham with good news and greeted him with, "Peace." He too said, "Peace be on you," and hastened to bring a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>There came Our messengers to Abraham with glad tidings. They said, "Peace!" He answered, "Peace!" and hastened to entertain them with a roasted calf.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="70">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When they did not stretch their hands towards it he became suspicious and afraid of them. They said: "Do not be afraid. We have been sent to the people of Lot."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And when he saw their hands not reaching towards it, he thought they were pretending and inwardly started fearing them; they said, “Do not be afraid – we are sent to the people of Lut.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when he saw their hands not reaching towards it, he was suspicious of them and conceived a fear of them. They said, 'Fear not; we have been sent to the people of Lot.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And when he beheld that their hands reached it not he misliked them, and ccnceived a fear of them. They said fear not verily we are sent unto the people of Lut.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>But when he saw their hands went not towards it (the meal), he felt some mistrust of them, and conceived a fear of them. They said: "Fear not, we have been sent against the people of Lout (Lot)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>But when he saw their hands not reaching towards it, he became suspicious of them, and conceived a fear of them. They said, “Do not fear, we were sent to the people of Lot.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>When he perceived that their hands could not reach it, he mistrusted them, and felt afraid of them. They said: 'Do not be afraid. We have been sent to the people of Lot.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>But when he saw their hands went not towards it (the meal), he mistrusted them, and conceived a fear of them. They said: "Fear not, we have been sent against the people of Lut."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when he saw their hands reached not to it, he mistrusted them and conceived a fear of them. They said: Fear not! Lo! we are sent unto the folk of Lot.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But when he saw that their hands did not reach towards it, he was wary and became fearful of them, but they said: 'Do not be afraid. We are sent to thenation of Lot'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>But when he saw their hands not reaching for it, he distrusted them and felt from them apprehension. They said, "Fear not. We have been sent to the people of Lot."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>but when he saw that their hands did not reach out for it, he could not know who they were and became afraid of them. They said, "Do not be afraid; we are God's angelic Messengers sent to the people of Lot."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>But when he saw that their hands were not extended towards it, he deemed them strange and conceived fear of them. They said: Fear not, surely we are sent to Lut's people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>But when he saw that they made no move to eat, he found this strange and became afraid of them. They said, "Do not be afraid, for we have been sent to the people of Lot."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>But when he saw their hands went not towards the (meal), he felt some mistrust of them, and conceived a fear of them. They said: "Fear not: We have been sent against the people of Lut."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="71">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>His wife who stood near, laughed as We gave her the good news of Isaac, and after Isaac of Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And his wife was standing by and she started laughing*, so We gave her glad tidings regarding Ishaq, and following Ishaq, regarding Yaqub.** (* She was glad that the disbelieving people of Lut would be destroyed.** The birth of these two.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And his wife was standing by; she laughed, therefore We gave her the glad tidings of Isaac, and, after Isaac, of Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And his wife was standing. she laughed. Then We gave her the glad tidings of Is'haq, and after Is'haq, Ya'qub.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And his wife was standing (there), and she laughed (either, because the Messengers did not eat their food or for being glad for the destruction of the people of Lout (Lot). But We gave her glad tidings of Ishaque (Isaac), and after him, of Ya'qub (Jacob).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>His wife was standing by, so she laughed. And We gave her good news of Isaac; and after Isaac, Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And Abraham's wife was standing by and on hearing this she laughed. And We gave her the good news of (the birth of) Isaac, and after Isaac, of Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And his wife was standing (there), and she laughed. But We gave her glad tidings of Ishaq, and after Ishaq, of Ya`qub.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And his wife, standing by laughed when We gave her good tidings (of the birth) of Isaac, and, after Isaac, of Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>His wife (Sarah), who was standing nearby, laughed. Thereupon, We gave her the good news of Isaac, and after Isaac of Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And his Wife was standing, and she smiled. Then We gave her good tidings of Isaac and after Isaac, Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>His wife who was standing nearby, smiled and so We gave her the glad news that she would give birth to Isaac who would have a son, Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And his wife was standing (by), so she laughed, then We gave her the good news of Ishaq and after Ishaq of (a son's son) Yaqoub.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>His wife, who was standing nearby, laughed when We gave her the good news of Isaac, and after Isaac, Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And his wife was standing (there), and she laughed: But we gave her glad tidings of Isaac, and after him, of Jacob.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="72">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>She said: "Woe betide me! Will I give birth when I am old and this my husband be aged? This is indeed surprising!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>She said, “Oh woe to me – will I bear a child whereas I am an old woman, and this my husband, is an old man? This is something really extraordinary.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>She said, 'Woe is me! Shall I bear, being an old woman, and this my husband is an old man? This assuredly is a strange thing.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>She said: Oh for me shall bring forth when I am old, and this my husband is advanced in years! Verily a marvellous thing is this!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>She said (in astonishment): "Woe unto me! Shall I bear a child while I am an old woman, and here is my husband, an old man? Verily! This is a strange thing!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>She said, “Alas for me. Shall I give birth, when I am an old woman, and this, my husband, is an old man? This is truly a strange thing.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>She said: 'Woe is me! Shall I bear a child now that I am an old woman and my husband is well advanced in years. This is indeed strange!'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>She said (in astonishment): "Woe unto me! Shall I bear a child while I am an old woman, and here is my husband an old man Verily, this is a strange thing!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>She said: Oh woe is me! Shall I bear a child when I am an old woman, and this my husband is an old man? Lo! this is a strange thing!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>She replied: 'Alas for me! Shall I bear (a child) when I am old woman and my husband is advanced in years? This is indeed a strange thing'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>She said, "Woe to me! Shall I give birth while I am an old woman and this, my husband, is an old man? Indeed, this is an amazing thing!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>She said, "Woe is me! How can I have a baby when I am barren and my husband is very old? This is certainly strange".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>She said: O wonder! shall I bear a son when I am an extremely old woman and this my husband an extremely old man? Most surely this is a wonderful thing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>She said, "Alas! Shall I bear a child in this old age, while my husband here is also old? This is indeed a strange thing!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>She said: "Alas for me! shall I bear a child, seeing I am an old woman, and my husband here is an old man? That would indeed be a wonderful thing!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="73">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"Why are you surprised at the command of God? God's mercy and blessings be upon you, O members of this household," they said. "Verily He is worthy of praise and glory."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>The angels said, “Do you wonder at the command of Allah? Allah’s mercy and His blessings be upon you, O people of this house; indeed He only is Most Praiseworthy, Most Honourable.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>They said, 'What, dost thou marvel at God's command? The mercy of God and His blessings be upon you, O people of the House! Surely He is All-laudable, All-glorious.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>They said marvellest thou at the decree of Allah? Mercy of Allah and His blessings be upon you, people of the house, verily He is Praiseworthy, Glorious.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They said: "Do you wonder at the Decree of Allah? The Mercy of Allah and His Blessings be on you, O the family [of Ibrahim (Abraham)]. Surely, He (Allah) is All-Praiseworthy, All-Glorious."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>They said, “Do you marvel at the decree of God? The mercy and blessings of God are upon you, O people of the house. He is Praiseworthy and Glorious.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>They said: 'Do you wonder at Allah's decree? Allah's mercy and His blessings be upon you, O people of the house. Surely, He is Praiseworthy, Glorious.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They said: "Do you wonder at the decree of Allah The mercy of Allah and His blessings be on you, O the family [of Ibrahim]. Surely, He (Allah) is All-Praiseworthy, All-Glorious."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>They said: Wonderest thou at the commandment of Allah? The mercy of Allah and His blessings be upon you, O people of the house! Lo! He is Owner of Praise, Owner of Glory!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>They said: 'What, do you marvel at the command of Allah? The Mercy of Allah and His Blessings be upon you, O people of the House. Indeed, He isPraised, Exalted'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>They said, "Are you amazed at the decree of Allah? May the mercy of Allah and His blessings be upon you, people of the house. Indeed, He is Praiseworthy and Honorable."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They replied, "Would you be surprised at God's decree? People of the house, may God's mercy and blessings be with you. God is Appreciative and Glorious."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>They said: Do you wonder at Allah's bidding? The mercy of Allah and His blessings are on you, O people of the house, surely He is Praised, Glorious.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They said, "Are you astonished at God's command? May the mercy of God and His blessings be upon you, O people of this house. Surely, He is praiseworthy and glorious."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They said: "Dost thou wonder at Allah's decree? The grace of Allah and His blessings on you, o ye people of the house! for He is indeed worthy of all praise, full of all glory!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="112">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We gave him the good news of Isaac, apostle, who is among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We gave him the glad tidings of Ishaq, a Herald of the Hidden, from among those who deserve Our proximity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Then We gave him the good tidings of Isaac, a Prophet, one of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We gave him the glad tidings of Is-haq, a prophet, and of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We gave him the glad tidings of Ishaque (Isaac) a Prophet from the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave him good news of Isaac, a prophet, one of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We gave him the good news of Isaac, a Prophet and among the righteous ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We gave him the glad tidings of Ishaq -- a Prophet from the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And we gave him tidings of the birth of Isaac, a prophet of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Then, We gave him the glad tidings of Isaac, a Prophet, one of the righteous,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave him good tidings of Isaac, a prophet from among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave him the glad news of the birth of Isaac, one of the righteous Prophets.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave him the good news of Ishaq, a prophet among the good ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave Abraham the good news of Isaac, a prophet and a righteous man,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We gave him the good news of Isaac - a prophet,- one of the Righteous.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="113">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We blessed him and Isaac. Among their descendants are some who do good, but some who wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We sent blessings upon him and Ishaq; and among their descendants – some who do good deeds, and some who clearly wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We blessed him, and Isaac; and of their seed some are good-doers, and some manifest self-wrongers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We blessed him and Is-haq; and of their offspring are some well-doers and some who wrong themselves manifestly.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>We blessed him and Ishaque (Isaac), and of their progeny are (some) that do right, and some that plainly wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We blessed him, and Isaac. But among their descendants are some who are righteous, and some who are clearly unjust to themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We blessed him and Isaac. Among the offspring of the two some did good and some plainly wronged themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>We blessed him and Ishaq. And of their progeny are (some) that do right, and some that plainly wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We blessed him and Isaac. And of their seed are some who do good, and some who plainly wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and We blessed him and Isaac, and from their offspring are some gooddoers, and others who clearly wronged themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We blessed him and Isaac. But among their descendants is the doer of good and the clearly unjust to himself.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We had blessed him and Isaac. Some of their offspring were righteous and others were openly unjust to themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We showered Our blessings on him and on Ishaq; and of their offspring are the doers of good, and (also) those who are clearly unjust to their own souls.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and blessed him and Isaac too: some of their offspring were good, but some clearly sinned against their souls.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We blessed him and Isaac: but of their progeny are (some) that do right, and (some) that obviously do wrong, to their own souls.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="72">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We bestowed on him Isaac, and Jacob as an additional gift, and made them righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed him Ishaq, and Yaqub the grandson; and We made all of them worthy of Our proximity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob in superfluity, and every one made We righteous</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him ls-haq and Ya qub as a grandson; and each one We made righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaque (Isaac), and (a grandson) Ya'qub (Jacob). Each one We made righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We granted him Isaac and Jacob as a gift; and each We made righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Isaac and Jacob as an additional gift, making each of them righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq, and Ya`qub Nafilatan. Each one We made righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Isaac, and Jacob as a grandson. Each of them We made righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave him, in excess, Isaac, and Jacob (for a grandson); and We made each righteous</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob in addition, and all [of them] We made righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We granted him Isaac and Jacob as a gift and helped both of them to become righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave him Ishaq and Yaqoub, a son's son, and We made (them) all good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We bestowed Isaac and then Jacob on him as an additional boon and We made all of them righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We bestowed on him Isaac and, as an additional gift, (a grandson), Jacob, and We made righteous men of every one (of them).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="49">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Thus, when he left them and the (idols) they worshipped, We bestowed on him Isaac and Jacob, and made each of them a prophet,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So when he had separated from them and what they worshipped other than Allah, We bestowed him Ishaq and Yaqub; and We made each of them a Herald of the Hidden.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So, when he went apart from them and that they were serving, apart from God, We gave him Isaac and Jacob, and each We made a Prophet;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then when he had renounced them and that which they worshipped beside Allah, We best owed on him Ishaq and Yaqub and each one We made a prophet!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So when he had turned away from them and from those whom they worshipped besides Allah, We gave him Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob), and each one of them We made a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When he withdrew from them, and from what they worship besides God, We granted him Isaac and Jacob. And each We made a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Thereupon Abraham dissociated himself from his people and the deities they worshipped instead of Allah, and We bestowed upon him Isaac and Jacob and made each of them a Prophet;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So when he had turned away from them and from those whom they worshipped besides Allah, We gave him Ishaq and Ya`qub, and each one of them We made a Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>So, when he had withdrawn from them and that which they were worshipping beside Allah, We gave him Isaac and Jacob. Each of them We made a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>So when he turned away from them and those they worshipped, other than Allah, We gave him Isaac and Jacob. Each of them We made a Prophet,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So when he had left them and those they worshipped other than Allah, We gave him Isaac and Jacob, and each [of them] We made a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When (Abraham) rejected his people and what they worshipped instead of God, We gave him Isaac and Jacob and made both of them Prophets.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So when he withdrew from them and what they worshipped besides Allah, We gave to him Ishaq and Yaqoub, and each one of them We made a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>So when he had separated himself from them and from what they worshipped besides God, We bestowed on him Isaac and Jacob, and We made each of them a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>When he had turned away from them and from those whom they worshipped besides Allah, We bestowed on him Isaac and Jacob, and each one of them We made a prophet.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="50">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And bestowed on them some of Our blessings, and gave them high renown.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We gave them Our mercy, and assigned for them a true and high repute.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and We gave them of Our mercy, and We appointed unto them a tongue of truthfulness, sublime.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed on them of Our mercy, and We made for them a renown lofty.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We gave them of Our Mercy (a good provision in plenty), and We granted them honour on the tongues (of all the nations, i.e. everybody remembers them with a good praise).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave them freely of Our mercy, and gave them a noble reputation of truth.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and We bestowed on them Our mercy, and granted them a truly lofty renown.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We gave them of Our mercy, and We granted them Sidqin `Aliyyan on the tongues.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And we gave them of Our mercy, and assigned to them a high and true renown.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and We gave them of Our Mercy and We appointed to them a truthful, highly sincere tongue,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave them of Our mercy, and we made for them a reputation of high honor.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We granted them Our blessing and high renown.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We granted to them of Our mercy, and We left (behind them) a truthful mention of eminence for them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We granted them Our mercy and bestowed on them true and high renown.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We bestowed of Our Mercy on them, and We granted them lofty honour on the tongue of truth.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="27">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We bestowed on him Isaac and Jacob and gave his progeny prophethood and scripture, and rewarded him in this world, and in the next he will be among the upright.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed Ishaq and Yaqub to him, and kept the Prophethood and the Book among his descendants, and We gave him his reward in the world; and in the Hereafter he is indeed among those who deserve Our proximity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob, and We appointed the Prophecy and the Book to be among his seed; We gave him his wage in this world, and in the world to come he shall be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed on him Is-haq and Y'aqub, and We placed among his posterity prophethood and the Book, and We vouchsafed unto him his hire in the World, and verily in the Hereafter he shall be of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed on him [Ibrahim (Abraham)], Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob), and ordained among his offspring Prophethood and the Book [i.e. the Taurat (Torah) (to Musa - Moses), the Injeel (Gospel) (to 'Iesa - Jesus), the Quran (to Muhammad SAW), all from the offspring of Ibrahim (Abraham)], and We granted him his reward in this world, and verily, in the Hereafter he is indeed among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We granted him Isaac and Jacob, and conferred on his descendants the Prophethood and the Book, and gave him his reward in this life; and in the Hereafter he will be among the upright.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and We bestowed upon him (offspring like) Isaac and Jacob, and bestowed prophethood and the Book on his descendants and granted him his reward in this world; he will certainly be among the righteous in the Hereafter.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We bestowed on him, Ishaq and Ya`qub, and We ordained among his offspring prophethood and the Book, and We granted him his reward in this world; and verily, in the Hereafter he is indeed among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed on him Isaac and Jacob, and We established the prophethood and the Scripture among his seed, and We gave him his reward in the world, and lo! in the Hereafter he verily is among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And, We gave him (Abraham), Isaac and Jacob and appointed on his descendants the Prophethood and the Book. We gave him his wage in this world, and in the Everlasting Life he shall be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave to Him Isaac and Jacob and placed in his descendants prophethood and scripture. And We gave him his reward in this world, and indeed, he is in the Hereafter among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We granted Isaac and Jacob to Abraham and We bestowed upon his offspring, prophethood and the Book. We gave him his reward in this world and in the next life, he will be among the pious ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We granted him Ishaq and Yaqoub, and caused the prophethood and the book to remain in his seed, and We gave him his reward in this world, and in the hereafter he will most surely be among the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob and granted prophethood and the Book to his descendants. We gave him his reward in this life and in the Hereafter he shall dwell among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We gave (Abraham) Isaac and Jacob, and ordained among his progeny Prophethood and Revelation, and We granted him his reward in this life; and he was in the Hereafter (of the company) of the Righteous.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="130">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Who will turn away from the creed of Abraham but one dull of soul? We made him the chosen one here in the world, and one of the best in the world to come,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And who will renounce the religion of Ibrahim except him who is a fool at heart? We indeed chose him (Ibrahim) in this world; and indeed in the Hereafter he is among those worthy of being closest to Us.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Who therefore shrinks from the religion of Abraham, except he be foolish-minded? Indeed, We chose him in the present world, and in the world to come he shall be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And who shall be averse from the faith of Ibrahim, save one who befooleth his soul! And assuredly We chose him in this World, and verily he in the Hereafter shall be of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And who turns away from the religion of Ibrahim (Abraham) (i.e. Islamic Monotheism) except him who befools himself? Truly, We chose him in this world and verily, in the Hereafter he will be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Who would forsake the religion of Abraham, except he who fools himself? We chose him in this world, and in the Hereafter he will be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Now, who else can have aversion to the way of Abraham but the one who has debased himself with folly and ignorance? Abraham was the man whom We chose for Our service in this world, and in the Next World he shall be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And who turns away from the religion of Ibrahim (i.e. Islamic Monotheism) except him who fools himself Truly, We chose him in this world and verily, in the Hereafter he will be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And who forsaketh the religion of Abraham save him who befooleth himself? Verily We chose him in the world, and lo! in the Hereafter he is among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And who has no desire for the religion of Abraham, except he who fooled himself? We chose him in this world, and in the Everlasting world, he shall be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And who would be averse to the religion of Abraham except one who makes a fool of himself. And We had chosen him in this world, and indeed he, in the Hereafter, will be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>No one turns away from Abraham's Tradition except one who makes a fool of himself. To Abraham We have granted distinction in this world and in the life hereafter he will be among the righteous ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And who forsakes the religion of Ibrahim but he who makes himself a fool, and most certainly We chose him in this world, and in the hereafter he is most surely among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Who but a foolish man would turn away from the religion of Abraham? We chose him in this world, and in the Hereafter he shall be among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And who turns away from the religion of Abraham but such as debase their souls with folly? Him We chose and rendered pure in this world: And he will be in the Hereafter in the ranks of the Righteous.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="131">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(For) when his Lord said to him: "Obey," he replied: "I submit to the Lord of all the worlds."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, “Submit”, he said, “I have submitted to the Lord Of The Creation.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, 'Surrender,' he said, 'I have surrendered me to the Lord of all Being.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Recall what time his Lord said unto him: submit, he said: I submit to the Lord of the Worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, "Submit (i.e. be a Muslim)!" He said, "I have submitted myself (as a Muslim) to the Lord of the 'Alamin (mankind, jinns and all that exists)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, “Submit!” He said, “I have submitted to the Lord of the Worlds.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, "Surrender," he promptly responded, "I have surrendered to the Lord of the Universe (and become a Muslim)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, "Submit (i.e. be a Muslim)!" He said, "I have submitted myself (as a Muslim) to the Lord of the `Alamin (mankind, Jinn and all that exists)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>When his Lord said unto him: Surrender! he said: I have surrendered to the Lord of the Worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>When his Lord said to him: 'Submit' he answered: 'I have submitted to the Lord of the Worlds'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, "Submit", he said "I have submitted [in Islam] to the Lord of the worlds."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When God commanded Abraham to submit, he replied, "I have submitted myself to the Will of the Lord of the universe."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, Be a Muslim, he said: I submit myself to the Lord of the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When his Lord said to him, "Surrender!" he responded, "I have surrendered to the Lord of the Universe,"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Behold! his Lord said to him: "Bow (thy will to Me):" He said: "I bow (my will) to the Lord and Cherisher of the Universe."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="132">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And Abraham left this legacy to his sons, and to Jacob, and said: "O my sons, God has chosen this as the faith for you. Do not die but as those who have submitted (to God)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And Ibrahim willed the same religion upon his sons, and also did Yaqub (Jacob); (saying), “O my sons – indeed Allah has chosen this religion for you; therefore do not die except as Muslims (those who submit to Him).”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Abraham charged his sons with this and Jacob likewise: 'My sons, God has chosen for you the religion; see that you die not save in surrender.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Ibrahim enjoined his sons the same and did Ya'qub also, saying: O my sons! verily Allah hath chosen for you the religion, so die not except ye be Muslims.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And this (submission to Allah, Islam) was enjoined by Ibrahim (Abraham) upon his sons and by Ya'qub (Jacob), (saying), "O my sons! Allah has chosen for you the (true) religion, then die not except in the Faith of Islam (as Muslims - Islamic Monotheism)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Abraham exhorted his sons, and Jacob, “O my sons, God has chosen this religion for you, so do not die unless you have submitted.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>He also enjoined on his children to follow the same way. Jacob also did the same and his last will to his sons was, "O my children, Allah has chosen the same way of life for you. Hence remain Muslims up to your last breath."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And this (submission to Allah, Islam) was enjoined by Ibrahim (Abraham) upon his sons and by Ya`qub (Jacob) (saying), "O my sons! Allah has chosen for you the (true) religion, then die not except as Muslims."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>The same did Abraham enjoin upon his sons, and also Jacob, (saying): O my sons! Lo! Allah hath chosen for you the (true) religion; therefore die not save as men who have surrendered (unto Him).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Abraham charged his children with this, and so did Jacob, saying: 'My sons, Allah has chosen for you the religion. Do not die except being submissive (Muslims)'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Abraham instructed his sons [to do the same] and [so did] Jacob, [saying], "O my sons, indeed Allah has chosen for you this religion, so do not die except while you are Muslims."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Abraham left this legacy to his sons and, in turn, so did Jacob saying, "God has chosen this religion for you. You must not leave this world unless you are a Muslim (submitted to the will of the Lord of the Universe)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And the same did Ibrahim enjoin on his sons and (so did) Yaqoub. O my sons! surely Allah has chosen for you (this) faith, therefore die not unless you are Muslims.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and Abraham enjoined his sons to do the same, as did Jacob, "My sons, God has chosen this religion for you; so do not let death overtake you, except when you are in a state of submission."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And this was the legacy that Abraham left to his sons, and so did Jacob; "Oh my sons! Allah hath chosen the Faith for you; then die not except in the Faith of Islam."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="133">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Were you present at the hour of Jacob's death? "What will you worship after me?" he asked his sons, and they answered: "We shall worship your God and the God of your fathers, of Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac, the one and only God; and to Him we submit."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>In fact, some of you yourselves were present when death approached Yaqub and when he said to his sons, “What will you worship after me?” They said, “We shall worship Him Who is your God, and is the God of your fathers, Ibrahim and Ismail and Ishaq (Isaac) – the One God; and to Him we have submitted ourselves.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Why, were you witnesses, when death came to Jacob? When he said to his sons, 'What will you serve after me?' They said, 'We will serve thy God and the God of thy fathers Abraham, Ishmael and Isaac, One God; to Him we surrender.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Were ye witnesses when death presented itself to Ya'qub, what time he said unto his sons: what will ye worship after me! They said: we shall worship the God the God of thy fathers, Ibrahim and Ismai'l and Ishaq, and unto Him we are submissive.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Or were you witnesses when death approached Ya'qub (Jacob)? When he said unto his sons, "What will you worship after me?" They said, "We shall worship your Ilah (God - Allah), the Ilah (God) of your fathers, Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma'il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), One Ilah (God), and to Him we submit (in Islam)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Or were you witnesses when death approached Jacob, and he said to his sons, “What will you worship after Me?” They said, “We will worship your God, and the God of your fathers, Abraham, Ishmael, and Isaac; One God; and to Him we submit.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Were you present at the time when Jacob was on the point of death? He asked his children, "Whom will you worship after me?" They all answered, "We will worship the same One Allah Whom you, your forefathers Abraham. Ismail and Isaac acknowledged as their Allah and to Him we all surrender as Muslims."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Or were you witnesses when death approached Ya`qub (Jacob) When he said unto his sons, "What will you worship after me" They said, "We shall worship your AIlah (God ـ Allah) the Ilah of your fathers, Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma`il (Ishmael), Ishaq (Isaac), One Ilah, and to Him we submit (in Islam)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Or were ye present when death came to Jacob, when he said unto his sons: What will ye worship after me? They said: We shall worship thy god, the god of thy fathers, Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac, One Allah, and unto Him we have surrendered.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Or, were you witnesses when death came to Jacob! He said to his children: 'What will you worship after me' They replied: 'We will worship your God and the God of your forefathers, Abraham, Ishmael, and Isaac, the One God. To Him, we are submissive'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Or were you witnesses when death approached Jacob, when he said to his sons, "What will you worship after me?" They said, "We will worship your God and the God of your fathers, Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac - one God. And we are Muslims [in submission] to Him."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Were you (believers) there when death approached Jacob? When he asked his sons, "Whom will you worship after my death?" They replied, "We will worship your Lord, the Lord of your fathers, Abraham, Ishmael, and Isaac. He is the only Lord, and to Him we have submitted ourselves."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Nay! were you witnesses when death visited Yaqoub, when he said to his sons: What will you serve after me? They said: We will serve your God and the God of your fathers, Ibrahim and Ismail and Ishaq, one God only, and to Him do we submit.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Were you present when Jacob faced the hour of death and he asked his sons, "Who will you worship after me?" They answered, "We will worship your God and the God of your fathers, Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac: the one God; we have submitted ourselves to Him."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Were ye witnesses when death appeared before Jacob? Behold, he said to his sons: "What will ye worship after me?" They said: "We shall worship Thy god and the god of thy fathers, of Abraham, Isma'il and Isaac,- the one (True) Allah: To Him we bow (in Islam)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="67">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Neither was Abraham a Jew nor a Christian, but upright and obedient, and not an idolater.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Ibrahim was neither a Jew nor a Christian; but he was a Muslim, free from all falsehood; and was not of the polytheists.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>No; Abraham in truth was not a Jew, neither a Christian; but he was a Muslim and one pure of faith; certainly he was never of the idolaters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Ibrahim was not a Jew, nor a Nazarene, but he was an upright Muslim, nor was he of the associators.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Ibrahim (Abraham) was neither a Jew nor a Christian, but he was a true Muslim Hanifa (Islamic Monotheism - to worship none but Allah Alone) and he was not of Al-Mushrikun (See V. 2:105).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Abraham was neither a Jew nor a Christian, but he was a Monotheist, a Muslim. And he was not of the Polytheists.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Abraham was neither a Jew nor a Christian; he was a Muslim, wholly devoted to God. And he certainly was not amongst those who associate others with Allah in His divinity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Ibrahim was neither a Jew nor a Christian, but he was a true Muslim Hanifa and he was not of the Mushrikin</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Abraham was not a Jew, nor yet a Christian; but he was an upright man who had surrendered (to Allah), and he was not of the idolaters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>No, Abraham was neither a Jew nor a Nazarene. He was of pure faith, a submitter (Muslim). He was never of the idolaters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Abraham was neither a Jew nor a Christian, but he was one inclining toward truth, a Muslim [submitting to Allah]. And he was not of the polytheists.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Abraham was not a Jew or a Christian. He was an upright person who had submitted himself to the will of God. Abraham was not a pagan.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Ibrahim was not a Jew nor a Christian but he was (an) upright (man), a Muslim, and he was not one of the polytheists.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Abraham was neither a Jew nor a Christian. He was an upright man, one who had surrendered himself to God. He was not one of those who associate partners with God.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Abraham was not a Jew nor yet a Christian; but he was true in Faith, and bowed his will to Allah's (Which is Islam), and he joined not gods with Allah.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="68">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Of all men the nearest to Abraham are those who follow him, and then this Prophet and the faithful; and God is the protector of all believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Undoubtedly among all mankind who have the best claim to Ibrahim are those who followed him, and this Prophet (Mohammed – peace and blessings be upon him) and the believers; and Allah is the Guardian of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Surely the people standing closest to Abraham are those who followed him, and this Prophet, and those who believe; and God is the Protector of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily the nearest of mankind to Ibrahim, surely those who followed him, and this prophet, and those who believe; and Allah is the Patron of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, among mankind who have the best claim to Ibrahim (Abraham) are those who followed him, and this Prophet (Muhammad SAW) and those who have believed (Muslims). And Allah is the Wali (Protector and Helper) of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>The people most deserving of Abraham are those who followed him, and this prophet, and those who believe. God is the Guardian of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Surely the people who have the best claim to a relationship with Abraham are those who followed him in the past, and presently this Prophet and those who believe in him; Allah is the guardian of the men of faith.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, among mankind who have the best claim to Ibrahim are those who followed him, and this Prophet and those who have believed. And Allah is the Wali (Protector and Helper) of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! those of mankind who have the best claim to Abraham are those who followed him, and this Prophet and those who believe (with him); and Allah is the Protecting Guardian of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Surely, the people who are nearest to Abraham are those who followed him, and this Prophet (Muhammad), and those who believe. Allah is the Guardian of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, the most worthy of Abraham among the people are those who followed him [in submission to Allah] and this prophet, and those who believe [in his message]. And Allah is the ally of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The nearest people to Abraham, among mankind, are those who followed him, this Prophet (Muhammad) and the true believers. God is the Guardian of the true believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Most surely the nearest of people to Ibrahim are those who followed him and this Prophet and those who believe and Allah is the guardian of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Surely, the people who are closest to Abraham are those who followed him and this Prophet [Muhammad], and those who believe in him. God is the guardian of the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Without doubt, among men, the nearest of kin to Abraham, are those who follow him, as are also this Prophet and those who believe: And Allah is the Protector of those who have faith.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>