<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="khadija, khadijah, khadeejah" generated="2026-02-01T20:59:21.386Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story generated from search: "khadija, khadijah, khadeejah"</title>
    <verses_count>20</verses_count>
    <translations_count>20</translations_count>
    <reordered>2026-02-01T20:59:21.391Z</reordered>
    <reorder_source>khadija_reorder.csv</reorder_source>
  </metadata>
  <verses>
    <verse chapter="1" verse="3">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 1</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol01</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Aisha:
(the mother of the faithful believers) The commencement of the Divine Inspiration to Allah's Apostle was in the form of good dreams which came true like bright day light, and then the love of seclusion was bestowed upon him. He used to go in seclusion in the cave of Hira where he used to worship (Allah alone) continuously for many days before his desire to see his family. He used to take with him the journey food for the stay and then come back to (his wife) Khadija to take his food like-wise again till suddenly the Truth descended upon him while he was in the cave of Hira. The angel came to him and asked him to read. The Prophet replied, "I do not know how to read.
The Prophet added, "The angel caught me (forcefully) and pressed me so hard that I could not bear it any more. He then released me and again asked me to read and I replied, 'I do not know how to read.' Thereupon he caught me again and pressed me a second time till I could not bear it any more. He then released me and again asked me to read but again I replied, 'I do not know how to read (or what shall I read)?' Thereupon he caught me for the third time and pressed me, and then released me and said, 'Read in the name of your Lord, who has created (all that exists) has created man from a clot. Read! And your Lord is the Most Generous." (96.1, 96.2, 96.3) Then Allah's Apostle returned with the Inspiration and with his heart beating severely. Then he went to Khadija bint Khuwailid and said, "Cover me! Cover me!" They covered him till his fear was over and after that he told her everything that had happened and said, "I fear that something may happen to me." Khadija replied, "Never! By Allah, Allah will never disgrace you. You keep good relations with your Kith and kin, help the poor and the destitute, serve your guests generously and assist the deserving calamity-afflicted ones."
Khadija then accompanied him to her cousin Waraqa bin Naufal bin Asad bin 'Abdul 'Uzza, who, during the PreIslamic Period became a Christian and used to write the writing with Hebrew letters. He would write from the Gospel in Hebrew as much as Allah wished him to write. He was an old man and had lost his eyesight. Khadija said to Waraqa, "Listen to the story of your nephew, O my cousin!" Waraqa asked, "O my nephew! What have you seen?" Allah's Apostle described whatever he had seen. Waraqa said, "This is the same one who keeps the secrets (angel Gabriel) whom Allah had sent to Moses. I wish I were young and could live up to the time when your people would turn you out." Allah's Apostle asked, "Will they drive me out?" Waraqa replied in the affirmative and said, "Anyone (man) who came with something similar to what you have brought was treated with hostility; and if I should remain alive till the day when you will be turned out then I would support you strongly." But after a few days Waraqa died and the Divine Inspiration was also paused for a while.
Narrated Jabir bin 'Abdullah Al-Ansari while talking about the period of pause in revelation reporting the speech of the Prophet "While I was walking, all of a sudden I heard a voice from the sky. I looked up and saw the same angel who had visited me at the cave of Hira' sitting on a chair between the sky and the earth. I got afraid of him and came back home and said, 'Wrap me (in blankets).' And then Allah revealed the following Holy Verses (of Quran):
'O you (i.e. Muhammad)! wrapped up in garments!' Arise and warn (the people against Allah's Punishment),... up to 'and desert the idols.' (74.1-5) After this the revelation started coming strongly, frequently and regularly."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="87" verse="111">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Aisha:
The commencement of the Divine Inspiration to Allah's Apostle was in the form of good righteous (true) dreams in his sleep. He never had a dream but that it came true like bright day light. He used to go in seclusion (the cave of) Hira where he used to worship(Allah Alone) continuously for many (days) nights. He used to take with him the journey food for that (stay) and then come back to (his wife) Khadija to take his food like-wise again for another period to stay, till suddenly the Truth descended upon him while he was in the cave of Hira. The angel came to him in it and asked him to read. The Prophet replied, "I do not know how to read." (The Prophet added), "The angel caught me (forcefully) and pressed me so hard that I could not bear it anymore. He then released me and again asked me to read, and I replied, "I do not know how to read," whereupon he caught me again and pressed me a second time till I could not bear it anymore. He then released me and asked me again to read, but again I replied, "I do not know how to read (or, what shall I read?)." Thereupon he caught me for the third time and pressed me and then released me and said, "Read: In the Name of your Lord, Who has created (all that exists). Has created man from a clot. Read and Your Lord is Most Generous...up to..... ..that which he knew not." (96.15)
Then Allah's Apostle returned with the Inspiration, his neck muscles twitching with terror till he entered upon Khadija and said, "Cover me! Cover me!" They covered him till his fear was over and then he said, "O Khadija, what is wrong with me?" Then he told her everything that had happened and said, 'I fear that something may happen to me." Khadija said, 'Never! But have the glad tidings, for by Allah, Allah will never disgrace you as you keep good reactions with your Kith and kin, speak the truth, help the poor and the destitute, serve your guest generously and assist the deserving, calamity-afflicted ones." Khadija then accompanied him to (her cousin) Waraqa bin Naufal bin Asad bin 'Abdul 'Uzza bin Qusai. Waraqa was the son of her paternal uncle, i.e., her father's brother, who during the Pre-Islamic Period became a Christian and used to write the Arabic writing and used to write of the Gospels in Arabic as much as Allah wished him to write. He was an old man and had lost his eyesight. Khadija said to him, "O my cousin! Listen to the story of your nephew." Waraqa asked, "O my nephew! What have you seen?" The Prophet described whatever he had seen.
Waraqa said, "This is the same Namus (i.e., Gabriel, the Angel who keeps the secrets) whom Allah had sent to Moses. I wish I were young and could live up to the time when your people would turn you out." Allah's Apostle asked, "Will they turn me out?" Waraqa replied in the affirmative and said: "Never did a man come with something similar to what you have brought but was treated with hostility. If I should remain alive till the day when you will be turned out then I would support you strongly." But after a few days Waraqa died and the Divine Inspiration was also paused for a while and the Prophet became so sad as we have heard that he intended several times to throw himself from the tops of high mountains and every time he went up the top of a mountain in order to throw himself down, Gabriel would appear before him and say, "O Muhammad! You are indeed Allah's Apostle in truth" whereupon his heart would become quiet and he would calm down and would return home. And whenever the period of the coming of the inspiration used to become long, he would do as before, but when he used to reach the top of a mountain, Gabriel would appear before him and say to him what he had said before. (Ibn 'Abbas said regarding the meaning of: 'He it is that Cleaves the daybreak (from the darkness)' (6.96) that Al-Asbah. means the light of the sun during the day and the light of the moon at night).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="478">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Aisha:
(the wife of the Prophet) The commencement (of the Divine Inspiration) to Allah's Apostle was in the form of true dreams in his sleep, for he never had a dream but it turned out to be true and clear as the bright daylight. Then he began to like seclusions, so he used to go in seclusion in the cave of Hira where he used to worship Allah continuously for many nights before going back to his family to take the necessary provision (of food) for the stay. He come back to (his wife) Khadija again to take his provision (of food) likewise, till one day he received the Guidance while he was in the cave of Hira. An Angel came to him and asked him to read. Allah's Apostle replied, "I do not know how to read." The Prophet added, "Then the Angel held me (forcibly) and pressed me so hard that I felt distressed. Then he released me and again asked me to read, and I replied, 'I do not know how to read.' Thereupon he held me again and pressed me for the second time till I felt distressed. He then released me and asked me to read, but again I replied. 'I do not know how to read.' Thereupon he held me for the third time and pressed me till I got distressed, and then he released me and said, 'Read, in the Name of your Lord Who has created (all that exists), has created man out of a clot, Read! And your Lord is the Most Generous. Who has taught (the writing) by the pen, has taught man that which he knew not." (96.1-5).
Then Allah's Apostle returned with that experience; and the muscles between his neck and shoulders were trembling till he came upon Khadija (his wife) and said, "Cover me!" They covered him, and when the state of fear was over, he said to Khadija, "O Khadija! What is wrong with me? I was afraid that something bad might happen to me." Then he told her the story. Khadija said, "Nay! But receive the good tidings! By Allah, Allah will never disgrace you, for by Allah, you keep good relations with your Kith and kin, speak the truth, help the poor and the destitute, entertain your guests generously and assist those who are stricken with calamities." Khadija then took him to Waraqa bin Naufil, the son of Khadija's paternal uncle. Waraqa had been converted to Christianity in the Pre-lslamic Period and used to write Arabic and write of the Gospel in Arabic as much as Allah wished him to write. He was an old man and had lost his eyesight. Khadija said (to Waraqa), "O my cousin! Listen to what your nephew is going to say." Waraqa said, "O my nephew! What have you seen?" The Prophet then described whatever he had seen. Waraqa said, "This is the same Angel (Gabriel) who was sent to Moses. I wish I were young." He added some other statement. Allah's Apostle asked, "Will these people drive me out?" Waraqa said, "Yes, for nobody brought the like of what you have brought, but was treated with hostility. If I were to remain alive till your day (when you start preaching). then I would support you strongly." But a short while later Waraqa died and the Divine Inspiration was paused (stopped) for a while so that Allah's Apostle was very much grieved.
Narrated Jabir bin 'Abdullah: While Allah's Apostle was talking about the period of pause in revelation. he said in his narration. "Once while I was walking, all of a sudden I heard a voice from the sky. I looked up and saw to my surprise, the same Angel as had visited me in the cave of Hira.' He was sitting on a chair between the sky and the earth. I got afraid of him and came back home and said, Wrap me! Wrap me!" So they covered him and then Allah revealed:
'O you, wrapped up! Arise and warn and your Lord magnify, and your garments purify and dessert the idols.' (74.1-5)
Abu Salama said, "(Rijz) are the idols which the people of the Pre-lslamic period used to worship." After this the revelation started coming frequently and regularly.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="605">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Aisha:
The Prophet returned to Khadija while his heart was beating rapidly. She took him to Waraqa bin Naufal who was a Christian convert and used to read the Gospels in Arabic Waraqa asked (the Prophet), "What do you see?" When he told him, Waraqa said, "That is the same angel whom Allah sent to the Prophet) Moses. Should I live till you receive the Divine Message, I will support you strongly."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="481">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Aisha:
The Prophet returned to Khadija and said, "Wrap me! Wrap me!" (Then the sub-narrator narrated the rest of the narration.)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="444">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Yahya bin Abi Kathir:
I asked Aba Salama bin 'Abdur-Rahman about the first Sura revealed of the Qur'an. He replied "O you, wrapped-up (i.e. Al Muddaththir)." I said, "They say it was, 'Read, in the Name of your Lord Who created,' (i.e. Surat Al-'Alaq (the Clot)." On that, Abu Salama said, "I asked Jabir bin 'Abdullah about that, saying the same as you have said, whereupon he said, 'I will not tell you except what Allah's Apostle had told us. Allah's Apostle said, "I was in seclusion in the cave of Hiram', and after I completed the limited period of my seclusion. I came down (from the cave) and heard a voice calling me. I looked to my right, but saw nothing. Then I looked up and saw something. So I went to Khadija (the Prophet's wife) and told her to wrap me up and pour cold water on me. So they wrapped me up and poured cold water on me." Then, 'O you, (Muhammad) wrapped up! Arise and warn,' (Surat Al Muddaththir) was revealed." (74.1)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="187">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn Abi Mulaika:
There was a disagreement between them (i.e. Ibn 'Abbas and Ibn Az-Zubair) so I went to Ibn 'Abbas in the morning and said (to him), "Do you want to fight against Ibn Zubair and thus make lawful what Allah has made unlawful (i.e. fighting in Meccas?" Ibn 'Abbas said, "Allah forbid! Allah ordained that Ibn Zubair and Bani Umaiya would permit (fighting in Mecca), but by Allah, I will never regard it as permissible." Ibn Abbas added. "The people asked me to take the oath of allegiance to Ibn AzZubair. I said, 'He is really entitled to assume authority for his father, Az-Zubair was the helper of the Prophet, his (maternal) grandfather, Abu Bakr was (the Prophet's) companion in the cave, his mother, Asma' was 'Dhatun-Nitaq', his aunt, 'Aisha was the mother of the Believers, his paternal aunt, Khadija was the wife of the Prophet , and the paternal aunt of the Prophet was his grandmother. He himself is pious and chaste in Islam, well versed in the Knowledge of the Quran. By Allah! (Really, I left my relatives, Bani Umaiya for his sake though) they are my close relatives, and if they should be my rulers, they are equally apt to be so and are descended from a noble family.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="168">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Gabriel came to the Prophet and said, "O Allah's Apostle! This is Khadija coming to you with a dish having meat soup (or some food or drink). When she reaches you, greet her on behalf of her Lord (i.e. Allah) and on my behalf, and give her the glad tidings of having a Qasab palace in Paradise wherein there will be neither any noise nor any fatigue (trouble) . "
Narrated 'Aisha: Once Hala bint Khuwailid, Khadija's sister, asked the permission of the Prophet to enter. On that, the Prophet remembered the way Khadija used to ask permission, and that upset him. He said, "O Allah! Hala!" So I became jealous and said, "What makes you remember an old woman amongst the old women of Quraish an old woman (with a teethless mouth) of red gums who died long ago, and in whose place Allah has given you somebody better than her?"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="588">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said that Gabriel said, "Here is Khadija coming to you with a dish of food or a tumbler containing something to drink. Convey to her a greeting from her Lord (Allah) and give her the glad tidings that she will have a palace in Paradise built of Qasab wherein there will be neither any noise nor any fatigue (trouble)." (See Hadith No. 168, Vol. 5)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="19">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Isma'il:
Abdullah bin Abu Aufa said: "Allah's Apostle performed 'Umra and we too performed 'Umra along with him. When he entered Mecca he performed the Tawaf (of Ka'ba) and we too performed it along with him, and then he came to the As-Safa and Al-Marwa (i.e. performed the Sai) and we also came to them along with him. We were shielding him from the people of Mecca lest they may hit him with an arrow." A friend of his asked him (i.e. 'Abdullah bin Aufa), "Did the Prophet enter the Ka'ba (during that 'Umra)?" He replied in the negative. Then he said, "What did he (the Prophet ) say about Khadija?" He (Abdullah bin Aufa) said, "(He said) 'Give Khadija the good tidings that she will have a palace made of Qasab in Paradise and there will be neither noise nor any trouble in it."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="167">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ismail:
I asked 'Abdullah bin Abi Aufa, "Did the Prophet give glad tidings to Khadija?" He said, "Yes, of a palace of Qasab (in Paradise) where there will be neither any noise nor any fatigue."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="236">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Hisham's father:
Khadija died three years before the Prophet departed to Medina. He stayed there for two years or so and then he married 'Aisha when she was a girl of six years of age, and he consumed that marriage when she was nine years old.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="642">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Ali:
I heard the Prophet saying, "Mary, the daughter of 'Imran, was the best among the women (of the world of her time) and Khadija is the best amongst the women. (of this nation)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="163">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Ali:
The Prophet said, "The best of the world's women is Mary (at her lifetime), and the best of the world's women is Khadija (at her lifetime)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="164">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated
'Aisha: I did not feel jealous of any of the wives of the Prophet as much as I did of Khadija (although) she died before he married me, for I often heard him mentioning her, and Allah had told him to give her the good tidings that she would have a palace of Qasab (i.e. pipes of precious stones and pearls in Paradise), and whenever he slaughtered a sheep, he would send her women-friends a good share of it.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="165">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Aisha:
I did not feel jealous of any woman as much as I did of Khadija because Allah's Apostle used to mention her very often. He married me after three years of her death, and his Lord (or Gabriel) ordered him to give her the good news of having a palace of Qasab in Paradise.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="62" verse="156">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Aisha:
I never felt so jealous of any wife of Allah's Apostle as I did of Khadija because Allah's Apostle used to remember and praise her too often and because it was revealed to Allah's Apostle that he should give her (Khadija) the glad tidings of her having a palace of Qasab in Paradise .</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="58" verse="166">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Aisha:
I did not feel jealous of any of the wives of the Prophet as much as I did of Khadija though I did not see her, but the Prophet used to mention her very often, and when ever he slaughtered a sheep, he would cut its parts and send them to the women friends of Khadija. When I sometimes said to him, "(You treat Khadija in such a way) as if there is no woman on earth except Khadija," he would say, "Khadija was such-and-such, and from her I had children."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="73" verse="33">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Aisha:
I never felt so jealous of any woman as I did of Khadija, though she had died three years before the Prophet married me, and that was because I heard him mentioning her too often, and because his Lord had ordered him to give her the glad tidings that she would have a palace in Paradise, made of Qasab and because he used to slaughter a sheep and distribute its meat among her friends.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="576">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Aisha:
I never felt so jealous of any woman as I felt of Khadija, for Allah ordered him (the Prophet ) to give Khadija the glad tidings of a palace in Paradise (for her).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>