<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="noah, nuh, ark" generated="2026-02-01T00:43:52.169Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story generated from search: "noah, nuh, ark"</title>
    <verses_count>98</verses_count>
    <translations_count>843</translations_count>
    <reordered>2026-02-01T00:43:52.169Z</reordered>
    <reorder_source>noah_reorder.csv</reorder_source>
  </metadata>
  <verses>
    <verse chapter="3" verse="33">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>God had chosen Adam and Noah and the families of Abraham and 'Imran in preference to others.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>God chose Adam and Noah and the House of Abraham and the House of Imran above all beings, the</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily did Allah choose Adam and Nuh and the house of lbrahim and the house of 'lmran out of the worlds</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Allah chose Adam, Nuh (Noah), the family of Ibrahim (Abraham) and the family of 'Imran above the 'Alamin (mankind and jinns) (of their times).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>God chose Adam, and Noah, and the family of Abraham, and the family of Imran, over all mankind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Truly Allah chose Adam and Noah and the descendants of Abraham and of 'Imran above all mankind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Allah chose Adam, Nuh (Noah), the family of Ibrahim and the family of `Imran above the nations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! Allah preferred Adam and Noah and the Family of Abraham and the Family of 'Imran above (all His) creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Indeed Allah chose Adam and Noah, and the progeny of Abraham and the progeny of Imran above all the nations;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Allah chose Adam and Noah, the House of Abraham and the House of Imran above all worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, Allah chose Adam and Noah and the family of Abraham and the family of 'Imran over the worlds -</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>God chose (and gave distinction to) Adam, Noah, the family of Abraham, and Imran over all the people of the world.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely Allah chose Adam and Nuh and the descendants of Ibrahim and the descendants of Imran above the nations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>God chose Adam and Noah and the family of Abraham and the family of 'Imran above all His creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Allah did choose Adam and Noah, the family of Abraham, and the family of 'Imran above all people,-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="163">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We have sent revelations to you as We sent revelations to Noah and the prophets (who came) after him; and We sent revelations to Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob, and their offspring, and to Jesus and Job, and to Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and to David We gave the Book of Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed We sent a divine revelation to you (Prophet Mohammed – peace and blessing be upon him) as We did send divine revelations to Nooh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; and We sent divine revelations to Ibrahim (Abraham) and Ismael (Ishmael) and Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob) and their offspring, and Eisa (Jesus) and Ayyub (Job) and Yunus (Jonah) and Haroon (Aaron) and Sulaiman (Solomon), and We bestowed the Zaboor (the Holy Book) upon Dawud (David).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We have revealed to thee as We revealed to Noah, and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, Jesus and Job, Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We have revealed unto thee even as We revealed unto Nuh and the prophets after him, and as We revealed unto Ibrahim and Isma'il and Is-haq and Ya'qub and the tribes, and 'Isa and Ayyub and Yunus and Harun and Sulaiman, and unto Daud We vouchsafed a Scripture.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, We have inspired you (O Muhammad SAW) as We inspired Nuh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; We (also) inspired Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma'il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya'qub (Jacob), and Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya'qub (Jacob)], 'Iesa (Jesus), Ayub (Job), Yunus (Jonah), Harun (Aaron), and Sulaiman (Solomon), and to Dawud (David) We gave the Zabur (Psalms).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We have inspired you, as We had inspired Noah and the prophets after him. And We inspired Abraham, and Ishmael, and Isaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs, and Jesus, and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron, and Solomon. And We gave David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(O Muhammad!) We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the offspring of Jacob, and Jesus and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, We have sent the revelation to you as We sent the revelation to Nuh and the Prophets after him; We (also) sent the revelation to Ibrahim, Isma`il, Ishaq, Ya`qub, and Al-Asbat, (the offspring of the twelve sons of Ya`qub) `Isa, Ayyub, Yunus, Harun, and Sulayman; and to Dawud We gave the Zabur.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! We inspire thee as We inspired Noah and the prophets after him, as We inspired Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob and the tribes, and Jesus and Job and Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and as We imparted unto David the Psalms;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>We have indeed revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and the prophets after him, and [as] We revealed to Abraham and Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, Jesus and Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon—and We gave David the Psalms—</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and to the Prophets after him, and We revealed to (Prophets) Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the tribes, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and We gave to David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, We have revealed to you, [O Muhammad], as We revealed to Noah and the prophets after him. And we revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, the Descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and to David We gave the book [of Psalms].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), We have sent revelations to you just as were sent to Noah and the Prophets who lived after him and to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, his descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon. We gave the Psalms to David.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely We have revealed to you as We revealed to Nuh, and the prophets after him, and We revealed to Ibrahim and Ismail and Ishaq and Yaqoub and the tribes, and Isa and Ayub and Yunus and Haroun and Sulaiman and We gave to Dawood</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We have sent revelation to you [Prophet] as We did to Noah and the prophets who came after him, to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon and David, to whom We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We have sent thee inspiration, as We sent it to Noah and the Messengers after him: we sent inspiration to Abraham, Isma'il, Isaac, Jacob and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and solomon, and to David We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="84">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided them, as We had guided Noah before them, and of his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus We reward those who are upright and do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave to him Isaac and Jacob -- each one We guided, And Noah We guided before; and of his seed David and Solomon, Job and Joseph, Moses and Aaron -- even so We recompense the good-doers --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Is-haq and Ya'qub: each one We guided. And Nuh We had guided afore, and of his progeny Da-ud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Musa and Harun. And thus We recompense the well-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob), each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh (Noah), and among his progeny Dawud (David), Sulaiman (Solomon), Ayub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses), and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob—each of them We guided. And We guided Noah previously; and from his descendants David, and Solomon, and Job, and Joseph, and Moses, and Aaron. Thus We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon Abraham (offspring) Ishaq (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob) and each of them did We guide to the right way as We had earlier guided Noah to the right way; and (of his descendants We guided) Da'ud (David) and Sulayman (Solomon), Ayyub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses) and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward those who do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq and Ya`qub, each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh and among his progeny Dawud, Sulayman, Ayyub, Yusuf, Musa, and Harun. Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Isaac and Jacob; each of them We guided; and Noah did We guide aforetime; and of his seed (We guided) David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided each of them. And Noah We had guided before, and from his offspring, David and Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron—thus do We reward the virtuous—</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided both; and We guided Noah before them, among his descendants were David and Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron as such, We recompense the gooddoers,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob - all [of them] We guided. And Noah, We guided before; and among his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave (Abraham) Isaac and Jacob. Both had received Our guidance. Noah received Our guidance before Abraham and so did his descendants: David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron. Thus is the reward for the righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave to him Ishaq and Yaqoub; each did We guide, and Nuh did We guide before, and of his descendants, Dawood and Sulaiman and Ayub and Yusuf and Musa and Haroun; and thus do We reward those who do good (to others).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob, each of whom We guided as We had guided Noah before. Among his descendants were David and Solomon, and Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob: all (three) guided: and before him, We guided Noah, and among his progeny, David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron: thus do We reward those who do good:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="33" verse="7">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When We made the covenant with the prophets, and with you, as with Noah and Abraham, Moses and Jesus son of Mary, a binding covenant,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when We took compact from the Prophets, and from thee, and from Noah, and Abraham, Moses, and Jesus, Mary's son; We took from them a solemn compact,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And recall what time We took a bond from the prophets and from thee and from Nuh and Ibrahim and Musa and 'Isa son of Maryam. And We took from them a solemn bond;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) when We took from the Prophets their covenant, and from you (O Muhammad SAW), and from Nuh (Noah), Ibrahim (Abraham), Musa (Moses), and 'Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary). We took from them a strong covenant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Recall that We received a pledge from the prophets, and from you, and from Noah, and Abraham, and Moses, and Jesus son of Mary. We received from them a solemn pledge.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And call to mind, (O Prophet), when We took the covenant from all Prophets; and also from you and Noah and Abraham, Moses, and Jesus the son of Mary. We took from them a solemn covenant</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And when We took from the Prophets their covenant, and from you, and from Nuh, Ibrahim, Musa, and `Isa son of Maryam. We took from them a strong covenant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when We exacted a covenant from the prophets, and from thee (O Muhammad) and from Noah and Abraham and Moses and Jesus son of Mary. We took from them a solemn covenant;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>[Recall] when We took a pledge from the prophets, and from you and from Noah and Abraham and Moses and Jesus son of Mary, and We took from them a solemn pledge,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We took from the Prophets their covenant and from you (Prophet Muhammad), from Noah and Abraham, from Moses and Jesus the son of Mary. We took a solemn covenant from them,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention, O Muhammad], when We took from the prophets their covenant and from you and from Noah and Abraham and Moses and Jesus, the son of Mary; and We took from them a solemn covenant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We had a solemn covenant with you (Muhammad), and the Prophets: Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Jesus, the son of Mary.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when We made a covenant with the prophets and with you, and with Nuh and Ibrahim and Musa and Isa, son of Marium, and We made with them a strong covenant</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We took a solemn pledge from the prophets, from you and Noah, Abraham, Moses and Jesus, the son of Mary -- We took a solemn pledge from all of them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And remember We took from the prophets their covenant: As (We did) from thee: from Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Jesus the son of Mary: We took from them a solemn covenant:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="42" verse="13">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>He has laid down for you the (same) way of life and belief which He had commended to Noah, and which We have enjoined on you, and which We had bequeathed to Abraham, Moses and Jesus, so that they should maintain the order and not be divided among themselves. Heavy is to idolaters what you invite them to. God chooses whom He please for Himself, and guides to Himself whoever turns to Him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>He has laid down for you as religion that He charged Noah with, and that We have revealed to thee, and that We charged Abraham with, Moses and Jesus: 'Perform the religion, and scatter not regarding it. Very hateful is that for the idolaters, that thou callest them to. God chooses unto Himself whomsoever He will, and He guides to Himself whosoever turns, penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He hath instituted for you in religion that which He had enjoined upon Nuh, and which We have revealed Unto thee, and which We had enjoined upon Ibrahim and Musa and Isa, saying: establish the religion, and be not divided therein. Grievous Unto the associaters is that Unto which thou callest them. Allah chooseth for Himself whomsoever He will and guideth Unto Himself whomsoever turneth in penitence.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He (Allah) has ordained for you the same religion (Islam) which He ordained for Nuh (Noah), and that which We have inspired in you (O Muhammad SAW), and that which We ordained for Ibrahim (Abraham), Musa (Moses) and 'Iesa (Jesus) saying you should establish religion (i.e. to do what it orders you to do practically), and make no divisions in it (religion) (i.e. various sects in religion). Intolerable for the Mushrikun, is that to which you (O Muhammad SAW) call them. Allah chooses for Himself whom He wills, and guides unto Himself who turns to Him in repentance and in obedience.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He prescribed for you the same religion He enjoined upon Noah, and what We inspired to you, and what We enjoined upon Abraham, and Moses, and Jesus: “You shall uphold the religion, and be not divided therein.” As for the idolaters, what you call them to is outrageous to them. God chooses to Himself whom He wills, and He guides to Himself whoever repents.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>He has prescribed for you the religion which He enjoined upon Noah and which We revealed to you (O Muhammad), and which We enjoined upon Abraham and Moses and Jesus, commanding: “Establish this religion and do not split up regarding it.” What you are calling to is very hard upon those who associate others with Allah in His Divinity. Allah chooses for Himself whomsoever He pleases and guides to Himself whoever penitently turns to Him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He (Allah) has ordained for you the same religion which He ordained for Nuh, and that which We have revealed to you, and that which We ordained for Ibrahim, Musa and `Isa saying you should establish religion and make no divisions in it. Intolerable for the idolators is that to which you call them. Allah chooses for Himself whom He wills, and guides unto Himself who turns to Him in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He hath ordained for you that religion which He commended unto Noah, and that which We inspire in thee (Muhammad), and that which We commended unto Abraham and Moses and Jesus, saying: Establish the religion, and be not divided therein. Dreadful for the idolaters is that unto which thou callest them. Allah chooseth for Himself whom He will, and guideth unto Himself him who turneth (toward Him).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>He has prescribed for you the religion which He had enjoined upon Noah and which We have [also] revealed to you, and which We had enjoined upon Abraham, Moses and Jesus, declaring, ‘Maintain the religion, and do not be divided in it.’ Hard on the polytheists is that to which you summon them. Allah chooses for it whomever He wishes, and He guides to it whomever returns penitently [to Him].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He has made plain for you the Religion with which He charged Noah and that which We have revealed to you, and that with which We charged (Prophets) Abraham, Moses and Jesus, (saying): 'Establish the Religion and do not be divided therein' That which you invite them to is too overwhelming for the idolaters. Allah brings close to Himself whom He will, and guides to Him those who turn in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>He has ordained for you of religion what He enjoined upon Noah and that which We have revealed to you, [O Muhammad], and what We enjoined upon Abraham and Moses and Jesus - to establish the religion and not be divided therein. Difficult for those who associate others with Allah is that to which you invite them. Allah chooses for Himself whom He wills and guides to Himself whoever turns back [to Him].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>He has plainly clarified the religion which is revealed to you and that which Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Jesus were commanded to follow (He has explained it) so that you would be steadfast and united in your religion. What you call the pagans to is extremely grave for them. God attracts to (the religion) whomever He wants and guides to it whoever turns to Him in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He has made plain to you of the religion what He enjoined upon Nuh and that which We have revealed to you and that which We enjoined upon Ibrahim and Musa and Isa that keep to obedience and be not divided therein; hard to the unbelievers is that which you call them to; Allah chooses for Himself whom He pleases, and guides to Himself him who turns (to Him), frequently.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>God has ordained for you the same religion which He enjoined on Noah, and which We have revealed to you, and which We enjoined upon Abraham and Moses and Jesus, so that you should remain steadfast in religion and not become divided in it. What you call upon the polytheists to do is hard for them; God chooses for Himself whoever He pleases and guides towards Himself those who turn to Him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>The same religion has He established for you as that which He enjoined on Noah - the which We have sent by inspiration to thee - and that which We enjoined on Abraham, Moses, and Jesus: Namely, that ye should remain steadfast in religion, and make no divisions therein: to those who worship other things than Allah, hard is the (way) to which thou callest them. Allah chooses to Himself those whom He pleases, and guides to Himself those who turn (to Him).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="57" verse="26">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We sent Noah and Abraham, and gave prophethood to their progeny and the Book, and some of them are well-directed, but many of them are disobedient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We sent Noah, and Abraham, and We appointed the Prophecy and the Book to be among their seed; and some of them are guided, and many of them are ungodly.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We sent Nuh and Ibrahim, and We placed in the posterity of the twain the prophecy and the Book. Then of them some are guided ones, and many of them are transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed, We sent Nuh (Noah) and Ibrahim (Abraham), and placed in their offspring Prophethood and Scripture, and among them there is he who is guided, but many of them are Fasiqun (rebellious, disobedient to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We sent Noah and Abraham, and established in their line Prophethood and the Scripture. Some of them are guided, but many of them are sinners.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Indeed We sent forth Noah and Abraham and established in their line Prophecy and the Book. Then some of them embraced the guidance and many of them are wicked.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed, We sent Nuh and Ibrahim, and placed in their offspring prophethood and Scripture. And among them there are some who are guided; but many of them are rebellious.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We verily sent Noah and Abraham and placed the prophethood and the scripture among their seed, and among them there is he who goeth right, but many of them are evil-livers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We sent Noah and Abraham and We ordained among their descendants prophethood and the Book. Some of them are [rightly] guided, and many of them are transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We sent forth Noah and Abraham, and appointed the Prophethood and the Book to be given to their descendants. Some were guided, but many wereimpious.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We have already sent Noah and Abraham and placed in their descendants prophethood and scripture; and among them is he who is guided, but many of them are defiantly disobedient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We sent Noah and Abraham and placed prophethood and the Book among their offsprings, some of whom have the right guidance. However, most of them are evil doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We sent Nuh and Ibrahim and We gave to their offspring the (gift of) prophecy and the Book; so there are among them those who go aright, and most of them are transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We sent forth Noah and Abraham and bestowed upon their offspring prophethood and the Book. Some of them were rightly guided, but many others were transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We sent Noah and Abraham, and established in their line Prophethood and Revelation: and some of them were on right guidance. But many of them became rebellious transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="19" verse="58">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>These are (some of) those who were favoured by God among the prophets of the progeny of Adam, and of those We bore in the ark with Noah, and the offspring of Abraham and Israel, and of those We guided and We chose, for they bowed weeping in adoration when the revelations of Ar-Rahman were recited to them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>These are they whom God has blessed among the Prophets of the seed of Adam, and of those We bore with Noah, and of the seed of Abraham and Israel, and of those We guided and chose. When the signs of the All-merciful were recited to them, they fell down prostrate, weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>These are they whom Allah hath favoured, from among the prophets, of the progeny of Adam and of them whom We bare with Nuh, and of the progeny of Ibrahim and Isra'il, and of those whom We have guided and chosen; whenever the revelations of the Compassionate were rehearsed unto them, they fell down prostrating themselves and weeping. *Chapter: 19</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Those were they unto whom Allah bestowed His Grace from among the Prophets, of the offspring of Adam, and of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Nuh (Noah), and of the offspring of Ibrahim (Abraham) and Israel and from among those whom We guided and chose. When the Verses of the Most Beneficent (Allah) were recited unto them, they fell down prostrating and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>These are some of the prophets God has blessed, from the descendants of Adam, and from those We carried with Noah, and from the descendants of Abraham and Israel, and from those We guided and selected. Whenever the revelations of the Most Gracious are recited to them, they would fall down, prostrating and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>These are the Prophets upon whom Allah bestowed His favour from the seed of Adam, and from the seed of those whom We carried (in the Ark) with Noah, and from the seed of Abraham and Israel. They were those whom We guided and chose (for an exalted position). They were such that when the words of the Most Compassionate Lord were recited to them, they fell down in prostration, weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Those were they unto whom Allah bestowed His grace from among the Prophets, of the offspring of Adam, and of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Nuh, and of the offspring of Ibrahim and Israel, and from among those whom We guided and chose. When the Ayat of the Most Gracious were recited unto them, they fell down prostrate and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>These are they unto whom Allah showed favour from among the prophets, of the seed of Adam and of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Noah, and of the seed of Abraham and Israel, and from among those whom We guided and chose. When the revelations of the Beneficent were recited unto them, they fell down, adoring and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>They are the ones whom Allah has blessed from among the prophets of Adam’s progeny, and from [the progeny of] those We carried with Noah, and from among the progeny of Abraham and Israel, and from among those that We guided and chose. When the signs of the All-beneficent were recited to them, they would fall down weeping in prostration.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>These are whom Allah has blessed among the Prophets from among the seed of Adam and of those whom We bore with Noah; the descendants ofAbraham, of Israel, and of those whom We have guided and chose. For when the verses of the Merciful were recited to them, they fell down prostrate, weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Those were the ones upon whom Allah bestowed favor from among the prophets of the descendants of Adam and of those We carried [in the ship] with Noah, and of the descendants of Abraham and Israel, and of those whom We guided and chose. When the verses of the Most Merciful were recited to them, they fell in prostration and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>These were the Prophets from the offspring of Adam, from those who embarked with Noah and from the offspring of Abraham and Israel. God guided them and chose them for His favor. Whenever they would hear the revelations of the Beneficent God they would bow down in prostration with tears.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>These are they on whom Allah bestowed favors, from among the prophets of the seed of Adam, and of those whom We carried with Nuh, and of the seed of Ibrahim and Israel, and of those whom We guided and chose; when the communications of the Beneficent Allah were recited to them, they fell down making obeisance and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>These are the ones whom God has favoured: the prophets from among the descendants of Adam and of those whom We carried in the Ark with Noah; the descendants of Abraham, of Israel, and of those whom We have guided and chosen. For when the revelations of the Merciful were recited to them, they fell down, prostrating themselves and weeping.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Those were some of the prophets on whom Allah did bestow His Grace,- of the posterity of Adam, and of those who We carried (in the Ark) with Noah, and of the posterity of Abraham and Israel of those whom We guided and chose. Whenever the Signs of (Allah) Most Gracious were rehearsed to them, they would fall down in prostrate adoration and in tears.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="71" verse="1">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>SENT NOAH to his people to warn them before the painful punishment came upon them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people, saying, 'Warn thy people, ere there come on them a painful chastisement.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We! We sent Nuh Unto his people saying: warn thy people ere there come Unto them torment afflictive.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, We sent Nuh (Noah) to his people (Saying): "Warn your people before there comes to them a painful torment."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people: “Warn your people before there comes upon them a painful punishment.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people (and directed him): “Warn your people before a grievous chastisement comes upon them.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, We sent Nuh to his people (saying): "Warn your people before there comes to them a painful torment."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! We sent Noah unto his people (saying): Warn thy people ere the painful doom come unto them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Indeed We sent Noah to his people, [saying,] ‘Warn your people before a painful punishment overtakes them.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We sent Noah to his nation, saying: 'Give warning to your nation before a painful punishment overtakes them'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, We sent Noah to his people, [saying], "Warn your people before there comes to them a painful punishment."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people telling him, "Warn your people before a painful torment approaches them".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely We sent Nuh to his people, saying: Warn your people before there come upon them a painful chastisement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We sent Noah forth to his people, saying, "Warn your people before there comes upon them a grievous punishment."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We sent Noah to his People (with the Command): "Do thou warn thy People before there comes to them a grievous Penalty."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="71" verse="2">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: “My people, I have certainly been sent as a clear warner to you,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah said, "My people, I am warning you plainly.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>[Noah] said, "My people! I am but a plain warner to you,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="59">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people, and he said: "O people worship God; you have no other god but He; for I fear the retribution of the great Day may fall on you."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We sent Noah to his people; and he said, 'O my people, serve God! You have no god other' than He; truly, I fear for you the chastisement of a dreadful day.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Assuredly We sent Nuh unto his people, and he said: O my people! worship Allah; no god ye have but He; verily I fear for you the torment of a mighty day.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Indeed, We sent Nuh (Noah) to his people and he said: "O my people! Worship Allah! You have no other Ilah (God) but Him. (La ilaha ill-Allah: none has the right to be worshipped but Allah). Certainly, I fear for you the torment of a Great Day!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people. He said, “O my people! Worship God; you have no god other than Him. I fear for you the punishment of a tremendous Day.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Indeed We sent forth Noah to his people and he said: 'O my people! Serve Allah, you have no other god than Him Indeed I fear for you the chastisement of an awesome Day.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Indeed, We sent Nuh to his people and he said: "O my people! Worship Allah! You have no other god but Him. Certainly, I fear for you the torment of a Great Day!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>We sent Noah (of old) unto his people, and he said: O my people! Serve Allah. Ye have no other Allah save Him. Lo! I fear for you the retribution of an Awful Day.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We sent Noah to his people. He said, ‘O my people, worship Allah! You have no other god besides Him. Indeed I fear for you the punishment of a tremendous day.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We sent forth Noah to his nation. He said: 'Worship Allah, my people for you have no god except He. I fear for you the punishment of a great Day.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>We had certainly sent Noah to his people, and he said, "O my people, worship Allah; you have no deity other than Him. Indeed, I fear for you the punishment of a tremendous Day.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people. He told them, "Worship God for He is your only Lord. I am afraid of the punishment that you might suffer on the great Day (of Judgment)".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Certainly We sent Nuh to his people, so he said: O my people! serve Allah, you have no god other than Him; surely I fear for you the chastisement of a grievous day.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people. He said, "O my people, worship God; you have no other god but He. I fear for you the punishment of a dreadful Day,"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people. He said: "O my people! worship Allah! ye have no other god but Him. I fear for you the punishment of a dreadful day!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="25">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people (and he said): "I give you a clear warning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We sent Noah to his people: 'I am for you a warner, and a bearer of good tidings:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We sent Nuh unto his people saying: verily I am unto you a plain warner.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We sent Nuh (Noah) to his people (and he said): "I have come to you as a plain warner."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people, “I am to you a clear warner.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(Such were the circumstances) when We sent forth Noah to his people. (He said): 'I have been sent to you to warn you plainly</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed We sent Nuh to his people (and he said): "I have come to you as a plain warner."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We sent Noah unto his folk (and he said): Lo! I am a plain warner unto you.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We sent Noah to his people [to declare]: ‘Indeed I am a manifest warner to you.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We sent Noah to his nation. (He said:) 'I am a warner for you, and a bearer of glad tidings.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We had certainly sent Noah to his people, [saying], "Indeed, I am to you a clear warner</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people to give them the clear warning</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We sent Nuh to his people: Surely I am a plain warner for you:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people. He said, "I have come to you with a clear warning:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people (with a mission): "I have come to you with a Clear Warning:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="26">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>that they should not worship anyone besides God. (Noah warned them), "I am afraid that you will suffer the most painful torment".</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="23">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people. He said: "O my people, worship God, for you have no other god but He. Will you not take heed for yourselves?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We sent Noah to his people; and he, said, 'O my people, serve God! You have no god other than He. Will you not be godfearing?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We sent Nuh unto his people, and he said: O my people! worship Allah; for you there is no god but he; will ye not then fear Him!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We sent Nuh (Noah) to his people, and he said: "O my people! Worship Allah! You have no other Ilah (God) but Him (Islamic Monotheism). Will you not then be afraid (of Him i.e. of His Punishment because of worshipping others besides Him)?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people. He said, “O my people, worship God, you have no deity other than Him. Will you not take heed?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people, and he said: "My people! Serve Allah; you have no deity other than He. Do you have no fear?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed We sent Nuh to his people, and he said: "O my people! Worship Allah! You have no other God but Him. Will you not then have Taqwa"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We verily sent Noah unto his folk, and he said: O my people! Serve Allah. Ye have no other Allah save Him. Will ye not ward off (evil)?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We sent Noah to his people, and he said, ‘O my people! Worship Allah! You have no other god besides Him. Will you not then be wary [of Him]?’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We sent Noah to his nation. 'Worship Allah, my nation' he said, 'for you have no god except He. Will you not be cautious'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We had certainly sent Noah to his people, and he said, "O my people, worship Allah; you have no deity other than Him; then will you not fear Him?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people who said, "My people, worship God for He is your only Lord. Will you then not have fear of Him?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We sent Nuh to his people, and he said: O my people! serve Allah, you have no god other than Him; will you not then guard (against evil)?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people, and he said, "My people, worship God; you have no other deity except Him. Will you not fear Him?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(Further, We sent a long line of prophets for your instruction). We sent Noah to his people: He said, "O my people! worship Allah! Ye have no other god but Him. Will ye not fear (Him)?"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="106">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When their brother Noah said to them: "Will you not take heed?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>when their brother Noah said to them, 'Will you not be godfearing?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>When their brother Nuh said Unto them: fear ye not?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>When their brother Nuh (Noah) said to them: "Will you not fear Allah and obey Him?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Their brother Noah said to them, “Do you not fear?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Recall when their brother Noah said to them: "Do you have no fear?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>When their brother Nuh said to them: "Will you not have Taqwa"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>When their brother Noah said unto them: Will ye not ward off (evil)?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>when Noah, their brother, said to them, ‘Will you not be wary [of Allah]?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>when Noah, their brother, said to them: 'Will you not be cautious?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>When their brother Noah said to them, "Will you not fear Allah?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>span class="col"&gt;Their brother Noah asked them, "Why do you not fear God?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>When their brother Nuh said to them: Will you not guard (against evil)?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When their brother Noah said to them, "Will you have no fear of God?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Behold, their brother Noah said to them: "Will ye not fear (Allah)?</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="71" verse="5">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah said, "My Lord, I have been preaching to my people, night and day,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="28">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: 'My people! If I base myself on a clear evidence from my Lord, and I have also been blessed by His mercy to which you have been blind, how can we force it upon you despite your aversion to it?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah replied, "My people do you think - that if my Lord has sent me a miracle and granted me mercy but your ignorance has obscured them from your sight - we can force you to believe when you do not want to?</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="61">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>[Nuh (Noah)] said: "O my people! There is no error in me, but I am a Messenger from the Lord of the 'Alamin (mankind, jinns and all that exists)!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>[Nuh] said: "O my people! There is no error in me, but I am a Messenger from the Lord of all that exists!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[Noah] said, "O my people, there is not error in me, but I am a messenger from the Lord of the worlds."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Noah) said, "My people, I am not in any error, rather I am a Messenger from the Lord of the Universe,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Said [Noah], "O my people! I am not in error. Indeed, I am a messenger from the Lord of the Worlds,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="112">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: "What knowledge do I have about their deeds?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Noah) said, "I have no knowledge of their deeds.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="14">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people, and he lived with them a thousand years minus fifty. Then they were caught by the deluge for they were evil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Indeed, We sent Noah to his people, and he tarried among them a thousand years, all but fifty; so the Flood seized them, while they were evildoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We sent Nuh unto his people. Then he tarried among them for a thousand years, save tifty years; and then deluge overtook them, while they were wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We sent Nuh (Noah) to his people, and he stayed among them a thousand years less fifty years [inviting them to believe in the Oneness of Allah (Monotheism), and discard the false gods and other deities], and the Deluge overtook them while they were Zalimun (wrong-doers, polytheists, disbelievers, etc.).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people, and He stayed among them for a thousand years minus fifty years. Then the Deluge swept them; for they were wrongdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We did indeed send Noah to his people and he lived among them a thousand years save fifty. Eventually the Flood overtook them while they were engaged in wrongdoing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed We sent Nuh to his people, and he stayed among them a thousand years less fifty years; so the Deluge overtook them while they were wrongdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And verily we sent Noah (as Our messenger) unto his folk, and he continued with them for a thousand years save fifty years; and the flood engulfed them, for they were wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We sent Noah to his people, and he remained with them for a thousand-less-fifty years. Then the flood overtook them while they were wrongdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Indeed, We sent Noah to his nation, and he lived amongst them for a thousand years, less fifty (but they belied him), then the Flood seized them while they were harmdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We certainly sent Noah to his people, and he remained among them a thousand years minus fifty years, and the flood seized them while they were wrongdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people and he lived with them for nine hundred and fifty years, then the flood engulfed them for their injustice.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We sent Nuh to his people, so he remained among them a thousand years save fifty years. And the deluge overtook them, while they were unjust.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We sent Noah to his people and he lived among them for fifty short of a thousand years; then the deluge overtook them, for they were wrongdoers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We (once) sent Noah to his people, and he tarried among them a thousand years less fifty: but the Deluge overwhelmed them while they (persisted in) sin.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="105">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>The people of Noah accused the apostles of lies.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>The people of Noah cried lies to the Envoys</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>The people of Nuh (Noah) belied the Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>The people of Noah disbelieved the messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>The people of Noah gave the lie to the Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>The people of Nuh denied the Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>The people of Noah impugned the apostles</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>The nation of Noah, belied their Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>The people of Noah denied the messengers</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The people of Noah rejected the Messengerss.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>The people of Nuh rejected the apostles.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>The people of Noah also rejected the messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>The people of Noah rejected the messengers.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="32">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>They said: "O Noah, you have argued with us, and disputed at length; so bring that (retribution) you promise, if you speak the truth."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>They said, 'Noah, thou hast disputed with us and make much disputation with us. Then bring us that thou promisest us, if thou speakest truly.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>They said: O Nuh! surely thou hast disputed with us and hath multiplied the disputation with us; now bring us that wherewith thou threatenest us, if thou be of the truth-tellers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They said: "O Nuh (Noah)! You have disputed with us and much have you prolonged the dispute with us, now bring upon us what you threaten us with, if you are of the truthful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>They said, “O Noah, you have argued with us, and argued a great deal. Now bring upon us what you threaten us with, if you are truthful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>They said: 'O Noah! Surely you have disputed with us and have prolonged your dispute. Now bring upon us the chastisement that you threaten us with; do so, if you are truthful.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They said: "O Nuh! You have disputed with us, and much have you prolonged the dispute with us, now bring upon us what you threaten us with, if you are of the truthful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>They said: O Noah! Thou hast disputed with us and multiplied disputation with us; now bring upon us that wherewith thou threatenest us, if thou art of the truthful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>They said, ‘O Noah, you have disputed with us already, and you have disputed with us exceedingly. Now bring us what you threaten us with, should you be truthful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>They said: 'O Noah, you have disputed, and disputed too much, with us. Bring (down) upon us that which you promised us, if what you say is true'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>They said, "O Noah, you have disputed us and been frequent in dispute of us. So bring us what you threaten us, if you should be of the truthful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They said, "Noah, you have argued with us a great deal. Bring down on us whatever torment with which you have been threatening us if what you say is true".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>They said: O Nuh! indeed you have disputed with us and lengthened dispute with us, therefore bring to us what you threaten us with, if you are of the truthful ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>"Noah," they replied, "you have argued with us, and argued to excess. Now bring down upon us what you threaten us with, if you speak the truth!?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They said: "O Noah! thou hast disputed with us, and (much) hast thou prolonged the dispute with us: now bring upon us what thou threatenest us with, if thou speakest the truth!?"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="9">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>The people of Noah had denied before them, and had called Our votary a liar, and said: "He is possessed," and repulsed him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>The people of Noah cried lies before them; they cried lies to Our servant, and said, 'A man possessed!' And he was rejected.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>There belied before them the people of Nuh. So they belied Our bondman Nuh and said: `a madman;' and moreover he was reproven.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>The people of Nuh (Noah) denied (their Messenger) before them, they rejected Our slave, and said: "A madman!" and he was insolently rebuked and threatened.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Before them the people of Noah disbelieved. They rejected Our servant, and said, “Crazy,” and he was rebuked.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>The people of Nuh denied (their Messenger) before them. They rejected Our servant and said: "A madman!" Wazdujir.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>The folk of Noah denied before them, yea, they denied Our slave and said: A madman; and he was repulsed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>The people of Noah impugned before them. So they impugned Our servant and said, ‘A crazy man,’ and he was reviled.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>(Long) before them the nation of Noah belied. They belied Our worshiper saying: 'Mad' and he was reprimanded.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>The people of Noah denied before them, and they denied Our servant and said, "A madman," and he was repelled.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The people of Noah, who lived before them, had also rejected (Our guidance). They rejected Our servant and said, "He is an insane person so let us drive him away".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Before them the people of Nuh rejected, so they rejected Our servant and called (him) mad, and he was driven away.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>The people of Noah denied [the truth] before them. They belied Our messenger saying, "He is mad!" He was rebuffed,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Before them the People of Noah rejected (their messenger): they rejected Our servant, and said, "Here is one possessed!", and he was driven out.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="116">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>They said: "If you do not desist, O Noah, you will be stoned to death."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>They said, 'If thou givest not over, Noah, thou shalt assuredly be one of the stoned.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They said: "If you cease not, O Nuh (Noah)! You will surely be among those stoned (to death)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>They said, “If you do not refrain, O Noah, you will be stoned.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>They said: "O Noah! If you do not desist, you will certainly become one of the accursed."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They said: "If you cease not, O Nuh you will surely be among those stoned."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>They said: If thou cease not, O Noah, thou wilt surely be among those stoned (to death).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>They said, ‘Noah, if you do not desist, you will certainly be stoned [to death].’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>'Noah' they replied, 'if you do not desist you shall be of those stoned'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>They said, "If you do not desist, O Noah, you will surely be of those who are stoned."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They said, "Noah, if you do not desist, you will, certainly, be stoned to death."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>They said: If you desist not, O Nuh, you shall most certainly be of those stoned to death.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They said, "Noah, if you do not desist, you will be stoned."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They said: "If thou desist not, O Noah! thou shalt be stoned (to death)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="71" verse="21">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>But they did not listen to me," Noah said, "and followed him whose wealth and children only added to his ruin.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Noah said, 'My Lord, they have rebelled against me, and followed him whose wealth and children increase him only in loss,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Nuh said. my Lord! verily they have disobeyed me and followed them whose riches and children have only increased them in loss.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Nuh (Noah) said: "My Lord! They have disobeyed me, and followed one whose wealth and children give him no increase but only loss.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Noah said, “My Lord, they have defied me, and followed him whose wealth and children increase him only in perdition.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: “My Lord, they did not pay heed to what I said, and followed those (nobles) whose possession of wealth and children has led them to an even greater loss.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Nuh said: "My Lord! They have disobeyed me, and followed one whose wealth and children give him no increase but loss."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Noah said: My Lord! Lo! they have disobeyed me and followed one whose wealth and children increase him in naught save ruin;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Noah said, ‘My Lord! They have disobeyed me, following someone whose wealth and children only add to his loss,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Noah said: 'My Lord, they have rebelled against me and followed he whose wealth and offspring increase him only in loss,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Noah said, "My Lord, indeed they have disobeyed me and followed him whose wealth and children will not increase him except in loss.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah said, "Lord, they have disobeyed me and followed those whose wealth and children will only bring about destruction for them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Nuh said: My Lord! surely they have disobeyed me and followed him whose wealth and children have added to him nothing but loss.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Noah supplicated, "Lord, they have disobeyed me, and followed those whose wealth and children have only added to their ruin;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Noah said: "O my Lord! They have disobeyed me, but they follow (men) whose wealth and children give them no increase but only Loss.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="71" verse="24">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.qaribullah</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And they have led many astray. (Noah supplicated saying): 'Allah, do not increase the harmdoers except in error'</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="66" verse="10">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.arberry</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>God has struck a similitude for the unbelievers -- the wife of Noah, and the wife of Lot; for they were under two of Our righteous servants, but they betrayed them, so they availed them nothing whatsoever against God; so it was said, 'Enter, you two, the Fire with those who enter.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Allah propoundeth for those who disbelieve the similitude of the wife of Nuh and the wife of Lut. They were under two of our righteous bondmen; then they defrauded them. Wherefore the twain availed them naught against Allah, and it was said: enter ye twain the Fire with those who enter.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Allah sets forth an example for those who disbelieve, the wife of Nuh (Noah) and the wife of Lout (Lot). They were under two of our righteous slaves, but they both betrayed their (husbands by rejecting their doctrine) so they [Nuh (Noah) and Lout (Lot)] benefited them (their respective wives) not, against Allah, and it was said: "Enter the Fire along with those who enter!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>God illustrates an example of those who disbelieve: the wife of Noah and the wife of Lot. They were under two of Our righteous servants, but they betrayed them. They availed them nothing against God, and it was said, “Enter the Fire with those who are entering.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Allah has set forth for the unbelievers the parable of the wives of Noah and Lot. They were wedded to two of Our righteous servants, but each acted treacherously with her husband, and their husbands could be of no avail to them against Allah. The two of them were told: “Enter the Fire with all the others who enter it.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Allah sets forth an example for those who disbelieve: the wife of Nuh and the wife of Lut. They were under two of our righteous servants, but they both betrayed them. So, they availed them not against Allah and it was said: "Enter the Fire along with those who enter!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Allah citeth an example for those who disbelieve: the wife of Noah and the wife of Lot, who were under two of Our righteous slaves yet betrayed them so that they (the husbands) availed them naught against Allah and it was said (unto them): Enter the Fire along with those who enter.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Allah cites an example of the faithless: the wife of Noah and the wife of Lot. They were under two of our righteous servants, yet they betrayed them. So they did not avail them in any way against Allah, and it was said [to them], ‘Enter the Fire, along with those who enter [it].’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Allah has given as an example for the unbelievers, the wife of Noah and the wife of Lot. They were married to two of Our righteous worshipers, but theybetrayed them. It was not for (Noah and Lot) to avail them a thing. It was said to them both: 'Enter the Fire with those who shall enter'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Allah presents an example of those who disbelieved: the wife of Noah and the wife of Lot. They were under two of Our righteous servants but betrayed them, so those prophets did not avail them from Allah at all, and it was said, "Enter the Fire with those who enter."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>God has told the disbelievers the story of the wives of Noah and Lot as a parable. They were married to two of Our righteous servants but were unfaithful to them. Nothing could protect them from the (wrath) of God and they were told to enter hell fire with the others.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Allah sets forth an example to those who disbelieve the wife of Nuh and the wife of Lut: they were both under two of Our righteous servants, but they acted treacherously towards them so they availed them naught against Allah, and it was said: Enter both the fire with those who enter.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>As an example to those who are bent on denying the truth, God cited the wife of Noah and the wife of Lot, who were married to two of Our righteous servants, but who betrayed them. So they could not help them against God, and they were told, "Enter the Fire along with all the others."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Allah sets forth, for an example to the Unbelievers, the wife of Noah and the wife of Lut: they were (respectively) under two of our righteous servants, but they were false to their (husbands), and they profited nothing before Allah on their account, but were told: "Enter ye the Fire along with (others) that enter!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="442">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
All the idols which were worshipped by the people of Noah were worshipped by the Arabs later on. As for the idol Wadd, it was worshipped by the tribe of Kalb at Daumat-al-Jandal; Suwa' was the idol of (the tribe of) Murad and then by Ban, Ghutaif at Al-Jurf near Saba; Yauq was the idol of Hamdan, and Nasr was the idol of Himyr, the branch of Dhi-al-Kala.' The names (of the idols) formerly belonged to some pious men of the people of Noah, and when they died Satan inspired their people to (prepare and place idols at the places where they used to sit, and to call those idols by their names. The people did so, but the idols were not worshipped till those people (who initiated them) had died and the origin of the idols had become obscure, whereupon people began worshipping them.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="10" verse="71">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Recount to them the story of Noah when he said to his people: "O people, if you find my staying with you and warning through God's signs, unbearable to you, know that I have reposed my trust in God. So plan your move, and call your associates, and make certain of your plan; then do whatever you intend against me, allowing me no respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And recite to them the story of Noah when he said to his people, 'My people, if my standing here is grievous to you and my reminding you of the signs of God, in God have I put my trust; so resolve on your affair, with your associates, then let not your affair be a worry to you, but make decision unto me, and respite me not.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And rehearse thou unto them the story of Nuh, when he said unto his people: O my people! if my standing forth and my admonishment with the commandments of Allah be hard upon you, then on Allah I rely; so devise your affair, ye and your associate-gods and let not your affair be dubious unto you, then have it decreed against me, and respite me not.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And recite to them the news of Nuh (Noah). When he said to his people: "O my people, if my stay (with you), and my reminding (you) of the Ayat (proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) of Allah is hard on you, then I put my trust in Allah. So devise your plot, you and your partners, and let not your plot be in doubt for you. Then pass your sentence on me and give me no respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And relate to them the story of Noah, when he said to his people, “O my people, if my presence among you and my reminding you of God’s signs is too much for you, then in God I have put my trust. So come to a decision, you and your partners, and do not let the matter perplex you; then carry out your decision on me, and do not hold back.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And narrate to them the story of Noah when he said to his people: 'My people! If my living in your midst and my effort to shake you out of heedlessness by reciting to you the revelations of Allah offend you, then remember that I have put all my trust in Allah. So draw up your plan in concert with those whom you associate with Allah in His divinity, leaving no part of it obscure, and then put it into effect against me, and give me no respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And recite to them the news of Nuh. When he said to his people: "O my people, if my stay (with you), and my reminding (you) of the Ayat of Allah is hard on you, then I put my trust in Allah. So devise your plot, you and your partners, and let not your plot be in confusion for you. Then pass your sentence on me and give me no respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Recite unto them the story of Noah, when he told his people: O my people! If my sojourn (here) and my reminding you by Allah's revelations are an offence unto you, in Allah have I put my trust, so decide upon your course of action you and your partners. Let not your course of action be in doubt for you. Then have at me, give me no respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Relate to them the account of Noah when he said to his people, ‘O my people! If my stay [among you] be hard on you and [also] my reminding you of Allah’s signs, [for my part] I have put my trust in Allah. So conspire together, along with your partners, leaving nothing vague in your plan, then carry it out against me without giving me any respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And recite to them the story of Noah. He said to his nation: 'O my nation, if my standing here, reminding you of the verses of Allah grieves you, and in Allah I have put my trust; decide upon your affair with your associates, then do not let your affair worry you. Come to a decision about me, and give me no respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And recite to them the news of Noah, when he said to his people, "O my people, if my residence and my reminding of the signs of Allah has become burdensome upon you - then I have relied upon Allah. So resolve upon your plan and [call upon] your associates. Then let not your plan be obscure to you. Then carry it out upon me and do not give me respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), tell them the story of Noah who told his people, "Even if my belief and my preaching of the revelation of God seem strange to you, I put my trust in Him. Unite yourselves and seek help from your idols. You should not regret what you want to do, but should execute your plans against me without delay</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And recite to them the story of Nuh when he said to his people: O my people! if my stay and my reminding (you) by the communications of Allah is hard on you-- yet on Allah do I rely-- then resolve upon your affair and (gather) your associates, then let not your affair remain dubious to you, then have it executed against me and give me no respite:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Tell them the story of Noah. He said to his people, "My people, if my presence among you and my preaching to you of God's revelations offends you, know that I put my trust in God, so agree on your course of action, along with your partner-gods, and let no hesitation deflect you from it, then put it into effect against me, and give me no respite.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Relate to them the story of Noah. Behold! he said to his people: "O my people, if it be hard on your (mind) that I should stay (with you) and commemorate the signs of Allah,- yet I put my trust in Allah. Get ye then an agreement about your plan and among your partners, so your plan be on to you dark and dubious. Then pass your sentence on me, and give me no respite.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="33">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: 'Only Allah will bring it upon you if He so wills, and you will be utterly unable to frustrate that.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Noah) replied, "God will bring torment down on you whenever He wants and you will not be able to make His (plans) fail.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="36">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And Noah was informed through revelation: "Apart from those who have come to believe already not one of your people is going to believe. So grieve not for what they are doing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And it was revealed to Noah, saying, 'None of thy people shall believe but he who has already believed; so be thou not distressed by that they may be doing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And it was revealed unto Nuh: verily none of thy people will believe save those that have believed already; so be not distressed for that which they have been doing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And it was inspired to Nuh (Noah): "None of your people will believe except those who have believed already. So be not sad because of what they used to do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And it was revealed to Noah: “None of your people will believe, except those who have already believed, so do not grieve over what they do.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>It was revealed to Noah that no more of your people, other than those who already believe, will ever come to believe. So do not grieve over their deeds,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And it was revealed to Nuh: "None of your people will believe except those who have believed already. So be not sad because of what they used to do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And it was inspired in Noah, (saying): No-one of thy folk will believe save him who hath believed already. Be not distressed because of what they do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>It was revealed to Noah: ‘None of your people will believe except those who already have faith; so do not sorrow for what they used to do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And it was revealed to Noah: 'None of your nation will believe except whosoever has already believed. Do not distress yourself with what they may do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And it was revealed to Noah that, "No one will believe from your people except those who have already believed, so do not be distressed by what they have been doing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>It was revealed to Noah that besides those who had already accepted his faith, no one from his people would ever believe him. He was told not to be disappointed about what his people had done,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And it was revealed to Nuh: That none of your people will believe except those who have already believed, therefore do not grieve at what they do:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>God's will was revealed to Noah, "No more of your people will believe in you than those who already believe; do not grieve, therefore, over what they have been doing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>It was revealed to Noah: "None of thy people will believe except those who have believed already! So grieve no longer over their (evil) deeds.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="26">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"O my Lord," prayed (Noah), "help me against them, for they accuse me of lies."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Nuh said: my Lord! vindicate me, for they belie me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>[Nuh (Noah)] said: "O my Lord! Help me because they deny me."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: "My Lord! Come to my help at their accusation that I am lying."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He (Noah) said: 'Lord, help me, for they belie me'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[Noah] said, "My Lord, support me because they have denied me."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah prayed, "Lord, help me; they have called me a liar".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Noah said, "My Lord, help me! for they have rejected me,"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(Noah) said: "O my Lord! help me: for that they accuse me of falsehood!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="10">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah prayed, "Lord, help me; I am defeated".</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="117">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Then Noah said, "Lord, my people have rejected me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Noah said, "My Lord, my people have rejected me,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="71" verse="26">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Noah said: "O Lord, do not leave a single habitation of unbelievers on the earth.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Noah said, 'My Lord, leave not upon the earth of the unbelievers even one.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Nuh said: my Lord! leave not upon the earth of the infidels one inhabitant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And Nuh (Noah) said: "My Lord! Leave not one of the disbelievers on the earth!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Noah said, “My Lord, do not leave of the unbelievers a single dweller on earth.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: “My Lord, do not leave out of these unbelievers even a single dweller on earth,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And Nuh said: "My Lord! Leave not one of the disbelievers on the earth Dayyar!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Noah said: My Lord! Leave not one of the disbelievers in the land.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And Noah said, ‘My Lord! ‘Do not leave on the earth any inhabitant from among the faithless.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And Noah (supplicated) saying: 'My Lord, do not leave a single unbeliever upon the earth.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Noah said, "My Lord, do not leave upon the earth from among the disbelievers an inhabitant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah said, "Lord, do not leave a single disbeliever on earth;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Nuh said: My Lord! leave not upon the land any dweller from among the unbelievers:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Noah prayed, "O my Lord! Do not leave on earth a single one of those who deny the truth --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And Noah, said: "O my Lord! Leave not of the Unbelievers, a single one on earth!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="37">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Build an ark under Our eye and as We instruct. Do not plead for those who have been wicked, for they shall certainly be drowned."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Make thou the Ark under Our eyes, and as We reveal; and address Me not concerning those who have done evil; they shall be drowned.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And make thou the ark under Our eyes and Our Revelation; and address Me not regarding those that have done wrong; verily they are to be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“And build the Ark, under Our eyes, and with Our inspiration, and do not address Me regarding those who did wrong; they are to be drowned.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and build the Ark under Our eyes and Our direction. And do not supplicate Me concerning those who have engaged in wrong-doing. They are doomed to be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Build the ark before Our eyes and by Our revelation, and do not plead with Me for those who are wrongdoers: they shall indeed be drowned.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Build the Ark with Our seeing (and protection), and as We reveal. Do not speak to Me concerning the evildoers; they shall be drowned'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>but to build the Ark under the supervision and guidance of his Lord. He was also told not to address any words to Him concerning the unjust for they were all to be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And make the ark before Our eyes and (according to) Our revelation, and do not speak to Me in respect of those who are unjust; surely they shall be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Build the Ark under Our eyes and in accordance with Our revelation. Do not plead with Me concerning the evil-doers. They shall certainly be drowned."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"But construct an Ark under Our eyes and Our inspiration, and address Me no (further) on behalf of those who are in sin: for they are about to be overwhelmed (in the Flood)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="38">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So he built the ark; and when groups of his people passed by him, they scoffed at him. He said to them: "Though you laugh at us (now), we shall laugh at you, as you are laughing at us.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So he was making the Ark; and whenever a council of his people passed by him they scoffed at him, He said, 'If you scoff at us, we shall surely scoff at you, as you scoff</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And he was making the ark; and whenever the chiefs of his people passed by him, they scoffed at him. He said: if ye scoff at us, verily we also scoff at you even as ye scoff at us.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>As he was building the ark, whenever some of his people passed by him, they ridiculed him. He said, “If you ridicule us, we will ridicule you, just as you ridicule.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>As Noah was building the Ark, whenever the leading men of his nation passed by him, they would scoff at him. He said: 'If you scoff at us, we too scoff at you in like manner.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>As he was building the ark, whenever the elders of his people passed by him, they would ridicule him. He said, ‘If you ridicule us [today], we shall ridicule you [tomorrow] just as you ridicule us [now].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Whenever an assembly of his nation passed by him as he was building the Ark, they mocked him. Whereupon he said: 'If you mock us, we shall indeedmock you, just as you mock.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Noah) started to build the Ark but whenever some of his people passed by, they would mock him. He in return would reply, "Mock us, but just as you mock us, we, too, will mock you.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And he began to make the ark; and whenever the chiefs from among his people passed by him they laughed at him. He said: If you laugh at us, surely we too laugh at you as you laugh (at us).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>So he began to build the Ark, and whenever leaders of his people passed by, they scoffed at him. He said, "If you are scoffing at us, we shall scoff at you [and your ignorance], just as you scoff at us:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Forthwith he (starts) constructing the Ark: Every time that the chiefs of his people passed by him, they threw ridicule on him. He said: "If ye ridicule us now, we (in our turn) can look down on you with ridicule likewise!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="27">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We asked him to build the ark under Our eyes and guidance, (and said): "When Our command is issued and the source of water boils over, put a pair of every species in it, and your family except those for whom Our sentence has been passed already; and do not speak to Me for those who are wicked: They will be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Then We said to him, 'Make thou the Ark under Our eyes and as We reveal, and then, when Our command comes and the Oven boils, insert in it two of every kind and thy, family -- except for him against whom the word already has been spoken; and address Me not concerning those who have done evil; they shall be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then We revealed unto him, saying: build the ark under Our eyes and Our Revelation; then when Our command cometh and the oven boileth over, make way therein of every pair two, and thy household save him thereof against whom there hath already gone forth the word; and address me not in respect of those who have done wrong; verily they are to be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>So We inspired him: “Build the Ark under Our observation and by Our inspiration. And when Our decree comes to pass, and the oven boils over, load into it two pairs of every kind, together with your family, except those of them against whom the word has already been pronounced. And do not speak to me concerning those who did wrong; for they are to be drowned.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Thereupon We revealed to him, saying: "Build the Ark under Our eyes and according to Our revelation. And when Our command comes to pass and the oven boils over, take on board a pair each from every species, and also take your household except those of them against whom sentence has already been passed and do not plead to Me on behalf of the wrong-doers. They are doomed to be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>So We revealed to him: ‘Build the ark before Our eyes and by Our revelation. When Our edict comes and the oven gushes [a stream of water], bring into it a pair of every kind [of animal], and your family, except those of them against whom the decree has gone beforehand, and do not plead with Me for those who are wrongdoers: they shall indeed be drowned.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We said to him: 'Make the Ark under Our Eye, and Our Revelation, and then when Our command comes and the oven gushes water, take onboard a pair from every kind and your family, except him against whom the decision has already been passed. Do not address Me concerning those who have done evil; they shall be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We inspired him, saying, "Build the Ark before Our eyes and by the instruction of Our revelation. When our decree comes to pass and water comes forth from the Oven, embark in the Ark with a pair of every kind of animals and your family except those already doomed (to perish). Do not plead with Me for the unjust; they will be drowned."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So We revealed to him, saying: Make the ark before Our eyes and (according to) Our revelation; and when Our command is given and the valley overflows, take into it of every kind a pair, two, and your followers, except those among them against whom the word has gone forth, and do not speak to Me in respect of those who are unjust; surely they shall be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>then We revealed Our will to him: "Build the Ark under Our watchful eye according to Our instructions. When Our command comes, and waters gush up out of the earth, take on board pairs of every species and members of your household, except for any of them on whom sentence has already been passed -- do not plead with Me for those who have done wrong: they shall be drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So We inspired him (with this message): "Construct the Ark within Our sight and under Our guidance: then when comes Our Command, and the fountains of the earth gush forth, take thou on board pairs of every species, male and female, and thy family- except those of them against whom the Word has already gone forth: And address Me not in favour of the wrong-doers; for they shall be drowned (in the Flood).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="40">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When Our command was issued and the waters gushed forth from the source, We said: "Take into (the ark) a pair of every species, and members of your family other than those against whom the sentence has been passed already, and those who come to believe." But only a few believed in him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Thus it was until Our command came to pass and the oven boiled over. We said: 'Take into the Ark a pair of every species; and take your own family except those who have already been declared (as unworthy); and also take everyone who believes. But those who, along with him, had believed were indeed just a few.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when Our command came and the oven gushed (forth with water), We said (to Noah): 'Take on board (the Ark) a pair from every species and yourfamily, except he of whom the word has already been spoken, and those who believe. And none except a few believed with him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When at last Our decree was fulfilled, water gushed forth from the Oven (in Noah's house). We told him to carry in the Ark a pair (male and female) from every species, his family - except those who were destined to perish - and the believers. No one believed in him, except a few.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When Our command came, and water gushed forth in torrents, We said to Noah, "Take into the Ark a pair from every species, and your own family -- except those on whom the sentence has already been passed, and all the true believers." But only a few believed along with him.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="41">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And (Noah) said: "Embark. In the name of God be its course and mooring. My Lord is surely forgiving and kind."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And he [Nuh (Noah)] said: "Embark therein, in the Name of Allah will be its moving course and its resting anchorage. Surely, my Lord is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful." (Tafsir At-Tabari, Vol. 12, Page 43)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: ' Embark in it. In the name of Allah is its sailing and its anchorage. My Lord is Ever Forgiving, Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He (Noah) said: 'Embark. In the Name of Allah will be its course and berthing. Indeed, my Lord is Forgiving, the Most Merciful'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [Noah] said, "Embark therein; in the name of Allah is its course and its anchorage. Indeed, my Lord is Forgiving and Merciful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Noah) said, "Embark in it. It will sail in the name of God, in His Name it will sail and in His Name it will cast anchor. My Lord is All-forgiving and All-merciful".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Noah said, "Embark on it. In the name of God, it shall set sail and cast anchor. Truly, my Lord is forgiving and merciful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So he said: "Embark ye on the Ark, In the name of Allah, whether it move or be at rest! For my Lord is, be sure, Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="28">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When you and those with you have boarded the ark, say: 'All praise be to God who has delivered us from the people who were sinful.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Then, when thou art seated in the Ark and those with thee, say, "Praise belongs to God, who has delivered us from the people of the evildoers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And when thou art settled, thou and those with thee, in the ark, say thou: praise unto Allah who hath delivered us from the wrong doing people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then, when you and those with you are settled in the Ark, say, “Praise be to God, who has saved us from the wrongdoing people.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And then when you and those accompanying you are firmly seated in the Ark, say: "Thanks be to Allah Who has delivered us from the wrong-doing people."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>‘When you, and those who are with you, are settled in the ark, say, ‘‘All praise belongs to Allah, who has delivered us from the wrongdoing lot.’’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when you and all those with you are seated in the Ark, say: 'Praise be to Allah who has saved us from the harmdoing nation'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When all of you settle in the Ark, say, "Only God Who has saved us from the unjust people deserves all praise".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And when you are firmly seated, you and those with you, in the ark, say: All praise is due to Allah who delivered us from the unjust people:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When you and all your followers have settled in the Ark, say, "Praise be to God who has delivered us from a wicked people,"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And when thou hast embarked on the Ark - thou and those with thee,- say: "Praise be to Allah, Who has saved us from the people who do wrong."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="42">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>It sailed on waves like mountains (high), and Noah called to his son who was separated from him: "Embark with us, O my son, and be not one of those who do not believe."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So it ran with them amid waves like mountains; and Noah called to his son, who was standing apart, 'Embark with us, my son, and be thou not with the unbelievers!'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And it moved on with them amidst waves like mountains. And Nuh called out his son, and he was apart: O my son! embark with us, and be not with the infidels.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So it (the ship) sailed with them amidst the waves like mountains, and Nuh (Noah) called out to his son, who had separated himself (apart), "O my son! Embark with us and be not with the disbelievers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And so it sailed with them amidst waves like hills. And Noah called to his son, who had kept away, “On my son! Embark with us, and do not be with the disbelievers.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>The Ark sailed along with them amid mountain-like waves. Noah, spotting his son at a distance, called out to him: 'My son. embark with us. and do not be with the unbelievers.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So it (the ship) sailed with them amidst waves like mountains, and Nuh called out to his son, who had separated himself (apart): "O my son! Embark with us and be not with the disbelievers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And it sailed with them amid waves like mountains, and Noah cried unto his son - and he was standing aloof - O my son! Come ride with us, and be not with the disbelievers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And it sailed along with them amid waves [rising] like mountains. Noah called out to his son, who stood aloof, ‘O my son! ‘Board with us, and do not be with the faithless!’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And so it (the Ark) ran with them amidst the mountainous waves, and Noah cried out to his son, who was standing apart, 'Embark with us, my son, do not be with the unbelievers'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And it sailed with them through waves like mountains, and Noah called to his son who was apart [from them], "O my son, come aboard with us and be not with the disbelievers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When the Ark sailed on with them amid the mountainous waves, Noah called out to his son who kept away from them, "My son, embark with us. Do not stay with the unbelievers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And it moved on with them amid waves like mountains; and Nuh called out to his son, and he was aloof: O my son! embark with us and be not with the unbelievers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>The Ark sailed along with them through mountainous waves. Noah called out to his son who stood apart, "O my son! Embark with us and do not be among the deniers!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So the Ark floated with them on the waves (towering) like mountains, and Noah called out to his son, who had separated himself (from the rest): "O my son! embark with us, and be not with the unbelievers!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="43">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"I shall go up a mountain," he said, "which will keep me from the water." "There is no getting away," said Noah, "from the decree of God today, except for those on whom be His mercy." And a wave came between them, and he was among those who were drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He said: I shall betake me to a mountain which will defend me from the water. Nuh said: there is no defender to-day from the decree of Allah save for one on whom He hath mercy. And a wave intervened betwixt the twain; so he was of the drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>The son replied: "I will betake myself to a mountain, it will save me from the water." Nuh (Noah) said: "This day there is no saviourfrom the Decree of Allah except him on whom He has mercy." And a wave came in between them, so he (the son) was among the drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>The son replied: 'I will go to a mountain for refuge and it will save me from the water.' Noah said: 'None can save anyone today from the command of Allah except those on whom He may have mercy.' Thereupon a wave swept in between the two and he was drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>The son replied: "I will betake myself to some mountain, it will save me from the water." Nuh said: "This day there is no savior from the decree of Allah except him on whom He has mercy." And waves came in between them, so he (the son) was among the drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He said: I shall betake me to some mountain that will save me from the water. (Noah) said: This day there is none that saveth from the commandment of Allah save him on whom He hath had mercy. And the wave came in between them, so he was among the drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But he replied: 'I shall seek refuge on a mountain, which will protect me from the water' He (Noah) said: 'Today, there is no defender from the command of Allah, except those to whom He has mercy' And the waves came between them, and he was drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[But] he said, "I will take refuge on a mountain to protect me from the water." [Noah] said, "There is no protector today from the decree of Allah, except for whom He gives mercy." And the waves came between them, and he was among the drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>His son replied, "I shall climb up a mountain and this will save me from the flood." Noah said, "No one can escape on this day from God's command except those on whom He has mercy." The waves separated Noah from his son who was then drowned with the rest (of the unbelievers).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: I will betake myself for refuge to a mountain that shall protect me from the water. Nuh said: There is no protector today from Allah's punishment but He Who has mercy; and a wave intervened between them, so he was of the drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>He replied, "I shall seek refuge on a mountain, which will save me from the water." Noah cried, "Today there is no refuge for anyone from God's command except for those to whom He shows mercy!" Thereupon, a wave swept in between them, and Noah's son was among those who were drowned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>The son replied: "I will betake myself to some mountain: it will save me from the water." Noah said: "This day nothing can save, from the command of Allah, any but those on whom He hath mercy! "And the waves came between them, and the son was among those overwhelmed in the Flood.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="13">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We bore Noah on the vessel built of planks and nails,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We carried him, (Noah), on a vessel built with boards fixed together with nails,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We bore him on an [ark] which, made of planks and nails,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>But We bore him on an (Ark) made of broad planks and caulked with palm-fibre:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="69" verse="11">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When the water rose in flood, We bore you in the ark,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We! when the water rose, We bare you upon the traversing ark.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily! When the water rose beyond its limits [Nuh's (Noah) Flood], We carried you (mankind) in the floating [ship that was constructed by Nuh (Noah)].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Verily when the water rose to great heights, We bore you upon a floating vessel (i.e. the Ark)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Indeed when the Flood rose high, We carried you in a floating ark,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when the waters rose (high) We carried you in the sailing (Ark),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When the flood rose high and covered the whole land, We carried you in the Ark.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>But We bore you away in the Ark, when the waters rose high,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We, when the water (of Noah's Flood) overflowed beyond its limits, carried you (mankind), in the floating (Ark),</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="36" verse="41">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>That We bore their progeny in the laden ark is a sign for them;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And an Ayah (sign) for them is that We bore their offspring in the laden ship [of Nuh (Noah)].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Another sign for them is that We carried their offspring in the laden Ark.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And a sign for them is that We carried their offspring in the laden Ark (of Noah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>how We carried them and their offspring inside the laden Ark</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Another sign for them is that We carried their offspring in the laden Ark.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And a Sign for them is that We bore their race (through the Flood) in the loaded Ark;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="44">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Then it was said: "O earth, swallow back your water; and, O sky, desist." And the water subsided, and the decree was accomplished. The ark came to rest on Judi (Mount Ararat), and it was said: "Away with the cursed people!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And it was said, 'Earth, swallow thy waters; and, heaven, abate!' And the waters subsided, the affair was accomplished, and the Ark settled on El-Judi, and it was said: 'Away with the people of the evildoers!'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And it was said: "O earth! Swallow up your water, and O sky! Withhold (your rain)." And the water was diminished (made to subside) and the Decree (of Allah) was fulfilled (i.e. the destruction of the people of Nuh (Noah). And it (the ship) rested on Mount Judi, and it was said: "Away with the people who are Zalimun (polytheists and wrong-doing)!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And the command was given: 'Earth! Swallow up your water'; and: 'Heaven! Abate!' So the water subsided, the command was fulfilled, and the Ark settled on Mount Judi, and it was said: 'Away with the wrong-doing folk!'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And it was said: 'Earth, swallow up your waters. Heaven, cease' The water subsided and the matter was accomplished. And the Ark came to rest upon (the mountain of) AlJudi, and it was said: 'Be gone, evildoing nation'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Then the earth was told to swallow-up its water and the sky was ordered to stop raining. The water abated and God's command had been fulfilled. The Ark came to rest on Mount Judi. A voice said, "The unjust people are far away from the mercy of God."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And it was said: O earth, swallow down your water, and O cloud, clear away; and the water was made to abate and the affair was decided, and the ark rested on the Judi, and it was said: Away with the unjust people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>A voice cried out, "Earth, swallow up your waters. O sky, cease your rain." The waters receded. The command was fulfilled. The Ark came to rest on Mount Judi. It was said, "Away with the wrong-doing people."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Then the word went forth: "O earth! swallow up thy water, and O sky! Withhold (thy rain)!" and the water abated, and the matter was ended. The Ark rested on Mount Judi, and the word went forth: "Away with those who do wrong!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="29">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Say, "Lord, grant us a blessed landing from the Ark; You are the One who provides the safest landing".</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="48">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(And the Lord) said: "O Noah, disembark with peace and safety from Us and blessings on you and the people with you. As for some (of them), We shall bestow advantages for a time, then send a grievous punishment on them."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>It was said, 'Noah, get thee down in peace from Us, and blessings upon thee and on the nations of those with thee; and nations -- We shall give them enjoyment, then there shall visit them from Us a painful chastisement.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>It was said: Nuh! get thou down with peace from us and blessings upon thee and the communities with thee. And there shall be communities whom we shall let enjoy themselves, and thereafter there shall befall them from us a torment afflictive.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>It was said: "O Nuh (Noah)! Come down (from the ship) with peace from Us and blessings on you and on the people who are with you (and on some of their off spring), but (there will be other) people to whom We shall grant their pleasures (for a time), but in the end a painful torment will reach them from Us."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>It was said, “O Noah, disembark with peace from Us; and with blessings upon you, and upon communities from those with you. And other communities We will grant prosperity, and then a painful torment from Us will befall them.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>It was said: 'Noah! Disembark, with Our peace, and with blessings upon you and upon those who are with you. There are also people whom We shall allow to enjoy themselves for a while, and then a painful chastisement from Us shall afflict them.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>It was said: "O Nuh! Come down (from the ship) with peace from Us and blessings on you and on the people who are with you (and on some of their offspring), but (there will be other) people to whom We shall grant their pleasures (for a time), but in the end a painful torment will reach them from Us."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>It was said (unto him): O Noah! Go thou down (from the mountain) with peace from Us and blessings upon thee and some nations (that will spring) from those with thee. (There will be other) nations unto whom We shall give enjoyment a long while and then a painful doom from Us will overtake them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>It was said, ‘O Noah! Disembark in peace from Us and with [Our] blessings upon you and upon nations [to descend] from those who are with you, and nations whom We shall provide for, then a painful punishment from Us shall befall them.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>It was said: 'O Noah, descend with peace from Us and blessings on you and on the nations of those with you; and nations We shall give them enjoyment, and then from Us they shall be visited with a painful punishment'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>It was said, "O Noah, disembark in security from Us and blessings upon you and upon nations [descending] from those with you. But other nations [of them] We will grant enjoyment; then there will touch them from Us a painful punishment."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah was told, "Get down from the Ark. Your Lord's peace and blessings are upon you and your followers. Your Lord will grant favors to other nations and then afflict them with a painful torment."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>It was said: O Nuh! descend with peace from Us and blessings on you and on the people from among those who are with you, and there shall be nations whom We will afford provisions, then a painful punishment from Us shall afflict them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>God said, "Noah, go ashore in peace; Our blessings upon you and upon the people who are with you and upon some of the descendants of those who are with you. [As for the unrighteous] We shall grant provision for a time, then a grievous punishment from Us shall afflict them."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>The word came: "O Noah! Come down (from the Ark) with peace from Us, and blessing on thee and on some of the peoples (who will spring) from those with thee: but (there will be other) peoples to whom We shall grant their pleasures (for a time), but in the end will a grievous penalty reach them from Us."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="45">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Noah called on his Lord and said: "O Lord, my son is surely a member of my family, and verily Your promise is true, as You are the most just of all judges."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Noah called unto his Lord, and said, 'O my Lord, my son is of my family, and Thy promise is surely the truth. Thou art the justest of those that judge.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Nuh cried unto his Lord, and said: my Lord! verily my son is of my household, and verily Thine promise is the truth: and Thou art the Greatest of the rulers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And Nuh (Noah) called upon his Lord and said, "O my Lord! Verily, my son is of my family! And certainly, Your Promise is true, and You are the Most Just of the judges."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Noah called to his Lord. He said, “O My Lord, my son is of my family, and Your promise is true, and You are the Wisest of the wise.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And Noah called out to his Lord, saying: 'My Lord! My son is of my family. Surely Your promise is true, and You are the greatest of those who judge.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And Nuh called upon his Lord and said, "O my Lord! Verily, my son is of my family! And certainly, Your promise is true, and You are the Most Just of the judges."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Noah cried unto his Lord and said: My Lord! Lo! my son is of my household! Surely Thy promise is the truth and Thou are the Most Just of Judges.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Noah called out to his Lord, and said, ‘My Lord! My son is indeed from my family. Your promise is indeed true, and You are the fairest of all judges.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Noah called out to his Lord, saying: 'O Lord, my son was of my family, and Your promise is surely the truth. You are the most Just of judges'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Noah called to his Lord and said, "My Lord, indeed my son is of my family; and indeed, Your promise is true; and You are the most just of judges!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah prayed to his Lord saying, "Lord, my son is a member of my family. Your promise is always true and you are the best Judge".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Nuh cried out to his Lord and said: My Lord! surely my son is of my family, and Thy promise is surely true, and Thou art the most just of the judges.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Noah called out to his Lord, saying, "My Lord, my son was a part of my family. Your promise was surely true. You are the most just of all judges."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And Noah called upon his Lord, and said: "O my Lord! surely my son is of my family! and Thy promise is true, and Thou art the justest of Judges!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="46">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"O Noah", He answered, "truly he is not of your family. He is surely the outcome of an unrighteous act. So ask Me not of what you do not know. I warn you not to be one of the ignorant."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Said He, 'Noah, he is not of thy family; it is a deed not righteous. Do not ask of Me that whereof thou hast no knowledge. I admonish thee, lest thou shouldst be among the ignorant.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He said: O Nuh! verily he is not of thy household; verily he is of unrighteous Conduct; wherefore ask Me not that whereof thou hast no knowledge; verily I exhort thee not to be of the ignorants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He said: "O Nuh (Noah)! Surely, he is not of your family; verily, his work is unrighteous, so ask not of Me that of which you have no knowledge! I admonish you, lest you be one of the ignorants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “O Noah, he is not of your family. It is an unrighteous deed. So do not ask Me about something you know nothing about. I admonish you, lest you be one of the ignorant.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>In response Noah was told: 'Most certainly he is not of your family; verily he is of unrighteous conduct. So do not ask of Me for that concerning which you have no knowledge. I admonish you never to act like the ignorant ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He said: "O Nuh! Surely, he is not of your family; verily, his work is unrighteous, so ask not of Me that of which you have no knowledge! I admonish you, lest you should be one of the ignorant."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He said: O Noah! Lo! he is not of thy household; lo! he is of evil conduct, so ask not of Me that whereof thou hast no knowledge. I admonish thee lest thou be among the ignorant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Said He, ‘O Noah! Indeed, He is not of your family. Indeed, he is [personification of] unrighteous conduct. So do not ask Me [something] of which you have no knowledge. I advise you lest you should be among the ignorant.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He said: 'Noah, he is not of your family. It is not a good deed. Do not ask Me about things of which you have no knowledge. I reproach you lest you become among the ignorant'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>He said, "O Noah, indeed he is not of your family; indeed, he is [one whose] work was other than righteous, so ask Me not for that about which you have no knowledge. Indeed, I advise you, lest you be among the ignorant."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: O Nuh! surely he is not of your family; surely he is (the doer of) other than good deeds, therefore ask not of Me that of which you have no knowledge; surely I admonish you lest you may be of the ignorant</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>God said, "Noah, he was not one of your family. For, indeed, he was unrighteous in his conduct. Do not question Me about something of which you have no knowledge; I admonish you lest you become like an ignorant man."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He said: "O Noah! He is not of thy family: For his conduct is unrighteous. So ask not of Me that of which thou hast no knowledge! I give thee counsel, lest thou act like the ignorant!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="47">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"Preserve me, O Lord," said (Noah), "from asking You that of which I have no knowledge. If You do not forgive me and have mercy on me I shall be among those who perish."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Nuh said: my Lord! verily take refuge with Thee lest I may ask Thee that whereof I have no knowledge. And if Thou forgivest me not and hast not mercy on me, I shall be of the losers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Nuh (Noah) said: "O my Lord! I seek refuge with You from asking You that of which I have no knowledge. And unless You forgive me and have Mercy on me, I would indeed be one of the losers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah said: 'My Lord! I take refuge with You that I should ask you for that concerning which I have no knowledge. And if You do not forgive me and do not show mercy to me, I shall be among the losers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Nuh said: "O my Lord! I seek refuge with You from asking You that of which I have no knowledge. And unless You forgive me and have mercy on me, I would indeed be one of the losers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[Noah] said, "My Lord, I seek refuge in You from asking that of which I have no knowledge. And unless You forgive me and have mercy upon me, I will be among the losers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah said, "Lord, I ask You to prevent me from asking You ignorant questions and beg you for pardon and mercy or else I shall certainly be lost".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Noah said: "O my Lord! I do seek refuge with Thee, lest I ask Thee for that of which I have no knowledge. And unless thou forgive me and have Mercy on me, I should indeed be lost!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="64">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>But they called him a liar, and We saved him and those with him in the Ark, and drowned the others who rejected Our signs, for they were a people purblind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>But they cried him lies; so We delivered him, and those with him, in the Ark, and We drowned those who cried lies to Our signs; assuredly they were a blind people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then they belied him; there upon We delivered him and those with him in the ark, and drowned those who belied Our signs; verily they were a people blind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>But they called him a liar. So We saved him and those with him in the Ark, and We drowned those who rejected Our revelations. They were blind people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>But they charged him with falsehood. Thereupon We delivered Noah and those who were with him in the Ark, and caused those who rejected Our signs as false to be drowned. Surely they were a blind folk.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>But they denied him. So We delivered him and those who were with him in the ark, and We drowned those who denied Our signs. Indeed, they were a blind lot.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>(But) they belied him, so We saved him and those who were with him in the Ark, and We drowned those who belied Our verses. Surely, they were a blind nation.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They accused him of telling lies. So We saved him and his companions in an ark and drowned those who called Our revelations mere lies. They were, no doubt, a blind people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>But they called him a liar, so We delivered him and those with him in the ark, and We drowned those who rejected Our communications; surely they were a blind people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>But they denied him, so We saved him and those with him in the Ark, and We drowned those who rejected Our signs. They were indeed a blind people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>But they rejected him, and We delivered him, and those with him, in the Ark: but We overwhelmed in the flood those who rejected Our signs. They were indeed a blind people!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="10" verse="73">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Even then they denied him; so We saved him and those with him, in the ark, and established them in the land, and drowned those who denied Our signs. So think of the fate of those who were warned (and took no heed).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>But they cried him lies; so We delivered him, and those with him, in the Ark, and We appointed them as viceroys, and We drowned those who cried lies to Our signs; then behold how was the end of them that were warned!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>So they belied him; then We delivered him and those with him in the ark, and We made them successors, while We drowned those who belied Our signs. Behold then what like hath been the end of those who were warned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>But they denounced him, so We saved him and those with him in the Ark, and We made them successors, and We drowned those who rejected Our signs. So consider the fate of those who were warned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>But they rejected Noah, calling him a liar. So We saved him and those who were with him in the Ark, and made them successors (to the authority in the land), and drowned all those who had rejected Our signs as false. Consider, then, the fate of those who had been warned (and still did not believe).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>But they impugned him. So We delivered him and those who were with him in the ark and We made them the successors, and We drowned those who denied Our signs. So observe how was the fate of those who were warned!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But they belied him. Therefore We saved him and those who were with him in the Ark, and We made them caliphs, and We drowned those who belied Our verses. See what was the end of those who were warned!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They rejected Noah. Then We saved him and his people in the Ark to make them the successors of the rest. The others, who had called Our revelations lies, were drowned. Consider the fate of those who (rejected) Our warnings!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>But they rejected him, so We delivered him and those with him in the ark, and We made them rulers and drowned those who rejected Our communications; see then what was the end of the (people) warned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Then they rejected him; then We delivered him and those with him in the Ark, and We made them successors; while We drowned the others who belied Our signs. Observe then the fate of those who had been forewarned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They rejected Him, but We delivered him, and those with him, in the Ark, and We made them inherit (the earth), while We overwhelmed in the flood those who rejected Our Signs. Then see what was the end of those who were warned (but heeded not)!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="26" verse="119">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We delivered him and those with him in the loaded ark,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Wherefore We delivered him and those with him in the laden ark.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>So We delivered him and those with him in the laden Ark.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Thereafter We rescued him and those who were with him in the laden Ark</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Thereupon We delivered him and those who were with him in the laden ark.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We saved him and those who were with him in a fully laden Ark,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So We delivered him and those with him in the laden ark.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>So We saved him, and those who were with him in the laden ark,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So We delivered him and those with him, in the Ark filled (with all creatures).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="15">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>But We saved him and those with him in the ark, and made it a sign for the creatures of the world.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then We delivered him and those in the ark, and made it a sign unto the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>But We saved him, together with the company of the Ark, and We made it a sign for all peoples.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Then We rescued Noah together with the people in the Ark and made it (that is, the Ark) a lesson for all people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Then We delivered him and those who were in the Ark, and made it a sign for all the nations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But We saved him and all who were in the Ark, and made (the event) a sign to the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We saved Noah and the people in the Ark and made (their case) a miracle for the world.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So We delivered him and the inmates of the ark, and made it a sign to the nations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>But We saved him and those who were with him in the Ark and made the event a sign for mankind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>But We saved him and the companions of the Ark, and We made the (Ark) a Sign for all peoples!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="76">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Remember Noah when he called to Us before this. We heard him and saved him and those with him from great distress;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Noah -- when he called before, and We answered him, and delivered him and his people from the great distress,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Nuh! recall what time he cried aforetime; so we answered him and delivered him and his house hold from a calamity mighty.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) Nuh (Noah), when he cried (to Us) aforetime. We listened to his invocation and saved him and his family from great distress.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Noah, when he called before. So We answered him, and delivered him and his family from the great disaster.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We bestowed the same favour upon Noah. Recall, when he cried to Us before; We accepted his prayer and delivered him and his household from the great distress</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) Nuh, when he cried (to Us) aforetime. We answered to his invocation and saved him and his family from the great distress.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Noah, when he cried of old, We heard his prayer and saved him and his household from the great affliction.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And before that Noah, when he called out, We responded to him and delivered him and his family from the great agony.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And (remember) Noah, when he supplicated to Us, We answered him, and We saved him and his nation from great distress,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] Noah, when he called [to Allah] before [that time], so We responded to him and saved him and his family from the great flood.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We answered the prayer of Noah who had prayed to Us before and saved him and his followers from the great disaster.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Nuh, when he cried aforetime, so We answered him, and delivered him and his followers from the great calamity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Before him Noah cried out to Us, and We heard his prayer. We saved him and all his household from a great distress.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(Remember) Noah, when he cried (to Us) aforetime: We listened to his (prayer) and delivered him and his family from great distress.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="25" verse="37">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We had drowned the people of Noah when they had accused the apostles of lies, and turned them into an example for men. We have prepared a painful punishment for the wicked.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And the people of Noah, when they cried lies to the Messengers, We drowned them, and made them to be a sign to mankind; and We have prepared for the evildoers a painful chastisement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And the people of Nuh! When they belied the apostles We drowned them, and made them a sign unto mankind. And We have gotten ready unto the wrong-doers a torment afflictive,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And Nuh's (Noah) people, when they denied the Messengers We drowned them, and We made them as a sign for mankind. And We have prepared a painful torment for the Zalimun (polytheists and wrong-doers, etc).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And the people of Noah: when they rejected the messengers, We drowned them, and made them a lesson for mankind. We have prepared for the wrongdoers a painful retribution.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>The same was the case with the people of Noah when they charged the Messenger with imposture: We drowned them and made them a sign of warning for entire mankind, and We have prepared a painful chastisement for the unjust.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>The nation of Noah, We drowned them when they belied their Messenger, and made of them a sign to the nation. For the harmdoers We have prepared a painful punishment</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And the people of Noah - when they denied the messengers, We drowned them, and We made them for mankind a sign. And We have prepared for the wrongdoers a painful punishment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We drowned the people of Noah because of their rejection of the Messengers and made them evidence of the Truth for mankind. We have prepared a painful torment for the unjust ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And the people of Nuh, when they rejected the apostles, We drowned them, and made them a sign for men, and We have prepared a painful punishment for the unjust;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We drowned the people of Noah also when they rejected their messengers and We made them an example to all mankind. We have prepared a painful punishment for the wrongdoers,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And the people of Noah,- when they rejected the messengers, We drowned them, and We made them as a Sign for mankind; and We have prepared for (all) wrong-doers a grievous Penalty;-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="82">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We drowned all the others (besides Noah and his people).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="51" verse="46">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(So had We destroyed) the people of Noah before them: They were surely a sinful people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And the people of Noah before; surely they were an ungodly people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And the people of Nuh We destroyed aforetime; verily they were a people transgressing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>(So were) the people of Nuh (Noah) before them. Verily, they were a people who were Fasiqun (rebellious, disobedient to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And before that, the people of Noah. They were immoral people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Before all these We destroyed the people of Noah: they were a wicked people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>(So were) the people of Nuh before them. Verily, they were a people who were rebellious.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And the folk of Noah aforetime. Lo! they were licentious folk.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And the people of Noah aforetime. Indeed, they were a transgressing lot.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And before them the nation of Noah, indeed they were a debauched nation.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [We destroyed] the people of Noah before; indeed, they were a people defiantly disobedient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The people of Noah who lived before them were also evil doing people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And the people of Nuh before, surely they were a transgressing people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>[We destroyed] the people of Noah before them. They were certainly a sinful people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So were the People of Noah before them for they wickedly transgressed.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="53" verse="52">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Like the people of Noah before them, who were surely oppressors and rebellious;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and the people of Noah before -- certainly they did exceeding evil, and were insolent</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And also the people of Nuh aforetime. Verily they were even greater wrong-doers and more contumacious.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And the people of Nuh (Noah) aforetime, verily, they were more unjust and more rebellious and transgressing [in disobeying Allah and His Messenger Nuh (Noah)].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And the people of Noah before that; for they were most unjust and most oppressive.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and that He it is Who destroyed the people of Noah before for they were much given to iniquity and transgression.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And the people of Nuh aforetime. Verily, they were more unjust and more rebellious and transgressing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And the folk of Noah aforetime, Lo! they were more unjust and more rebellious;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>and the people of Noah before that; indeed they were more unjust and rebellious;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and before them the nation of Noah, they exceeded in evil and were insolent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And the people of Noah before. Indeed, it was they who were [even] more unjust and oppressing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>and the people of Noah; they were the most unjust and rebellious people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And the people of Nuh before; surely they were most unjust and inordinate;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and before them the people of Noah who were even more unjust and insolent;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And before them, the people of Noah, for that they were (all) most unjust and most insolent transgressors,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="15">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.maududi</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We left the Ark as a Sign. Is there, then, any who will take heed?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made (the story of Noah) as evidence of the Truth. However, is there anyone who would take heed?</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="30">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, in this [what We did as regards drowning of the people of Nuh (Noah)], there are indeed Ayat (proofs, evidences, lessons, signs, etc. for men to understand), for sure We are ever putting (men) to the test.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="17" verse="3">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>O you, the offspring of those We bore (in the ark) with Noah, he was indeed a grateful votary.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>The seed of those We bore with Noah; he was a thankful servant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>O progeny of those whom We bare with Nuh: verily he was a bondman grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"O offspring of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Nuh (Noah)! Verily, he was a grateful slave."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>The descendants of those We carried with Noah. He was an appreciative servant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>You are the descendants of those whom We carried (in the Ark) with Noah. He was truly a thankful servant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"O offspring of those whom We carried (in the ship) with Nuh! Verily, he was a grateful servant."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>(They were) the seed of those whom We carried (in the ship) along with Noah. Lo! he was a grateful slave.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>descendants of those whom We carried [in the ark] with Noah. Indeed, he was a grateful servant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>(You are) the descendants of those whom We carried (in the Ark) with Noah. He was a truly thankful worshiper'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>O descendants of those We carried [in the ship] with Noah. Indeed, he was a grateful servant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(We made it a guide for) the offspring of those whom We carried in the Ark with Noah, a thankful servant (of God).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>The offspring of those whom We bore with Nuh; surely he was a grateful servant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>you who are the descendants of those whom We carried in the Ark with Noah. He was a truly thankful servant."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>O ye that are sprung from those whom We carried (in the Ark) with Noah! Verily he was a devotee most grateful.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="248">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.arberry</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And their Prophet said to them, 'The sign of his kingship is that the Ark will come to you, in it a Shechina from your Lord, and a remnant of what the folk of Moses and Aaron's folk left behind, the angels bearing it. Surely in that shall be a sign for you, if you are believers.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And their prophet said unto them: verily the sign of his dominion is that there shall come unto you the ark wherein is tranquillity from your Lord and the relic of that which the household of Musa and the household of Harun had left, the angels bearing it; verily, herein is a sign for you if ye are believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And their prophet said to them, “The proof of his kingship is that the Ark will be restored to you, bringing tranquility from your Lord, and relics left by the family of Moses and the family of Aaron. It will be carried by the angels. In that is a sign for you, if you are believers.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Their Prophet further informed them, "The sign of his appointment as king from Allah is that during his reign you will get back the Ark, wherein are the means of your peace of mind from your Lord, and which contains the sacred relics of the family of Moses and Aaron, and which is being borne at this time by the angels. Herein is a great Sign for you, if you are true believers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And their Prophet said unto them: Lo! the token of his kingdom is that there shall come unto you the ark wherein is peace of reassurance from your Lord, and a remnant of that which the house of Moses and the house of Aaron left behind, the angels bearing it. Lo! herein shall be a token for you if (in truth) ye are believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Their prophet said to them, ‘Indeed the sign of his kingship shall be that the Ark will come to you, bearing tranquillity from your Lord and the relics left behind by the House of Moses and the House of Aaron, borne by the angels. There is indeed a sign in that for you, should you be faithful.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Their Prophet said to them: 'The sign of his kingship is the coming of the Ark to you, therein shall be tranquility from your Lord, and a remnant which the House of Moses and the House of Aaron left behind. It will be borne by the angels. That will be a sign for you if you are believers'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Their Prophet further told them, "As the evidence of his authority, he will bring to you the Ark which will be a comfort to you from your Lord and a legacy of the household of Moses and Aaron. It will be carried by the angels. This is the evidence for you if you have faith."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Their prophet also said to them, "The sign of his kingship is that the Ark [of the Covenant] shall come to you. Therein shall be tranquillity from your Lord, and the relics which the House of Moses and the House of Aaron left behind. It will be borne by the angels. There is a sign in this for you, if you believe."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And (further) their Prophet said to them: "A Sign of his authority is that there shall come to you the Ark of the covenant, with (an assurance) therein of security from your Lord, and the relics left by the family of Moses and the family of Aaron, carried by angels. In this is a symbol for you if ye indeed have faith."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="75">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Noah had verily called to Us. And how gracious was He who answered (him).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Noah called to Us; and how excellent were the Answerers!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly Nuh cried Unto us; and We are the Best of answerers!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed Nuh (Noah) invoked Us, and We are the Best of those who answer (the request).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Noah called out to Us, and We are the Best of responders.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Noah had called upon Us (earlier). See, how excellent We were in answering him!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed Nuh invoked Us, and We are the best of those who answer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Noah verily prayed unto Us, and gracious was the Hearer of his prayer</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly Noah called out to Us, and how well did We respond!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Noah called to Us, and We are the Best to answer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Noah had certainly called Us, and [We are] the best of responders.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Noah called for help. How blessed was the answer which he received.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Nuh did certainly call upon Us, and most excellent answerer of prayer are We.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Noah cried to Us, and how excellent was Our response!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(In the days of old), Noah cried to Us, and We are the best to hear prayer.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="79">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Peace on Noah among all men.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>'Peace be upon Noah among all beings!'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Peace be on Nuh among the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Salamun (peace) be upon Nuh (Noah) (from Us) among the 'Alamin (mankind, jinns and all that exists)!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Peace be upon Noah among all people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Peace be upon Noah among all the nations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Salam (peace!) be upon Nuh among the all creatures!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Peace be unto Noah among the peoples!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>‘Peace to Noah, throughout the nations!’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>'Peace be upon Noah among all the worlds'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>"Peace upon Noah among the worlds."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Peace be with Noah among all men in the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Peace and salutation to Nuh among the nations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Peace be upon Noah among all the peoples!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Peace and salutation to Noah among the nations!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="81">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, he [Nuh (Noah)] was one of Our believing slaves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, he [Nuh] was one of Our believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="83">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And, verily, among those who followed his [Nuh's (Noah)] way (Islamic Monotheism) was Ibrahim (Abraham).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Abraham was on the self-same way (as Noah).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="23" verse="31">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We brought another generation into existence after the people of Noah.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="10" verse="74">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.sarwar</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>After (Noah) We sent other Messengers to their people with clear authoritative evidence proving their prophetic claims). But how could the people believe what they had previously called lies? Thus do We seal the hearts of the transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="17" verse="17">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"How many generations have We laid low after Noah, for your Lord knows and notices well enough the sins of His creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>How many generations We have destroyed after Noah! Thy Lord suffices as one who is aware of and sees the sins of His servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>How many a generation have We destroyed after Nuh; and sufficeth for the offences of His bondmen thy Lord as the Aware, the Beholder.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And how many generations have We destroyed after Nuh (Noah)! And Sufficient is your Lord as an All-Knower and All-Beholder of the sins of His slaves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>How many generations have We destroyed after Noah? Your Lord is sufficient as Knower and Beholder of the sins of his servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And how many generations have We destroyed after Nuh! And sufficient is your Lord as All-Knower and Seer of the sins of His servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>How many generations have We destroyed since Noah! And Allah sufficeth as Knower and Beholder of the sins of His slaves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>How many generations We have destroyed since Noah! Your Lord is sufficient as [a witness who is] well aware and percipient of His servants’ sins.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>How many generations have We destroyed since Noah! Your Lord suffices as One who is Aware of and sees the sins of His worshipers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And how many have We destroyed from the generations after Noah. And sufficient is your Lord, concerning the sins of His servants, as Acquainted and Seeing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We have destroyed many generations after the time of Noah. Your Lord is All knowing and Well Aware of the sins of His servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And how many of the generations did We destroy after Nuh! and your Lord is sufficient as Knowing and Seeing with regard to His servants' faults.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>How many generations have We destroyed after Noah? and enough is thy Lord to note and see the sins of His servants.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="9" verse="70">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Has not the account of those before them come to them, -- of the people of Noah and 'Ad and Thamud, of Abraham and Midian, and all the habitations that were destroyed? Their apostles had come to them with clear proofs; and God did not surely wrong them, they wronged themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Has there not come to you the tidings of those who were before you -- the people of Noah, Ad, Thamood, the people of Abraham, the men of Midian and the subverted cities? Their Messengers came to them with the clear signs God would not wrong them, but themselves they wronged.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Have not come to them the tidings of those before them: the people of Nuh and 'Ad and Thamud and the people of Ibrahim and the dwellers of Madyan and of the overturned cities! There came unto them their apostles with evidences. Wherefore Allah was not one to wrong them, but themselves they were wont to wrong.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Has not the story reached them of those before them? - The people of Nuh (Noah), 'Ad, and Thamud, the people of Ibrahim (Abraham), the dwellers of Madyan (Midian) and the cities overthrown [i.e. the people to whom Lout (Lot) preached], to them came their Messengers with clear proofs. So it was not Allah Who wronged them, but they used to wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Have they not heard the stories of those before them? The people of Noah, and Aad, and Thamood; and the people of Abraham, and the inhabitants of Median, and the Overturned Cities? Their messengers came to them with the clear proofs. God never wronged them, but they used to wrong their own selves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Have they not heard the accounts of those who came before them - of the people of Noah and 'Ad and Thamud, and the people of Abraham and the dwellers of Madyan (Midian), and the cities that were overturned? Their Messengers came to them with Clear Signs. Then, it was not Allah Who caused them any wrong; they rather wronged themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Has not the story reached them of those before them -- The people of Nuh,`Ad, Thamud, the people of Ibrahim, the dwellers of Madyan and the overturned cities; to them came their Messengers with clear proofs. So it was not Allah Who wronged them, but they used to wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Hath not the fame of those before them reached them - the folk of Noah, A'ad, Thamud, the folk of Abraham, the dwellers of Midian and the disasters (which befell them)? Their messengers (from Allah) came unto them with proofs (of Allah's Sovereignty). So Allah surely wronged them not, but they did wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Has there not come to them the account of those who were before them—the people of Noah, ‘Ad, and Tham£d, and the people of Abraham, the inhabitants of Midian, and the towns that were overturned? Their apostles brought them manifest proofs. So it was not Allah who wronged them, but it was they who used to wrong themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Have they not heard the news of those who have gone before them? The news of the nations of Noah, Aad and Thamood, of Abraham's nation, and the people of Midian and the ruined cities? Their Messengers showed them clear signs. Allah did not harm them, but they harmed themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Has there not reached them the news of those before them - the people of Noah and [the tribes of] 'Aad and Thamud and the people of Abraham and the companions of Madyan and the towns overturned? Their messengers came to them with clear proofs. And Allah would never have wronged them, but they were wronging themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Have they not heard the stories of the people of Noah, the tribe of Ad, Thamud, the people of Abraham, the dwellers of the city of Midian, and those of the Subverted Cities? God's Messengers came to each of them with miracles. God did not do any injustice to them, but they wronged themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Has not the news of those before them come to them; of the people of Nuh and Ad and Samood, and the people of Ibrahim and the dwellers of Madyan and the overthrown cities; their apostles came to them with clear arguments; so it was not Allah Who should do them injustice, but they were unjust to themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Have they never heard the stories about their predecessors, the peoples of Noah, 'Ad, Thamud, Abraham, Midian, and of the ruined cities? Their messengers brought them clear evidence of the truth. It was not God who wronged them; they wronged themselves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Hath not the story reached them of those before them?- the People of Noah, and 'Ad, and Thamud; the People of Abraham, the men of Midian, and the cities overthrown. To them came their messengers with clear signs. It is not Allah Who wrongs them, but they wrong their own souls.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="14" verse="9">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Has not the news of those before you, the people of Noah and 'Ad and Thamud, and those who came after them, come to you? None knows (about) them except God. Their apostles came to them with clear proofs, but they tried to silence them and said: "We do not believe in what you have been sent with, and we are in doubt of what you call us to, about which we are in disquiet.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Has there not come to you the tidings of those who were before you -- the people of Noah, Ad, Thamood, and of those after them whom none knows but God? Their Messengers came to them with the clear signs; but they thrust their hands into their mouths, saying, 'We certainly disbelieve in the Message you have been sent with, and we are in doubt, concerning that you call us unto, disquieting.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Hath not the tidings come to you of those before you: the people of Nuh and the 'Aad and the Thamud and those after them! None knoweth them save Allah. There came unto them their apostles with the evidences, but they put their hands to their mouths, and said: verily we disbelieve in that where- with ye have been sent, and verily regarding that to which ye call Us We are in doubt disquieting.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Has not the news reached you, of those before you, the people of Nuh (Noah), and 'Ad, and Thamud? And those after them? None knows them but Allah. To them came their Messengers with clear proofs, but they put their hands in their mouths (biting them from anger) and said: "Verily, we disbelieve in that with which you have been sent, and we are really in grave doubt as to that to which you invite us (i.e. Islamic Monotheism)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Has not the story reached you, of those before you, the people of Noah, and Aad, and Thamood—and those after them? None knows them except God. Their messengers came to them with the clear proofs, but they tried to silence them, and said, “We reject what you are sent with, and we are in serious doubt regarding what you are calling us to.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Have the accounts of your predecessors not reached you: the people of Noah, the Ad, the Thamud, and those who came after them - they whose number is not known to any except Allah? Their Messengers came to them with Clear Signs, but they thrust their hands in their mouths, and said: "We do surely reject the Message you have brought, and we are in disquieting doubt about what you are summoning us to."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Has not the news reached you, of those before you, the people of Nuh, `Ad, and Thamud And those after them None knows them but Allah. To them came their Messengers with clear proofs, but they put their hands in their mouths and said: "Verily, we disbelieve in that with which you have been sent, and we are really in grave doubt as to that to which you invite us."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Hath not the history of those before you reached you: the folk of Noah, and (the tribes of) A'ad and Thamud, and those after them? None save Allah knoweth them. Their messengers came unto them with clear proofs, but they thrust their hands into their mouths, and said: Lo! we disbelieve in that wherewith ye have been sent, and lo! we are in grave doubt concerning that to which ye call us.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Has there not come to you the account of those who were before you—the people of Noah, ‘Ad and Thamud, and those who were after them, whom no one knows [well] except Allah? Their apostles brought them manifest proofs, but they did not respond to them, and said, ‘We disbelieve in what you have been sent with. Indeed we have grave doubts concerning that to which you invite us.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Have you not heard what befell the nations that have gone before you? The nations of Noah, Aad, and Thamood, and those who came after? None knows them but Allah. Their Messengers came to them with clear signs, but they thrust their hands into their mouths and said: 'Without doubt we disbelieve the Message you have been sent with. That which you call us to is disquieting'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Has there not reached you the news of those before you - the people of Noah and 'Aad and Thamud and those after them? No one knows them but Allah. Their messengers brought them clear proofs, but they returned their hands to their mouths and said, "Indeed, we disbelieve in that with which you have been sent, and indeed we are, about that to which you invite us, in disquieting doubt."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Have you (believers) ever heard the news about those who lived before you, like the people of Noah, Ad, Thamud, and those who lived after them? No one knows about them except God. Messengers were sent to them with miracles, but they put their hands to their mouths and said, "We do not believe in whatever you preach and we are also doubtful and uncertain about that to which you invite us."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Has not the account reached you of those before you, of the people of Nuh and Ad and Samood, and those after them? None knows them but Allah. Their apostles come to them with clear arguments, but they thrust their hands into their mouths and said: Surely we deny that with which you are sent, and most surely we are in serious doubt as to that to which you invite us.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Has not the story reached you, (O people!), of those who (went) before you? - of the people of Noah, and 'Ad, and Thamud? - And of those who (came) after them? None knows them but Allah. To them came messengers with Clear (Signs); but they put their hands up to their mouths, and said: "We do deny (the mission) on which ye have been sent, and we are really in suspicious (disquieting) doubt as to that to which ye invite us."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="22" verse="42">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>If they accuse you of falsehood, (remember that) the people of Noah, 'Ad and Thamud had accused (their apostles) before,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>If they cry lies to thee, so too before them the people of Noah cried lies, and Ad and Thamood,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And if they belie thee, then surely there have belied before them the people of Nuh and the 'Aad and the Thamud.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And if they belie you (O Muhammad SAW), so were belied the Prophets before them, (by) the people of Nuh (Noah), 'Ad and Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>If they deny you—before them the people of Noah, and Aad, and Thamood also denied.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And if they deny you, so did deny before them the people of Nuh, `Ad and Thamud.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>If they deny thee (Muhammad), even so the folk of Noah, and (the tribes of) A'ad and Thamud, before thee, denied (Our messengers);</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>If they impugn you, the people of Noah had impugned before them and ‘Ad and Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>If they belie you, so too before them, the nation of Noah belied, and Aad and Thamood</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And if they deny you, [O Muhammad] - so, before them, did the people of Noah and 'Aad and Thamud deny [their prophets],</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>If they have called you, (Muhammad), a liar, (remember that) the people of Noah, Ad, Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And if they reject you, then already before you did the people of Nuh and Ad and Samood reject (prophets).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>If your opponents deny you, remember that, before them, the people of Noah and the tribes of 'Ad and Thamud denied their messengers likewise.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>If they treat thy (mission) as false, so did the peoples before them (with their prophets),- the People of Noah, and 'Ad and Thamud;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="40" verse="5">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>The people of Noah had denied before them, and many factions after them. Every nation has intrigued against its apostle and afflicted him, and argued with false arguments to condemn the truth. Then I seized them. How was then My retribution!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>The people of Noah before them also cried lies, and the parties after them; every nation purposed against their Messenger to seize him, and disputed with falsehood that they might rebut thereby the truth. Then I seized them; and how was My retribution!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>The people of Nuh and the confederates after them belied their apostles before these, and each disbelieving community advanced toward their apostle that they may lay hold of him and disputed with vain speech that they may confute the truth thereby. Wherefore I laid hold of them; and how terrible was My chastisement!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>The people of Nuh (Noah) and the confederates after them denied (their Messengers) before these, and every (disbelieving) nation plotted against their Messenger to seize him, and disputed by means of falsehood to refute therewith the truth. So I seized them (with punishment), and how (terrible) was My punishment!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Before them the people of Noah rejected the truth, as did the confederates after them. Every community plotted against their messenger, to capture him. And they argued with falsehood, to defeat with it the truth. But I seized them. What a punishment it was!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Before them the people of Noah also gave the lie (to Messengers), and so did many parties after them. Each nation sallied forth against its Messenger to seize him, and they disputed with false arguments seeking therewith to repudiate the Truth. Then I seized them; and behold, how woeful was My retribution!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>The people of Nuh and the groups after them denied before these; and every nation plotted against their Messenger to seize him, and disputed by means of falsehood to refute therewith the truth. So I seized them, and how was My punishment!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>The folk of Noah and the factions after them denied (their messengers) before these, and every nation purposed to seize their messenger and argued falsely, (thinking) thereby to refute the Truth. Then I seized them, and how (awful) was My punishment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>The people of Noah denied before them and the [heathen] factions [who came] after them. Every nation attempted to lay hands on their apostle, and disputed erroneously to refute the truth. Then I seized them; so how was My retribution?!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>The nation of Noah before them belied, and so did the parties after them. Every nation strove against their Messenger to seize him, disputing with false arguments to refute the truth. Then I seized them, how was My punishment!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>The people of Noah denied before them and the [disbelieving] factions after them, and every nation intended [a plot] for their messenger to seize him, and they disputed by [using] falsehood to [attempt to] invalidate thereby the truth. So I seized them, and how [terrible] was My penalty.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The people of Noah who lived before and the Confederate tribes who lived after them rejected Our revelations. Every nation schemed against its Messengers to seize them and disputed against them to defeat the truth. But torment struck them and how terrible was their retribution!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>The people of Nuh and the parties after them rejected (prophets) before them, and every nation purposed against their apostle to destroy him, and they disputed by means of the falsehood that they might thereby render null the truth, therefore I destroyed them; how was then My retribution!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>The people of Noah and later factions also rejected the truth and every community plotted against the messenger sent to them, aiming to lay hands on him, and they contended [against his message] with fallacious arguments, so that they might defeat the truth, therefore I seized them. How terrible was My punishment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>But (there were people) before them, who denied (the Signs),- the People of Noah, and the Confederates (of Evil) after them; and every People plotted against their prophet, to seize him, and disputed by means of vanities, therewith to condemn the Truth; but it was I that seized them! and how (terrible) was My Requital!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="40" verse="31">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Like the people of Noah, 'Ad and Thamud, and those that came after them. God does not want to be unjust to His creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Like the wont of the people of Nuh and A'ad and Thamud and those after them, and God intendeth not any wrong Unto His bondmen.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"Like the fate of the people of Nuh (Noah), and 'Ad, and Thamud and those who came after them. And Allah wills no injustice for (His) slaves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Like the fate of the people of Noah, and Aad, and Thamood, and those after them. God wants no injustice for the servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>like the day that overtook the people of Noah and Ad and Thamud, and those who came after them. Allah does not wish to subject His servants to any injustice.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Like the end of the people of Nuh, and `Ad, and Thamud and those who came after them. And Allah wills no injustice for (His) servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>like the case of the people of Noah, of Ad and Thamud, and those who came after them, and Allah does not desire any wrong for [His] servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>or, something similar to the circumstances of the nations of Noah, Aad, and Thamood, and those who came after them. Allah does not want to wrong His worshipers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Like the custom of the people of Noah and of 'Aad and Thamud and those after them. And Allah wants no injustice for [His] servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>people of Noah, Ad, Thamud, and those after them. God did not want injustice for His servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>The like of what befell the people of Nuh and Ad and Samood and those after them, and Allah does not desire injustice for (His) servants;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>like the fate of the people of Noah, 'Ad, Thamud, and those who came after them -- God never wills injustice on His creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Something like the fate of the People of Noah, the 'Ad, and the Thamud, and those who came after them: but Allah never wishes injustice to his Servants.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="12">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Even before them the people of Noah, 'Ad, the mighty Pharoah,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Cried lies before them the people of Noah, and Ad, and Pharaoh, he of the tent-pegs,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Before them there have belied the people of Nuh and the 'Aad, and Fir'awn the owner of the stakes.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Before them (were many who) belied Messengers, the people of Nuh (Noah); and 'Ad; and Fir'aun (Pharaoh) the man of stakes (with which he used to punish the people),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Before them the people of Noah denied the truth; as did Aad, and Pharaoh of the Stakes.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Before them the people of Noah, Ad, and Pharaoh of the tent-pegs gave the lie (to the Messengers)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Before them denied -- the people of Nuh; and `Ad; and Fir`awn the man of stakes,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>The folk of Noah before them denied (their messenger) and (so did the tribe of) A'ad, and Pharaoh firmly planted,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Before them the nations of Noah, Aad and Pharaoh, and he of the tentpegs belied,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>The people of Noah denied before them, and [the tribe of] 'Aad and Pharaoh, the owner of stakes,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The people of Noah, Ad and the dominating Pharaoh had rejected Our revelations.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>The people of Nuh and Ad, and Firon, the lord of spikes, rejected (apostles) before them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Before them the people of Noah denied the truth, as did the 'Ad and Pharaoh of the Stakes,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Before them (were many who) rejected messengers,- the people of Noah, and 'Ad, and Pharaoh, the Lord of Stakes,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="50" verse="12">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>The people of Noah, Ar-Rass and Thamud denied before you,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Cried lies before them the people of Noah and the men of Er-Rass, and Thamood,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And before them the people of Nuh belied, and so did the dwellers Of Rass and the Thamud.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Denied before them (i.e. these pagans of Makkah who denied you, O Muhammad SAW) the people of Nuh (Noah), and the dwellers of Rass, and the Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Before them the people of Noah denied the truth, and so did the dwellers of Russ, and Thamood.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Denied before them the people of Nuh, and the Dwellers of Rass, and Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>The folk of Noah denied (the truth) before them, and (so did) the dwellers at Ar-Rass and (the tribe of) Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>The people of Noah denied before them, and [so did] the people of Rass and Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Before them, the nation of Noah, the nation of ArRass belied and so did Thamood</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>The people of Noah denied before them, and the companions of the well and Thamud</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The people of Noah, dwellers of the Ra's, Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>(Others) before them rejected (prophets): the people of Nuh and the dwellers of Ar-Rass and Samood,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Before them, the people of Noah and the people of Rass denied this truth; and so did the people of Thamud.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Before them was denied (the Hereafter) by the People of Noah, the Companions of the Rass, the Thamud,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="54" verse="43">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Are your disbelievers (O Quraish!) better than these [nations of Nuh (Noah), Lout (Lot), Salih (Saleh), and the people of Fir'aun (Pharaoh), etc., who were destroyed)? Or have you an immunity (against Our Torment) in the Divine Scriptures?</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="11" verse="89">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"O my people (I fear) lest your opposition to me should bring you the like of what befell the people of Noah or Hud or Saleh; and the people of Lot are not distant from you.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>O my people, let not the breach with me move you, so that there smite you the like of what smote the people of Noah, or the people of Hood, or the people of Salih; and the people of Lot are not far away from you.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And, O my people! let not the cleavage with me incite you so that there befall you the like of that which befell the people of Nuh and the people of Hud and the people of Saleh; and the people of Lut are not from you far away.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"And O my people! Let not my Shiqaqcause you to suffer the fate similar to that of the people of Nuh (Noah) or of Hud or of Salih (Saleh), and the people of Lout (Lot) are not far off from you!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“O my people, let not your hostility towards me cause you to suffer what was suffered by the people of Noah, or the people of Hud, or the people of Saleh. The people of Lot are not far away from you.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>My people! Let not your opposition to me lead you to guilt that would bring upon you the chastisement that struck earlier the people of Noah, and the people of Hud, and the people of Salih. And the land of the people of Lot is not far from you!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"And O my people! Let not my Shiqaq cause you to suffer the fate similar to that of the people of Nuh or of Hud or of Salih, and the people of Lut are not far off from you!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And, O my people! Let not the schism with me cause you to sin so that there befall you that which befell the folk of Noah and the folk of Hud, and the folk of Salih; and the folk of Lot are not far off from you.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>O my people, do not let your defiance toward me lead you to be visited by the like of what was visited on the people of Noah, or the people of Hud, or the people of Salih, and the people of Lot are not distant from you.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And my nation, do not let your breaking with me bring upon you something similar to that which struck the nation of Noah, Hood, and Salih and it is not long since the people of Lot (were punished).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And O my people, let not [your] dissension from me cause you to be struck by that similar to what struck the people of Noah or the people of Hud or the people of Salih. And the people of Lot are not from you far away.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>My people, do not let your opposition to me lead you to commit sins or make you suffer what the people of Noah, Hud, and Salih suffered. Remember that the people of Lot were destroyed not very long ago.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And, O my people! let not opposition to me make you guilty so that there may befall you the like of what befell the people of Nuh, or the people of Hud, or the people of Salih, nor are the people of Lut far off from you;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>O my people, do not let your opposition to me bring upon you a fate similar to the peoples of Noah or Hud or Salih; nor is it long since the people of Lot were punished!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"And O my people! let not my dissent (from you) cause you to sin, lest ye suffer a fate similar to that of the people of Noah or of Hud or of Salih, nor are the people of Lut far off from you!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="29" verse="40">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So We punished each (of them) for his sins, of them were some on whom We sent Hasiban (a violent wind with shower of stones) [as the people of Lout (Lot)], and of them were some who were overtaken by As-Saihah [torment - awful cry, etc. (as Thamud or Shu'aib's people)], and of them were some whom We caused the earth to swallow [as Qarun (Korah)], and of them were some whom We drowned [as the people of Nuh (Noah), or Fir'aun (Pharaoh) and his people]. It was not Allah Who wronged them, but they wronged themselves.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="69">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Do you wonder that a warning has come to you from your Lord through a man who is one of you and warns you? Remember, He made you leaders after the people of Noah, and gave you a greater increase in your stature. So think of the favours of God; you may haply be blessed."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>What, do you wonder that a reminder from your Lord should come to you by the lips of a man from among you? That he may warn you; and remember when He appointed you as successors after the people of Noah, and increased you in stature broadly; remember God's bounties; haply you will prosper.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Marvel ye that an admonition from your Lord should come unto you upon a Man from amongst you in order that he may warn you? Remember what time He made you successors after the people, of Nuh, and increased you amply in stature Remember the benefits of Allah, that haply ye may fare well.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"Do you wonder that there has come to you a Reminder (and an advice) from your Lord through a man from amongst you that he may warn you? And remember that He made you successors after the people of Nuh (Noah), and increased you amply in stature. So remember the graces (bestowed upon you) from Allah, so that you may be successful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“Are you surprised that a reminder has come to you from your Lord, through a man from among you, to warn you? Remember how He made you successors after the people of Noah, and increased you greatly in stature. And remember God’s blessings, so that you may prosper.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Do you wonder that an exhortation should come to you from your Lord through a man from amongst yourselves that he may warn you? And do call to mind when He made you successors after the people of Noah and amply increased you in stature. Remember then the wondrous bounties of Allah, that you may prosper.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Do you wonder that there has come to you a Reminder (and an advice) from your Lord through a man from among you to warn you And remember that He made you successors (generations after generations) after the people of Nuh and increased you amply in stature. So remember the graces (bestowed upon you) from Allah so that you may be successful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Do you consider it odd that there should come to you a reminder from your Lord through a man from among yourselves, so that he may warn you? Remember when He made you successors after the people of Noah, and increased you vastly in creation. So remember Allah’s bounties so that you may be felicitous.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Then do you wonder that there has come to you a reminder from your Lord through a man from among you, that he may warn you? And remember when He made you successors after the people of Noah and increased you in stature extensively. So remember the favors of Allah that you might succeed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Does it seem strange to you that a reminder from your Lord should be sent to a man among you so that He may warn you? Recall when God appointed you as successors of the people of Noah and increased your power over other people. Give thanks to God for His blessings so that perhaps you will have everlasting happiness."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Do ye wonder that there hath come to you a message from your Lord through a man of your own people, to warn you? call in remembrance that He made you inheritors after the people of Noah, and gave you a stature tall among the nations. Call in remembrance the benefits (ye have received) from Allah: that so ye may prosper."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="7" verse="89">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We shall only be guilty of blaspheming God if we accept your way after the people of Noah, and gave you a greater increase in your stature. So think of the favours of God; you may haply be blessed."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="20" verse="39">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.arberry</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>"Cast him into the ark, and cast him into the river, and let the river throw him up on the shore. An enemy of Mine and his shall take him." And I loaded on thee love from Me, and to be formed in My sight,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Saying! cast him in the ark, and cast him into the river, and the river will throw him on the bank, and then an enemy of Mine and an enemy of his will take him up. And I cast on thee love from Me in order that thou mayest be formed under Mine eye.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Saying: Throw him into the ark, and throw it into the river, then the river shall throw it on to the bank, and there an enemy to Me and an enemy to him shall take him. And I endued thee with love from Me that thou mightest be trained according to My will,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="553">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn Umar:
Once Allah's Apostle stood amongst the people, glorified and praised Allah as He deserved and then mentioned the Dajjal saying, "l warn you against him (i.e. the Dajjal) and there was no prophet but warned his nation against him. No doubt, Noah warned his nation against him but I tell you about him something of which no prophet told his nation before me. You should know that he is one-eyed, and Allah is not one-eyed."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="554">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah's Apostle said, "Shall I not tell you about the Dajjal a story of which no prophet told his nation? The Dajjall is one-eyed and will bring with him what will resemble Hell and Paradise, and what he will call Paradise will be actually Hell; so I warn you (against him) as Noah warned his nation against him."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="52" verse="290">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn 'Umar:
Umar and a group of the companions of the Prophet set out with the Prophet to Ibn Saiyad. He found him playing with some boys near the hillocks of Bani Maghala. Ibn Saiyad at that time was nearing his puberty. He did not notice (the Prophet's presence) till the Prophet stroked him on the back with his hand and said, "Ibn Saiyad! Do you testify that I am Allah's Apostle?" Ibn Saiyad looked at him and said, "I testify that you are the Apostle of the illiterates."
Then Ibn Saiyad asked the Prophet. "Do you testify that I am the apostle of Allah?" The Prophet said to him, "I believe in Allah and His Apostles." Then the Prophet said (to Ibn Saiyad). "What do you see?" Ibn Saiyad replied, "True people and false ones visit me." The Prophet said, "Your mind is confused as to this matter." The Prophet added, " I have kept something (in my mind) for you." Ibn Saiyad said, "It is Ad-Dukh." The Prophet said (to him), "Shame be on you! You cannot cross your limits." On that 'Umar said, "O Allah's Apostle! Allow me to chop his head off." The Prophet said, "If he should be him (i.e. Ad-Dajjal) then you cannot overpower him, and should he not be him, then you are not going to benefit by murdering him."
Narrated Ibn Umar:
(Later on) Allah's Apostle (once again) went along with Ubai bin Ka'b to the garden of date-palms where Ibn Saiyad was staying. When the Prophet entered the garden, he started hiding himself behind the trunks of the date-palms as he wanted to hear something from the Ibn Saiyad before the latter could see him. Ibn Saiyad was lying in his bed, covered with a velvet sheet from where his murmurs were heard. Ibn Saiyad's mother saw the Prophet while he was hiding himself behind the trunks of the date-palms. She addressed Ibn Saiyad, "O Saf!" (And this was his name). Ibn Saiyad got up. The Prophet said, "Had this woman let him to himself, he would have revealed the reality of his case." Then the Prophet got up amongst the people, glorifying Allah as He deserves, he mentioned Ad-Dajjal, saying, "I warn you about him (i.e. Ad-Dajjal) and there is no prophet who did not warn his nation about him, and Noah warned his nation about him, but I tell you a statement which no prophet informed his nation of. You should understand that he is a one-eyed man and Allah is not one-eyed."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="73" verse="194">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Umar:
'Umar bin Al-Khattab set out with Allah's Apostle, and a group of his companions to Ibn Saiyad. They found him playing with the boys in the fort or near the Hillocks of Bani Maghala. Ibn Saiyad was nearing his puberty at that time, and he did not notice the arrival of the Prophet till Allah's Apostle stroked him on the back with his hand and said, "Do you testify that I am Allah's Apostle?" Ibn Saiyad looked at him and said, "I testify that you are the Apostle of the unlettered ones (illiterates)". Then Ibn Saiyad said to the Prophets . "Do you testify that I am Allah's Apostle?" The Prophet denied that, saying, "I believe in Allah and all His Apostles," and then said to Ibn Saiyad, "What do you see?" Ibn Saiyad said, "True people and liars visit me." The Prophet said, "You have been confused as to this matter." Allah's Apostle added, "I have kept something for you (in my mind)." Ibn Saiyad said, "Ad-Dukh." The Prophet said, "Ikhsa (you should be ashamed) for you can not cross your limits." 'Umar said, "O Allah's Apostle! Allow me to chop off h is neck." Allah's Apostle said (to Umar). "Should this person be him (i.e. Ad-Dajjal) then you cannot over-power him; and should he be someone else, then it will be no use your killing him." 'Abdullah bin 'Umar added: Later on Allah's Apostle and Ubai bin Ka'b Al-Ansari (once again) went to the garden in which Ibn Saiyad was present.
When Allah's Apostle entered the garden, he started hiding behind the trunks of the date-palms intending to hear something from Ibn Saiyad before the latter could see him. Ibn Saiyad was Lying on his bed, covered with a velvet sheet from where his mumur were heard. Ibn Saiyad's mother saw the Prophet and said, "O Saf (the nickname of Ibn Saiyad)! Here is Muhammad!" Ibn Saiyad stopped his murmuring. The Prophet said, "If his mother had kept quiet, then I would have learnt more about him." 'Abdullah added: Allah's Apostle stood up before the people (delivering a sermon), and after praising and glorifying Allah as He deserved, he mentioned the Ad-Dajjal saying, "I warn you against him, and there has been no prophet but warned his followers against him. Noah warned his followers against him but I am telling you about him, something which no prophet has told his people of, and that is: Know that he is blind in one eye where as Allah is not so."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="59" verse="685">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 5</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol05</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn Umar:
We were talking about Hajjat-ul-Wada, while the Prophet was amongst us. We did not know what Hajjat-ul-Wada' signified. The Prophet praised Allah and then mentioned Al-Masih Ad-Dajjal and described him extensively, saying, "Allah did not send any prophet but that prophet warned his nation of Al-Masih Ad-Dajjal. Noah and the prophets following him warned (their people) of him. He will appear amongst you (O Muhammad's followers), and if it happens that some of his qualities may be hidden from you, but your Lord's State is clear to you and not hidden from you. The Prophet said it thrice. Verily, your Lord is not blind in one eye, while he (i.e. Ad-Dajjal) is blind in the right eye which looks like a grape bulging out (of its cluster). No doubt,! Allah has made your blood and your properties sacred to one another like the sanctity of this day of yours, in this town of yours, in this month of yours." The Prophet added: No doubt! Haven't I conveyed Allah's Message to you? " They replied, "Yes," The Prophet said thrice, "O Allah! Be witness for it." The Prophet added, "Woe to you!" (or said), "May Allah be merciful to you! Do not become infidels after me (i.e. my death) by cutting the necks (throats) of one another."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="555">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Said:
Allah's Apostle said, "Noah and his nation will come (on the Day of Resurrection and Allah will ask (Noah), "Did you convey (the Message)?' He will reply, 'Yes, O my Lord!' Then Allah will ask Noah's nation, 'Did Noah convey My Message to you?' They will reply, 'No, no prophet came to us.' Then Allah will ask Noah, 'Who will stand a witness for you?' He will reply, 'Muhammad and his followers (will stand witness for me).' So, I and my followers will stand as witnesses for him (that he conveyed Allah's Message)." That is, (the interpretation) of the Statement of Allah: "Thus we have made you a just and the best nation that you might be witnesses Over mankind .." (2.143)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="14">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Said Al-Khudri:
Allah's Apostle said, "Noah will be called on the Day of Resurrection and he will say, 'Labbaik and Sa'daik, O my Lord!' Allah will say, 'Did you convey the Message?' Noah will say, 'Yes.' His nation will then be asked, 'Did he convey the Message to you?' They will say, 'No Warner came to us.' Then Allah will say (to Noah), 'Who will bear witness in your favor?' He will say, 'Muhammad and his followers. So they (i.e. Muslims) will testify that he conveyed the Message. And the Apostle (Muhammad) will be a witness over yourselves, and that is what is meant by the Statement of Allah "Thus We have made of you a just and the best nation that you may be witnesses over mankind and the Apostle (Muhammad) will be a witness over yourselves."
(2.143)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="92" verse="448">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Said Al-Khudri:
Allah's Apostle said, "Noah will be brought (before Allah) on the Day of Resurrection, and will be asked, 'Did you convey the message of Allah?" He will reply, 'Yes, O Lord.' And then Noah's nation will be asked, 'Did he (Noah) convey Allah's message to you?' They will reply, 'No warner came to us.' Then Noah will be asked, 'Who are your witnesses?' He will reply. '(My witnesses are) Muhammad and his followers.' Thereupon you (Muslims) will be brought and you will bear witness." Then the Prophet recited: 'And thus We have made of you (Muslims) a just and the best nation, that you might be witness over the nations, and the Apostle a witness over you.' (2.143)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="556">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
We were in the company of the Prophet at a banquet and a cooked (mutton) forearm was set before him, and he used to like it. He ate a morsel of it and said, "I will be the chief of all the people on the Day of Resurrection. Do you know how Allah will gather all the first and the last (people) in one level place where an observer will be able to see (all) of them and they will be able to hear the announcer, and the sun will come near to them. Some People will say: Don't you see, in what condition you are and the state to which you have reached? Why don't you look for a person who can intercede for you with your Lord? Some people will say: Appeal to your father, Adam.' They will go to him and say: 'O Adam! You are the father of all mankind, and Allah created you with His Own Hands, and ordered the angels to prostrate for you, and made you live in Paradise. Will you not intercede for us with your Lord? Don't you see in what (miserable) state we are, and to what condition we have reached?' On that Adam will reply, 'My Lord is so angry as He has never been before and will never be in the future; (besides), He forbade me (to eat from) the tree, but I disobeyed (Him), (I am worried about) myself! Myself! Go to somebody else; go to Noah.' They will go to Noah and say; 'O Noah! You are the first amongst the messengers of Allah to the people of the earth, and Allah named you a thankful slave. Don't you see in what a (miserable) state we are and to what condition we have reached? Will you not intercede for us with your Lord? Noah will reply: 'Today my Lord has become so angry as he had never been before and will never be in the future Myself! Myself! Go to the Prophet (Muhammad). The people will come to me, and I will prostrate myself underneath Allah's Throne. Then I will be addressed: 'O Muhammad! Raise your head; intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask (for anything). for you will be given. "</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="236">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Some (cooked) meat was brought to Allah Apostle and the meat of a forearm was presented to him as he used to like it. He ate a morsel of it and said, "I will be the chief of all the people on the Day of Resurrection. Do you know the reason for it? Allah will gather all the human being of early generations as well as late generation on one plain so that the announcer will be able to make them all-hear his voice and the watcher will be able to see all of them. The sun will come so close to the people that they will suffer such distress and trouble as they will not be able to bear or stand. Then the people will say, 'Don't you see to what state you have reached? Won't you look for someone who can intercede for you with your Lord' Some people will say to some others, 'Go to Adam.' So they will go to Adam and say to him. 'You are the father of mankind; Allah created you with His Own Hand, and breathed into you of His Spirit (meaning the spirit which he created for you); and ordered the angels to prostrate before you; so (please) intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see in what state we are? Don't you see what condition we have reached?' Adam will say, 'Today my Lord has become angry as He has never become before, nor will ever become thereafter. He forbade me (to eat of the fruit of) the tree, but I disobeyed Him . Myself! Myself! Myself! (has more need for intercession). Go to someone else; go to Noah.' So they will go to Noah and say (to him), 'O Noah! You are the first (of Allah's Messengers) to the people of the earth, and Allah has named you a thankful slave; please intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see in what state we are?' He will say.' Today my Lord has become angry as He has never become nor will ever become thereafter. I had (in the world) the right to make one definitely accepted invocation, and I made it against my nation. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Abraham.' They will go to Abraham and say, 'O Abraham! You are Allah's Apostle and His Khalil from among the people of the earth; so please intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see in what state we are?' He will say to them, 'My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before, nor will ever become thereafter. I had told three lies (Abu Haiyan (the sub-narrator) mentioned them in the Hadith) Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Moses.' The people will then go to Moses and say, 'O Moses! You art Allah's Apostle and Allah gave you superiority above the others with this message and with His direct Talk to you; (please) intercede for us with your Lord Don't you see in what state we are?' Moses will say, 'My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before, nor will become thereafter, I killed a person whom I had not been ordered to kill. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Jesus.' So they will go to Jesus and say, 'O Jesus! You are Allah's Apostle and His Word which He sent to Mary, and a superior soul created by Him, and you talked to the people while still young in the cradle. Please intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see in what state we are?' Jesus will say. 'My Lord has today become angry as He has never become before nor will ever become thereafter. Jesus will not mention any sin, but will say, 'Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Muhammad.' So they will come to me and say, 'O Muhammad ! You are Allah's Apostle and the last of the prophets, and Allah forgave your early and late sins. (Please) intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see in what state we are?" The Prophet added, "Then I will go beneath Allah's Throne and fall in prostration before my Lord. And then Allah will guide me to such praises and glorification to Him as He has never guided anybody else before me. Then it will be said, 'O Muhammad Raise your head. Ask, and it will be granted. Intercede It (your intercession) will be accepted.' So I will raise my head and Say, 'My followers, O my Lord! My followers, O my Lord'. It will be said, 'O Muhammad! Let those of your followers who have no accounts, enter through such a gate of the gates of Paradise as lies on the right; and they will share the other gates with the people." The Prophet further said, "By Him in Whose Hand my soul is, the distance between every two gate-posts of Paradise is like the distance between Mecca and Busra (in Sham)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="3">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, "On the Day of Resurrection the Believers will assemble and say, 'Let us ask somebody to intercede for us with our Lord.' So they will go to Adam and say, 'You are the father of all the people, and Allah created you with His Own Hands, and ordered the angels to prostrate to you, and taught you the names of all things; so please intercede for us with your Lord, so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.' Adam will say, 'I am not fit for this (i.e. intercession for you).' Then Adam will remember his sin and feel ashamed thereof. He will say, 'Go to Noah, for he was the first Apostle, Allah sent to the inhabitants of the earth.' They will go to him and Noah will say,
'I am not fit for this undertaking.' He will remember his appeal to his Lord to do what he had no knowledge of, then he will feel ashamed thereof and will say, 'Go to the Khalil--r-Rahman (i.e. Abraham).' They will go to him and he will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking. Go to Moses, the slave to whom Allah spoke (directly) and gave him the Torah .' So they will go to him and he will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking.' and he will mention (his) killing a person who was not a killer, and so he will feel ashamed thereof before his Lord, and he will say, 'Go to Jesus, Allah's Slave, His Apostle and Allah's Word and a Spirit coming from Him. Jesus will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking, go to Muhammad the Slave of Allah whose past and future sins were forgiven by Allah.' So they will come to me and I will proceed till I will ask my Lord's Permission and I will be given permission. When I see my Lord, I will fall down in Prostration and He will let me remain in that state as long as He wishes and then I will be addressed.' (Muhammad!) Raise your head. Ask, and your request will be granted; say, and your saying will be listened to; intercede, and your intercession will be accepted.' I will raise my head and praise Allah with a saying (i.e. invocation) He will teach me, and then I will intercede. He will fix a limit for me (to intercede for) whom I will admit into Paradise. Then I will come back again to Allah, and when I see my Lord, the same thing will happen to me. And then I will intercede and Allah will fix a limit for me to intercede whom I will let into Paradise, then I will come back for the third time; and then I will come back for the fourth time, and will say, 'None remains in Hell but those whom the Quran has imprisoned (in Hell) and who have been destined to an eternal stay in Hell.' " (The compiler) Abu 'Abdullah said: 'But those whom the Qur'an has imprisoned in Hell,' refers to the Statement of Allah:
"They will dwell therein forever." (16.29)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="76" verse="570">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas:
Allah's Apostle said, "Allah will gather all the people on the Day of Resurrection and they will say, 'Let us request someone to intercede for us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.' Then they will go to Adam and say, 'You are the one whom Allah created with His Own Hands, and breathed in you of His soul, and ordered the angels to prostrate to you; so please intercede for us with our Lord.' Adam will reply, 'I am not fit for this undertaking, and will remember his sin, and will say, 'Go to Noah, the first Apostle sent by Allah' They will go to him and he will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking', and will remember his sin and say, 'Go to Abraham whom Allah took as a Khalil. They will go to him (and request similarly). He will reply, 'I am not fit for this undertaking,' and will remember his sin and say, 'Go to Moses to whom Allah spoke directly.' They will go to Moses and he will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking,' and will remember his sin and say, 'Go to Jesus.' They will go to him, and he will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking, go to Muhammad as Allah has forgiven his past and future sins.' They will come to me and I will ask my Lord's permission, and when I see Him, I will fall down in prostration to Him, and He will leave me in that state as long as (He) Allah will, and then I will be addressed. 'Raise up your head (O Muhammad)! Ask, and your request will be granted, and say, and your saying will be listened to; intercede, and your intercession will be accepted.' Then I will raise my head, and I will glorify and praise my Lord with a saying(i.e. invocation) He will teach me, and then I will intercede, Allah will fix a limit for me (i.e., certain type of people for whom I may intercede), and I will take them out of the (Hell) Fire and let them enter Paradise. Then I will come back (to Allah) and fall in prostration, and will do the same for the third and fourth times till no-one remains in the (Hell) Fire except those whom the Qur'an has imprisoned therein." (The sub-narrator, Qatada used to say at that point, "...those upon whom eternity (in Hell) has been imposed.") (See Hadith No. 3, Vol 6).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="507">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, "Allah will gather the believers on the Day of Resurrection in the same way (as they are gathered in this life), and they will say, 'Let us ask someone to intercede for us with our Lord that He may relieve us from this place of ours.' Then they will go to Adam and say, 'O Adam! Don't you see the people (people's condition)? Allah created you with His Own Hands and ordered His angels to prostrate before you, and taught you the names of all the things. Please intercede for us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.' Adam will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking' and mention to them the mistakes he had committed, and add, "But you d better go to Noah as he was the first Apostle sent by Allah to the people of the Earth.' They will go to Noah who will reply, 'I am not fit for this undertaking,' and mention the mistake which he made, and add, 'But you'd better go to Abraham, Khalil Ar-Rahman.'
They will go to Abraham who will reply, 'I am not fit for this undertaking,' and mention to them the mistakes he made, and add, 'But you'd better go to Moses, a slave whom Allah gave the Torah and to whom He spoke directly' They will go to Moses who will reply, 'I am not fit for this undertaking,' and mention to them the mistakes he made, and add, 'You'd better go to Jesus, Allah's slave and His Apostle and His Word (Be: And it was) and a soul created by Him.' They will go to Jesus who will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking, but you'd better go to Muhammad whose sins of the past and the future had been forgiven (by Allah).' So they will come to me and I will ask the permission of my Lord, and I will be permitted (to present myself) before Him. When I see my Lord, I will fall down in (prostration) before Him and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then it will be said to me, 'O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.' I will then raise my head and praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit whom I will admit into Paradise.
I will come back again, and when I see my Lord (again), I will fall down in prostration before Him, and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then He will say, 'O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.' I will then praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit to whom I will admit into Paradise, I will return again, and when I see my Lord, I will fall down (in prostration) and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He wishes, and then He will say, 'O Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted.' I will then praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit to whom I will admit into Paradise. I will come back and say, 'O my Lord! None remains in Hell (Fire) but those whom Qur'an has imprisoned therein and for whom eternity in Hell (Fire) has become inevitable.' "
The Prophet added, "There will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: 'La ilaha illal-lah,' and has in his heart good equal to the weight of a barley grain. Then there will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: ' La ilaha illal-lah,' and has in his heart good equal to the weight of a wheat grain. Then there will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: 'La ilaha illal-lah,' and has in his heart good equal to the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="532">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Ata' bin Yazid Al-Laithi:
On the authority of Abu Huraira: The people said, "O Allah's Apostle! Shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?" The Prophet said, "Do you have any difficulty in seeing the moon on a full moon night?" They said, "No, O Allah's Apostle." He said, "Do you have any difficulty in seeing the sun when there are no clouds?" They said, "No, O Allah's Apostle." He said, "So you will see Him, like that. Allah will gather all the people on the Day of Resurrection, and say, 'Whoever worshipped something (in the world) should follow (that thing),' so, whoever worshipped the sun will follow the sun, and whoever worshiped the moon will follow the moon, and whoever used to worship certain (other false) deities, he will follow those deities. And there will remain only this nation with its good people (or its hypocrites). (The sub-narrator, Ibrahim is in doubt.) Allah will come to them and say, 'I am your Lord.' They will (deny Him and) say, 'We will stay here till our Lord comes, for when our Lord comes, we will recognize Him.' So Allah will come to them in His appearance which they know, and will say, 'I am your Lord.' They will say, 'You are our Lord,' so they will follow Him.
Then a bridge will be laid across Hell (Fire)' I and my followers will be the first ones to go across it and none will speak on that Day except the Apostles. And the invocation of the Apostles on that Day will be, 'O Allah, save! Save!' In Hell (or over The Bridge) there will be hooks like the thorns of As-Sa'dan (thorny plant). Have you seen As-Sa'dan? " They replied, "Yes, O Allah's Apostle!" He said, "So those hooks look like the thorns of As-Sa'dan, but none knows how big they are except Allah. Those hooks will snap the people away according to their deeds. Some of the people will stay in Hell (be destroyed) because of their (evil) deeds, and some will be cut or torn by the hooks (and fall into Hell) and some will be punished and then relieved. When Allah has finished His Judgments among the people, He will take whomever He will out of Hell through His Mercy. He will then order the angels to take out of the Fire all those who used to worship none but Allah from among those whom Allah wanted to be merciful to and those who testified (in the world) that none has the right to be worshipped but Allah. The angels will recognize them in the Fire by the marks of prostration (on their foreheads), for the Fire will eat up all the human body except the mark caused by prostration as Allah has forbidden the Fire to eat the mark of prostration. They will come out of the (Hell) Fire, completely burnt and then the water of life will be poured over them and they will grow under it as does a seed that comes in the mud of the torrent.
Then Allah will finish the judgments among the people, and there will remain one man facing the (Hell) Fire and he will be the last person among the people of Hell to enter Paradise. He will say, 'O my Lord! Please turn my face away from the fire because its air has hurt me and its severe heat has burnt me.' So he will invoke Allah in the way Allah will wish him to invoke, and then Allah will say to him, 'If I grant you that, will you then ask for anything else?' He will reply, 'No, by Your Power, (Honor) I will not ask You for anything else.' He will give his Lord whatever promises and covenants Allah will demand.
So Allah will turn his face away from Hell (Fire). When he will face Paradise and will see it, he will remain quiet for as long as Allah will wish him to remain quiet, then he will say, 'O my Lord! Bring me near to the gate of Paradise.' Allah will say to him, 'Didn't you give your promises and covenants that you would never ask for anything more than what you had been given? Woe on you, O Adam's son! How treacherous you are!' He will say, 'O my lord,' and will keep on invoking Allah till He says to him, 'If I give what you are asking, will you then ask for anything else?' He will reply, 'No, by Your (Honor) Power, I will not ask for anything else.'
Then he will give covenants and promises to Allah and then Allah will bring him near to the gate of Paradise. When he stands at the gate of Paradise, Paradise will be opened and spread before him, and he will see its splendor and pleasures whereupon he will remain quiet as long as Allah will wish him to remain quiet, and then he will say, O my Lord! Admit me into Paradise.' Allah will say, 'Didn't you give your covenants and promises that you would not ask for anything more than what you had been given?' Allah will say, 'Woe on you, O Adam's son! How treacherous you are! '
The man will say, 'O my Lord! Do not make me the most miserable of Your creation,' and he will keep on invoking Allah till Allah will laugh because of his sayings, and when Allah will laugh because of him, He will say to him, 'Enter Paradise,' and when he will enter it, Allah will say to him, 'Wish for anything.' So he will ask his Lord, and he will wish for a great number of things, for Allah Himself will remind him to wish for certain things by saying, '(Wish for) so-and-so.' When there is nothing more to wish for, Allah will say, 'This is for you, and its equal (is for you) as well."
'Ata' bin Yazid added: Abu Sa'id Al-Khudri who was present with Abu Huraira, did not deny whatever the latter said, but when Abu Huraira said that Allah had said, "That is for you and its equal as well," Abu Sa'id Al-Khudri said, "And ten times as much, O Abu Huraira!" Abu Huraira said, "I do not remember, except his saying, 'That is for you and its equal as well.'" Abu Sa'id Al-Khudri then said, "I testify that I remember the Prophet saying, 'That is for you, and ten times as much.' ' Abu Huraira then added, "That man will be the last person of the people of Paradise to enter Paradise."
Narrated Abu Sa'id Al-Khudri:
We said, "O Allah's Apostle! Shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?" He said, "Do you have any difficulty in seeing the sun and the moon when the sky is clear?" We said, "No." He said, "So you will have no difficulty in seeing your Lord on that Day as you have no difficulty in seeing the sun and the moon (in a clear sky)." The Prophet then said, "Somebody will then announce, 'Let every nation follow what they used to worship.' So the companions of the cross will go with their cross, and the idolators (will go) with their idols, and the companions of every god (false deities) (will go) with their god, till there remain those who used to worship Allah, both the obedient ones and the mischievous ones, and some of the people of the Scripture. Then Hell will be presented to them as if it were a mirage. Then it will be said to the Jews, "What did you use to worship?' They will reply, 'We used to worship Ezra, the son of Allah.' It will be said to them, 'You are liars, for Allah has neither a wife nor a son. What do you want (now)?' They will reply, 'We want You to provide us with water.' Then it will be said to them 'Drink,' and they will fall down in Hell (instead). Then it will be said to the Christians, 'What did you use to worship?'
They will reply, 'We used to worship Messiah, the son of Allah.' It will be said, 'You are liars, for Allah has neither a wife nor a son. What: do you want (now)?' They will say, 'We want You to provide us with water.' It will be said to them, 'Drink,' and they will fall down in Hell (instead). When there remain only those who used to worship Allah (Alone), both the obedient ones and the mischievous ones, it will be said to them, 'What keeps you here when all the people have gone?' They will say, 'We parted with them (in the world) when we were in greater need of them than we are today, we heard the call of one proclaiming, 'Let every nation follow what they used to worship,' and now we are waiting for our Lord.' Then the Almighty will come to them in a shape other than the one which they saw the first time, and He will say, 'I am your Lord,' and they will say, 'You are not our Lord.' And none will speak: to Him then but the Prophets, and then it will be said to them, 'Do you know any sign by which you can recognize Him?' They will say. 'The Shin,' and so Allah will then uncover His Shin whereupon every believer will prostrate before Him and there will remain those who used to prostrate before Him just for showing off and for gaining good reputation. These people will try to prostrate but their backs will be rigid like one piece of a wood (and they will not be able to prostrate). Then the bridge will be laid across Hell." We, the companions of the Prophet said, "O Allah's Apostle! What is the bridge?'
He said, "It is a slippery (bridge) on which there are clamps and (Hooks like) a thorny seed that is wide at one side and narrow at the other and has thorns with bent ends. Such a thorny seed is found in Najd and is called As-Sa'dan. Some of the believers will cross the bridge as quickly as the wink of an eye, some others as quick as lightning, a strong wind, fast horses or she-camels. So some will be safe without any harm; some will be safe after receiving some scratches, and some will fall down into Hell (Fire). The last person will cross by being dragged (over the bridge)." The Prophet said, "You (Muslims) cannot be more pressing in claiming from me a right that has been clearly proved to be yours than the believers in interceding with Almighty for their (Muslim) brothers on that Day, when they see themselves safe.
They will say, 'O Allah! (Save) our brothers (for they) used to pray with us, fast with us and also do good deeds with us.' Allah will say, 'Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of one (gold) Dinar.' Allah will forbid the Fire to burn the faces of those sinners. They will go to them and find some of them in Hell (Fire) up to their feet, and some up to the middle of their legs. So they will take out those whom they will recognize and then they will return, and Allah will say (to them), 'Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of one half Dinar.' They will take out whomever they will recognize and return, and then Allah will say, 'Go and take out (of Hell) anyone in whose heart you find faith equal to the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant), and so they will take out all those whom they will recognize." Abu Sa'id said: If you do not believe me then read the Holy Verse:--
'Surely! Allah wrongs not even of the weight of an atom (or a smallest ant) but if there is any good (done) He doubles it.' (4.40) The Prophet added, "Then the prophets and Angels and the believers will intercede, and (last of all) the Almighty (Allah) will say, 'Now remains My Intercession. He will then hold a handful of the Fire from which He will take out some people whose bodies have been burnt, and they will be thrown into a river at the entrance of Paradise, called the water of life.
They will grow on its banks, as a seed carried by the torrent grows. You have noticed how it grows beside a rock or beside a tree, and how the side facing the sun is usually green while the side facing the shade is white. Those people will come out (of the River of Life) like pearls, and they will have (golden) necklaces, and then they will enter Paradise whereupon the people of Paradise will say, 'These are the people emancipated by the Beneficent. He has admitted them into Paradise without them having done any good deeds and without sending forth any good (for themselves).' Then it will be said to them, 'For you is what you have seen and its equivalent as well.'"
Narrated Anas:
The Prophet said, "The believers will be kept (waiting) on the Day of Resurrection so long that they will become worried and say, "Let us ask somebody to intercede far us with our Lord so that He may relieve us from our place.
Then they will go to Adam and say, 'You are Adam, the father of the people. Allah created you with His Own Hand and made you reside in His Paradise and ordered His angels to prostrate before you, and taught you the names of all things will you intercede for us with your Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours? Adam will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking.' He will mention his mistakes he had committed, i.e., his eating off the tree though he had been forbidden to do so. He will add, 'Go to Noah, the first prophet sent by Allah to the people of the Earth.' The people will go to Noah who will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking' He will mention his mistake which he had done, i.e., his asking his Lord without knowledge.' He will say (to them), 'Go to Abraham, Khalil Ar-Rahman.' They will go to Abraham who will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking. He would mention three words by which he told a lie, and say (to them). 'Go to Moses, a slave whom Allah gave the Torah and spoke to, directly and brought near Him, for conversation.'
They will go to Moses who will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking. He will mention his mistake he made, i.e., killing a person, and will say (to them), 'Go to Jesus, Allah's slave and His Apostle, and a soul created by Him and His Word.' (Be: And it was.) They will go to Jesus who will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking but you'd better go to Muhammad the slave whose past and future sins have been forgiven by Allah.' So they will come to me, and I will ask my Lord's permission to enter His House and then I will be permitted. When I see Him I will fall down in prostration before Him, and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He will, and then He will say, 'O Muhammad, lift up your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask (for anything) for it will be granted:' Then I will raise my head and glorify my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me. Allah will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people) I will take them out and make them enter Paradise." (Qatada said: I heard Anas saying that), the Prophet said, "I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, and then I will return and ask my Lord for permission to enter His House and I will be permitted.
When I will see Him I will fall down in prostration before Him and He will leave me in prostration as long as He will let me (in that state), and then He will say, 'O Muhammad, raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask, your request will be granted.' " The Prophet added, "So I will raise my head and glorify and praise Him as He has taught me. Then I will intercede and He will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people). I will take them out and let them enter Paradise." (Qatada added: I heard Anas saying that) the Prophet said, 'I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, and I will return for the third time and will ask my Lord for permission to enter His house, and I will be allowed to enter.
When I see Him, I will fall down in prostration before Him, and will remain in prostration as long as He will, and then He will say, 'Raise your head, O Muhammad, and speak, for you will be listened to, and intercede, for your intercession will be accepted, and ask, for your request will be granted.' So I will raise my head and praise Allah as He has taught me and then I will intercede and He will put a limit for me (to intercede for a certain type of people). I will take them out and let them enter Paradise." (Qatada said: I heard Anas saying that) the Prophet said, "So I will go out and take them out of Hell (Fire) and let them enter Paradise, till none will remain in the Fire except those whom Quran will imprison (i.e., those who are destined for eternal life in the fire)." The narrator then recited the Verse:-- "It may be that your Lord will raise you to a Station of Praise and Glory.' (17.79) The narrator added: This is the Station of Praise and Glory which Allah has promised to your Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>