<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="sulayman" generated="2026-03-30T00:16:23.053Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story of Solomon (Sulayman)</title>
    <verses_count>53</verses_count>
    <translations_count>753</translations_count>
    <reordered>2026-03-30T00:16:23.072Z</reordered>
    <reorder_source>sulayman_reorder.csv</reorder_source>
  </metadata>
  <verses>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="84">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided them, as We had guided Noah before them, and of his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus We reward those who are upright and do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob); We guided all of them; and We guided Nooh before them and of his descendants, Dawud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Moosa and Haroon; and this is the way We reward the virtuous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave to him Isaac and Jacob -- each one We guided, And Noah We guided before; and of his seed David and Solomon, Job and Joseph, Moses and Aaron -- even so We recompense the good-doers --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Is-haq and Ya'qub: each one We guided. And Nuh We had guided afore, and of his progeny Da-ud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Musa and Harun. And thus We recompense the well-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob), each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh (Noah), and among his progeny Dawud (David), Sulaiman (Solomon), Ayub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses), and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob—each of them We guided. And We guided Noah previously; and from his descendants David, and Solomon, and Job, and Joseph, and Moses, and Aaron. Thus We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon Abraham (offspring) Ishaq (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob) and each of them did We guide to the right way as We had earlier guided Noah to the right way; and (of his descendants We guided) Da'ud (David) and Sulayman (Solomon), Ayyub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses) and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward those who do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq and Ya`qub, each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh and among his progeny Dawud, Sulayman, Ayyub, Yusuf, Musa, and Harun. Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Isaac and Jacob; each of them We guided; and Noah did We guide aforetime; and of his seed (We guided) David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided both; and We guided Noah before them, among his descendants were David and Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron as such, We recompense the gooddoers,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob - all [of them] We guided. And Noah, We guided before; and among his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave (Abraham) Isaac and Jacob. Both had received Our guidance. Noah received Our guidance before Abraham and so did his descendants: David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron. Thus is the reward for the righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave to him Ishaq and Yaqoub; each did We guide, and Nuh did We guide before, and of his descendants, Dawood and Sulaiman and Ayub and Yusuf and Musa and Haroun; and thus do We reward those who do good (to others).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob, each of whom We guided as We had guided Noah before. Among his descendants were David and Solomon, and Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob: all (three) guided: and before him, We guided Noah, and among his progeny, David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron: thus do We reward those who do good:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="30">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We bestowed Solomon on David who was an excellent devotee, for he turned to God in penitence.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed Sulaiman to Dawud; what an excellent bondman! He is indeed most inclined.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave unto David Solomon; how excellent a servant he was! He was a penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We vouchsafed Unto Da-ud Sulaiman. How excellent a bondman! j Verily he was oft-returning.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And to Dawud (David) We gave Sulaiman (Solomon). How excellent (a) slave! Verily, he was ever oft-returning in repentance (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We granted David, Solomon, an excellent servant. He was penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We bestowed upon David (an illustrious son), Solomon. How excellent a servant (of Ours he was)! Indeed he constantly turned to Us in devotion.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And to Dawud We gave Sulayman. How excellent a servant! Verily, he was ever turning in repentance (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed on David, Solomon. How excellent a slave! Lo! he was ever turning in repentance (toward Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave Solomon to David; and he was an excellent worshiper, he was penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And to David We gave Solomon. An excellent servant, indeed he was one repeatedly turning back [to Allah].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We granted Solomon to David, a blessed servant of Ours and certainly the most repentant person.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave to Dawood Sulaiman, most excellent the servant! Surely he was frequent in returning (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave David Solomon. He was an excellent servant who always turned to God.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>To David We gave Solomon (for a son),- How excellent in Our service! Ever did he turn (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="163">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We have sent revelations to you as We sent revelations to Noah and the prophets (who came) after him; and We sent revelations to Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob, and their offspring, and to Jesus and Job, and to Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and to David We gave the Book of Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed We sent a divine revelation to you (Prophet Mohammed – peace and blessing be upon him) as We did send divine revelations to Nooh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; and We sent divine revelations to Ibrahim (Abraham) and Ismael (Ishmael) and Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob) and their offspring, and Eisa (Jesus) and Ayyub (Job) and Yunus (Jonah) and Haroon (Aaron) and Sulaiman (Solomon), and We bestowed the Zaboor (the Holy Book) upon Dawud (David).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We have revealed to thee as We revealed to Noah, and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, Jesus and Job, Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We have revealed unto thee even as We revealed unto Nuh and the prophets after him, and as We revealed unto Ibrahim and Isma'il and Is-haq and Ya'qub and the tribes, and 'Isa and Ayyub and Yunus and Harun and Sulaiman, and unto Daud We vouchsafed a Scripture.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, We have inspired you (O Muhammad SAW) as We inspired Nuh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; We (also) inspired Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma'il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya'qub (Jacob), and Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya'qub (Jacob)], 'Iesa (Jesus), Ayub (Job), Yunus (Jonah), Harun (Aaron), and Sulaiman (Solomon), and to Dawud (David) We gave the Zabur (Psalms).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We have inspired you, as We had inspired Noah and the prophets after him. And We inspired Abraham, and Ishmael, and Isaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs, and Jesus, and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron, and Solomon. And We gave David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(O Muhammad!) We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the offspring of Jacob, and Jesus and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, We have sent the revelation to you as We sent the revelation to Nuh and the Prophets after him; We (also) sent the revelation to Ibrahim, Isma`il, Ishaq, Ya`qub, and Al-Asbat, (the offspring of the twelve sons of Ya`qub) `Isa, Ayyub, Yunus, Harun, and Sulayman; and to Dawud We gave the Zabur.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! We inspire thee as We inspired Noah and the prophets after him, as We inspired Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob and the tribes, and Jesus and Job and Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and as We imparted unto David the Psalms;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and to the Prophets after him, and We revealed to (Prophets) Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the tribes, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and We gave to David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, We have revealed to you, [O Muhammad], as We revealed to Noah and the prophets after him. And we revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, the Descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and to David We gave the book [of Psalms].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), We have sent revelations to you just as were sent to Noah and the Prophets who lived after him and to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, his descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon. We gave the Psalms to David.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely We have revealed to you as We revealed to Nuh, and the prophets after him, and We revealed to Ibrahim and Ismail and Ishaq and Yaqoub and the tribes, and Isa and Ayub and Yunus and Haroun and Sulaiman and We gave to Dawood</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We have sent revelation to you [Prophet] as We did to Noah and the prophets who came after him, to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon and David, to whom We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We have sent thee inspiration, as We sent it to Noah and the Messengers after him: we sent inspiration to Abraham, Isma'il, Isaac, Jacob and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and solomon, and to David We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="78">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Remember) David and Solomon, when they pronounced judgement about the field which was eaten up at night by sheep belonging to certain people. We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Dawud and Sulaiman, when they were deciding the dispute of a field, when some people’s sheep had strayed into it at night; and We were Present at the time of their deciding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And David and Solomon -- when they gave judgment concerning the tillage, when the sheep of the people strayed there, and We bore witness to their judgment;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Daud and Sulaiman! recall what time they gave judgment regarding the tillage when certain people's sheep had pastured therein at night; and of the judgment concerning them We were the Witnesses.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) Dawud (David) and Sulaiman (Solomon), when they gave judgement in the case of the field in which the sheep of certain people had pastured at night and We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And David and Solomon, when they gave judgment in the case of the field, when some people’s sheep wandered therein by night; and We were witnesses to their judgment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We bestowed the same favour upon David and Solomon. Recall, when they gave judgement regarding a tillage into which the sheep of some people had strayed at night, and We were witnesses to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) Dawud and Sulayman, when they gave judgement in the case of the field in which the sheep of certain people had Nafashat; and We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And David and Solomon, when they gave judgment concerning the field, when people's sheep had strayed and browsed therein by night; and We were witnesses to their judgment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And David and Solomon they passed judgment upon the tilled land on which the people? s sheep had strayed. We bore witness to their judgment, and</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] David and Solomon, when they judged concerning the field - when the sheep of a people overran it [at night], and We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>David and Solomon were trying to settle the case of the people's sheep that grazed in a corn-field at night. We witnessed their decree in that matter.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Dawood and Sulaiman when they gave judgment concerning the field when the people's sheep pastured therein by night, and We were bearers of witness to their judgment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Tell of David and Solomon who both passed judgement on the field into which some people's sheep had strayed [and grazed] at night. We bore witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And remember David and Solomon, when they gave judgment in the matter of the field into which the sheep of certain people had strayed by night: We did witness their judgment.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="79">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We made Solomon understand the case, and bestowed on each wisdom and knowledge, We subdued the al-jibal (mountains) with David to sing Our praises, and at-tair (birds). It is We who did it.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We explained the case to Sulaiman; and to both We gave the kingdom and knowledge; and subjected the hills to proclaim the Purity along with Dawud, and (also subjected) the birds; and these were Our works.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and We made Solomon to understand it, and unto each gave We judgment and knowledge. And with David We subjected the mountains to give glory, and the birds, and We were doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>So We gave the understanding thereof unto Sulaiman; and unto each We vouchsafed judgment and knowledge. And We so subjected the mountains that they shall hallow us along with Daud, and also the birds; and We were the doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We made Sulaiman (Solomon) to understand (the case), and to each of them We gave Hukman (right judgement of the affairs and Prophethood) and knowledge. And We subjected the mountains and the birds to glorify Our Praises along with Dawud (David), And it was We Who were the doers (of all these things).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And so We made Solomon understand it, and to each We gave wisdom and knowledge. And We subjected the mountains along with David to sing Our praises, and the birds as well—surely We did.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We guided Solomon to the right verdict, and We had granted each of them judgement and knowledge. We made the mountains and the birds celebrate the praise of Allah with David. It was We Who did all this.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We made Sulayman to understand (the case); and to each of them We gave wisdom (Hukm) and knowledge. And We subjected the mountains and the birds to glorify Our praises along with Dawud. And it was We Who were the doer (of all these things).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We made Solomon to understand (the case); and unto each of them We gave judgment and knowledge. And we subdued the hills and the birds to hymn (His) praise along with David. We were the doers (thereof).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We made Solomon to understand it, and to both We gave judgment and knowledge. And with David We subjected the mountains and birds to exalt (Allah). All this We have done.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave understanding of the case to Solomon, and to each [of them] We gave judgement and knowledge. And We subjected the mountains to exalt [Us], along with David and [also] the birds. And We were doing [that].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made Solomon understand the law about the case and gave both David and Solomon knowledge and wisdom. We made the mountains and birds glorify the Lord along with David. We had also done to him such favors before.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So We made Sulaiman to understand it; and to each one We gave wisdom and knowledge; and We made the mountains, and the birds to celebrate Our praise with Dawood; and We were the doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave Solomon the right understanding of the matter, and We bestowed wisdom and knowledge on both of them. We caused the mountains and the birds to celebrate Our praises along with David. We had the power to do this --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>To Solomon We inspired the (right) understanding of the matter: to each (of them) We gave Judgment and Knowledge; it was Our power that made the hills and the birds celebrate Our praises, with David: it was We Who did (all these things).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="15">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We gave David and Solomon knowledge; and they said: "All praise be to God who has favoured us over many of His creatures who believe."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We indeed bestowed great knowledge to Dawud and Sulaiman; and they both said, “All praise is to Allah, Who bestowed us superiority over many of His believing bondmen.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave David and Solomon knowledge and they said, 'Praise belongs to God who has preferred us over many of His believing servants.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We vouchsafed unto Daud and Sulaiman a knowledge, and the twain said: praise unto Allah Who hath preferred us above many of His believing bondmen!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We gave knowledge to Dawud (David) and Sulaiman (Solomon), and they both said: "All the praises and thanks be to Allah, Who has preferred us above many of His believing slaves!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave David and Solomon knowledge. They said, “Praise God, who has favored us over many of His believing servants.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(On the other hand), We granted knowledge to David and Solomon and they said: "All praise be to Allah Who has exalted us above many of His believing servants!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed We gave knowledge to Dawud and Sulayman, and they both said: "All praise be to Allah, Who has preferred us above many of His believing servants!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We verily gave knowledge unto David and Solomon, and they said: Praise be to Allah, Who hath preferred us above many of His believing slaves!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave knowledge to David and Solomon. They said: 'Praise be to Allah who has preferred us above many of His believing worshipers'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We had certainly given to David and Solomon knowledge, and they said, "Praise [is due] to Allah, who has favored us over many of His believing servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave knowledge to David and Soloman. They said, "It is only God who deserves all praise. He has exalted us above many of His believing servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We gave knowledge to Dawood and Sulaiman, and they both said: Praise be to Allah, Who has made us to excel many of His believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We bestowed knowledge on David and Solomon and they both said, "Praise be to God who has exalted us above many of His believing servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We gave (in the past) knowledge to David and Solomon: And they both said: "Praise be to Allah, Who has favoured us above many of his servants who believe!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="16">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Solomon was heir to David, and he said: "O people, we have been taught the language of Tair, and have been given of everything. This is a clear favour indeed."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And Sulaiman became Dawud’s heir; and he said, “O people, we have indeed been taught the language of birds, and have been given from all things; this surely is a manifest favour.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Solomon was David's heir, and he said, 'Men, we have been taught the speech of the birds, and we have been given of everything; surely this is indeed the manifest bounty.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Sulaiman inherited from Daud. And he said: O mankind! verily have been taught the diction of we birds, and we have been vcuchsafed of every thing; and verily this is grace manifest.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And Sulaiman (Solomon) inherited (the knowledge of) Dawud (David). He said: "O mankind! We have been taught the language of birds, and on us have been bestowed all things. This, verily, is an evident grace (from Allah)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Solomon succeeded David. He said, “O people, we were taught the language of birds, and we were given from everything. This is indeed a real blessing.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And Solomon succeeded David and said: "O people, we have been taught the speech of birds and we have been endowed with all kinds of things. Surely this is a conspicuous favour (from Allah)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And Sulayman inherited from Dawud. He said: "O mankind! We have been taught the language of birds, and we have been given from everything. This, verily, is an evident grace."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Solomon was David's heir. And he said: O mankind! Lo! we have been taught the language of birds, and have been given (abundance) of all things. This surely is evident favour.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Solomon inherited David. He said: 'Know, my people, we have been taught the speech of birds and given everything. Surely, this is a clear bounty'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Solomon inherited David. He said, "O people, we have been taught the language of birds, and we have been given from all things. Indeed, this is evident bounty."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Solomon became the heir to David. He said, "People, we have been taught the language of the birds and have been granted a share of everything. This indeed is a manifest favor (from God)".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Sulaiman was Dawood's heir, and he said: O men! we have been taught the language of birds, and we have been given all things; most surely this is manifest grace.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Solomon succeeded David. He said, "Know, my people, that we have been taught the speech of birds and endowed with all good things. Surely this is God's manifest grace."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And Solomon was David's heir. He said: "O ye people! We have been taught the speech of birds, and on us has been bestowed (a little) of all things: this is indeed Grace manifest (from Allah.)"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="80" verse="760">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah's Apostle said, "There were two women with whom there were their two sons. A wolf came and took away the son of one of them. That lady said to her companion, 'The wolf has taken your son.' The other said, 'But it has taken your son.' So both of them sought the judgment of (the Prophet) David who judged that the boy should be given to the older lady. Then both of them went to (the Prophet) Solomon, son of David and informed him of the case. Solomon said, 'Give me a knife so that I may cut the child into two portions and give one half to each of you.' The younger lady said, 'Do not do so; may Allah bless you ! He is her child.' On that, he gave the child to the younger lady." Abu Huraira added: By Allah! I had never heard the word 'Sakkin' as meaning knife, except on that day, for we used to call it 'Mudya"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="12">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We (subjugated) the wind to Solomon. Its morning's journey took one month, and the evening's one month. We made a spring of molten brass to flow for him; and many jinns laboured for him by the will of his Lord. Anyone of them who turned from Our command was made to taste the torment of blazing fire.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We gave the wind in Sulaiman’s control – its morning journey equal to a month’s course and the evening journey equal to a month’s course; and We sprung a stream of molten copper for him; and from the jinns, who worked before him by the command of his Lord; and those among them who turned away from Our command – We shall make them taste the punishment of the blazing fire.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And to Solomon the wind; its morning course was a month's journey, and its evening course was a month's journey. And We made the Fount of Molten Brass to flow for him. And of the jinn, some worked before him by the leave of his Lord; and such of them as swerved away from Our commandment, We would let them taste the chastisement of the Blaze;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Unto Sulaiman We subjected the wind, whereof the morning journeying was a month and the evening journeying a month. And We made a fount of brass to flow for him. And of the Jinn were some who worked before him by the Will Of his Lord. And whosoever of them swerved from Our command, him We shall cause to taste the torment of the Blaze.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And to Solomon (We subjected) the wind, its morning (stride from sunrise till midnoon) was a month's (journey), and its afternoon (stride from the midday decline of the sun to sunset) was a month's (journey i.e. in one day he could travel two months' journey). And We caused a fount of (molten) brass to flow for him, and there were jinns that worked in front of him, by the Leave of his Lord, and whosoever of them turned aside from Our Command, We shall cause him to taste of the torment of the blazing Fire.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And for Solomon the wind—its outward journey was one month, and its return journey was one month. And We made a spring of tar flow for him. And there were sprites that worked under him, by the leave of his Lord. But whoever of them swerved from Our command, We make him taste of the punishment of the Inferno.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We subdued the wind to Solomon: its morning course was a month's journey and its evening course was a month's journey. We gave him a spring flowing with molten brass, and We subdued for him jinn who, by his Lord's permission, worked before him. Such of them as swerved from Our commandment, We let them taste the chastisement of the Blazing Fire.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And to Sulayman (We subjected) the wind, its morning was a month's (journey), and its afternoon was a month's (journey). And We caused a fount of Qitr to flow for him, and there were Jinn that worked in front of him, by the leave of his Lord. And whosoever of them turned aside from Our command, We shall cause him to taste of the torment of the blazing Fire.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And unto Solomon (We gave) the wind, whereof the morning course was a month's journey and the evening course a month's journey, and We caused the fount of copper to gush forth for him, and (We gave him) certain of the jinn who worked before him by permission of his Lord. And such of them as deviated from Our command, them We caused to taste the punishment of flaming Fire.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>To Solomon the morning course of the wind was a month's journey, and its evening course was also a month's journey. We caused copper to be (as a) molten spring for him. And the jinn, some served him by the permission of his Lord. But as for those amongst them that swerved away from Our Command, We shall let them taste the punishment of the Blaze (the Fire).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And to Solomon [We subjected] the wind - its morning [journey was that of] a month - and its afternoon [journey was that of] a month, and We made flow for him a spring of [liquid] copper. And among the jinn were those who worked for him by the permission of his Lord. And whoever deviated among them from Our command - We will make him taste of the punishment of the Blaze.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(We made subservient to) Solomon the wind that travelled a month's journey in the morning and a month's journey in the evening. We made a stream of brass flow for him and some of the jinn worked for him by his Lord's command. We would make whichever of them (jinn) who turned away from Our command to suffer a burning torment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And (We made) the wind (subservient) to Sulaiman, which made a month's journey in the morning and a month's journey in the evening, and We made a fountain of molten copper to flow out for him, and of the jinn there were those who worked before him by the command of his Lord; and whoever turned aside from Our command from among them, We made him taste of the punishment of burning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We subjected the wind to Solomon; its morning course was a month and its evening course a month; and We caused a fount of molten copper to flow for him. And of the jinn there were some who worked under him, by the command of his Lord. If any one of them turned away from Our command, We would make him taste the punishment of the burning fire.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And to Solomon (We made) the Wind (obedient): Its early morning (stride) was a month's (journey), and its evening (stride) was a month's (journey); and We made a Font of molten brass to flow for him; and there were Jinns that worked in front of him, by the leave of his Lord, and if any of them turned aside from our command, We made him taste of the Penalty of the Blazing Fire.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="36">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So we subjugated the wind to his service which carried his merchandise wheresoever he wished;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>We therefore gave the wind under his control, moving steadily by his command wherever he wished.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So We subjected to him the wind, that ran at his commandment, softly, wherever he might light on,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then We subjected to him the wind: it ran gently by his command withersoever he directed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So, We subjected to him the wind, it blew gently to his order whithersoever he willed,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>So We placed the wind at his service, blowing gently by his command, wherever he directed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We subjected the wind to him, so that it blew gently at his bidding, wherever he directed it,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So, We subjected to him the wind; it blew gently by his order wherever he willed,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>So We made the wind subservient unto him, setting fair by his command whithersoever he intended.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>So We subjected the wind to him, so that it ran softly by his command wherever he wished;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So We subjected to him the wind blowing by his command, gently, wherever he directed,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made the wind subservient to him, to blow gently wherever he desired at his command</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Then We made the wind subservient to him; it made his command to run gently wherever he desired,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Then We subjected the wind to his power, so that it blew gently, at his behest, wherever he willed,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Then We subjected the wind to his power, to flow gently to his order, Whithersoever he willed,-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="37">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And the devils -- the builders and divers of all kinds,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And made the demons subservient to him, all builders and divers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and the Satans, every builder and diver</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We subjected to him the evil ones: every builder and diver.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And also the Shayatin (devils) from the jinns (including) every kind of builder and diver,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And the demons—every builder and diver.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and We also subjected the devils to him -- all kinds of builders and divers;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And the Shayatin, from every kind of builder and diver,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And the unruly, every builder and diver (made We subservient),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and the satans, every builder and diver</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [also] the devils [of jinn] - every builder and diver</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>and all the devils who built and dived for him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And the shaitans, every builder and diver,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and also the jinn, every kind of builder and diver</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>As also the evil ones, (including) every kind of builder and diver,-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="81">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We made tempestuous winds obedient to Solomon which blew swiftly to sail at his bidding (with his ships) to the land We had blessed. We are cognisant of everything.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We subjected the fast wind for Sulaiman, which moved by his command towards the land in which We have placed blessings; and We know everything.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And to Solomon the wind, strongly blowing, that ran at his command unto the land that We had blessed; and We had knowledge of everything;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And unto Sulaiman We subjected the wind, strongly raging, running at his command toward the land wherein We had placed Our blessing; and of evrything We are the knowers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And to Sulaiman (Solomon) (We subjected) the wind strongly raging, running by his command towards the land which We had blessed. And of everything We are the All-Knower.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And to Solomon the stormy wind, blowing at His command towards the land that We have blessed. We are aware of everything.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We subdued the strongly raging wind to Solomon which blew at his bidding towards the land We blessed. We know everything.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And to Sulayman (We subjected) the wind strongly raging, running by his command towards the land which We had blessed. And of everything We are the All-Knower.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And unto Solomon (We subdued) the wind in its raging. It set by his command toward the land which We had blessed. And of everything We are Aware.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>To Solomon the raging wind ran at his command to the land which We had blessed. We have knowledge of all things.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And to Solomon [We subjected] the wind, blowing forcefully, proceeding by his command toward the land which We had blessed. And We are ever, of all things, Knowing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made subservient to Solomon the swift wind that blew on his command to the land in which We had sent blessings. We have the knowledge of all things.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And (We made subservient) to Sulaiman the wind blowing violent, pursuing its course by his command to the land which We had blessed, and We are knower of all things.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We subjected to Solomon the stormy wind, which blew at his behest towards the land which We had blessed. For it is We who have knowledge of all things --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(It was Our power that made) the violent (unruly) wind flow (tamely) for Solomon, to his order, to the land which We had blessed: for We do know all things.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="82">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And many of the devils (We also made obedient to him) who dived for him, and did many other things; and We kept watch over them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And among the devils, were those who dived (in water) for him and did works other than this; and We had kept them restrained.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and of the Satans some dived for him and did other work besides; and We were watching over them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And of the satans were some who dove for him, and worked a work beside that; and of them We were the Watchers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And of the Shayatin (devils) (from the jinns) were some who dived for him, and did other work besides that; and it was We Who guarded them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And of the devils were some that dived for him, and performed other, lesser tasks. But We kept them restrained.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We subdued many devils who dived (into the sea) for him and carried out other jobs besides that. We kept watch over all of them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And of the Shayatin were some who dived for him, and did other work besides that; and it was We Who guarded them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And of the evil ones (subdued We unto him) some who dived (for pearls) for him and did other work, and We were warders unto them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And some of the satans dived for him and others did work as well. We were watching over them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And of the devils were those who dived for him and did work other than that. And We were of them a guardian.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We subdued the devils who would dive into the sea for him and perform other tasks for Solomon. We kept them in his service.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And of the rebellious people there were those who dived for him and did other work besides that, and We kept guard over them;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We also subjected to him some of the jinn who dived for him in the sea and performed other tasks; We kept a watch over them.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And of the evil ones, were some who dived for him, and did other work besides; and it was We Who guarded them.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="13">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>They made for him whatever he wished, synagogues and statues, dishes large as water-troughs, and cauldrons firmly fixed (on ovens; and We said): "O House of David, act, and give thanks." But few among My creatures are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>They made for him whatever he wished – synagogues and statues, basins like ponds, and large pots built into the ground; “Be thankful, O the people of Dawud!” And few among My bondmen are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>fashioning for him whatsoever he would -- places of worship, statues, porringers like water-troughs, and anchored cooking-pots. 'Labour, O House of David, in thankfulness; for few indeed are those that are thankful among My servants.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>They worked for him whatsoever he pleased, of lofty halls and statues and basins like cisterns and cauldrons Standing firm. Work ye, house of Da'ud! with thanksgiving; few of My bondmen are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They worked for him what he desired, (making) high rooms, images, basins as large as reservoirs, and (cooking) cauldrons fixed (in their places). "Work you, O family of Dawud (David), with thanks!" But few of My slaves are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>They made for him whatever he wished: sanctuaries, statues, bowls like pools, and heavy cauldrons. “O House of David, work with appreciation,” but a few of My servants are appreciative.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>They made for him whatever he would desire: stately buildings, images, basins like water-troughs and huge, built-in-cauldrons: “Work, O house of David, in thankfulness (to your Lord). Few of My servants are truly thankful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They worked for him as he desired on Maharib, Tamathil, large basins like Jawab and Qudur Rasiyat. "Work you, O family of Dawud, with thanks!" But few of My servants are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>They made for him what he willed: synagogues and statues, basins like wells and boilers built into the ground. Give thanks, O House of David! Few of My bondmen are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>They made for him whatever he wanted, arches, statues, bowls as basins, and fixed cauldrons. (We said:) 'Give thanks, House of David and work' Yet only a few of My worshipers are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>They made for him what he willed of elevated chambers, statues, bowls like reservoirs, and stationary kettles. [We said], "Work, O family of David, in gratitude." And few of My servants are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They would make for him anything that he wanted like fortresses, statues, large basins like reservoirs, and huge immovable cooking pots. It was said, "Family of David, worship and act gratefully. Only few of my servants are grateful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>They made for him what he pleased of fortresses and images, and bowls (large) as watering-troughs and cooking-pots that will not move from their place; give thanks, O family of Dawood! and very few of My servants are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They made for him whatever he desired: palaces and statues, basins like reservoirs, and large cooking vessels fixed in their places. We said, "Give thanks, house of David, for few of My servants are truly grateful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They worked for him as he desired, (making) arches, images, basons as large as reservoirs, and (cooking) cauldrons fixed (in their places): "Work ye, sons of David, with thanks! but few of My servants are grateful!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="38">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And many others bound in bond.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And other demons bound in chains.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and others also, coupled in fetters:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And others bound in fetters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And also others bound in fetters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And others fettered in chains.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and others that were bound with chains.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And also others bound in fetters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And others linked together in chains,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and others joined together by (iron) fetters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And others bound together in shackles.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The rest of the devils were bound in chains.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And others fettered in chains.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and others chained in fetters.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>As also others bound together in fetters.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="39">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"This is Our gift," (We said to him), "so bestow freely or withhold without reckoning."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“This is Our bestowal – you may therefore bestow favours or withhold them – you will not be questioned.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>'This is Our gift; bestow or withhold without reckoning.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>This is Our gift, SO bestow thou or withhold, without rendering an account.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>[Saying of Allah to Sulaiman (Solomon)]: "This is Our gift, so spend you or withhold, no account will be asked."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“This is Our gift; so give generously, or withhold; without account.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>“This is Our bestowal. So give or withhold as you wish without account.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>[Allah said to Sulayman]: "This is Our gift, so spend you or withhold, no account will be asked of you."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>(Saying): This is Our gift, so bestow thou, or withhold, without reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>'This is Our gift, give or withhold without reckoning'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[We said], "This is Our gift, so grant or withhold without account."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We told him, "This is Our gift to you so give them away free or keep them as you like".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>This is Our free gift, therefore give freely or withhold, without reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We said: "This is Our gift, so give or withhold as you wish without reckoning."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Such are Our Bounties: whether thou bestow them (on others) or withhold them, no account will be asked."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="17">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>His armies of jinns and men and Tair assembled, formed into ranks, (and marched)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And assembled together for Sulaiman were his armies of jinns and men, and of birds – so they had to be restricted.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And his hosts were mustered to Solomon, jinn, men and birds, duly disposed;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And there were gathered unto Sulaiman his hosts of jinns and mankind and birds, and they were set in bands.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And there were gathered before Sulaiman (Solomon) his hosts of jinns and men, and birds, and they all were set in battle order (marching forwards).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>To the service of Solomon were mobilized his troops of sprites, and men, and birds—all held in strict order.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Hosts of jinn and humans and birds were marshalled for Solomon and were kept under full control.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And there were gathered before Sulayman his hosts of Jinn and men, and birds, and they all were set in battle order (marching forward).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And there were gathered together unto Solomon his armies of the jinn and humankind, and of the birds, and they were set in battle order;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gathered to Solomon his army of jinn, humans and birds; gathered and dispersed,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And gathered for Solomon were his soldiers of the jinn and men and birds, and they were [marching] in rows.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Soloman's army, consisting of human beings, jinn, and birds were gathered together in his presence in ranks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And his hosts of the jinn and the men and the birds were gathered to him, and they were formed into groups.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Solomon's hosts of jinn and men and birds, were all gathered together in his presence and were ranged in battle order,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And before Solomon were marshalled his hosts,- of Jinns and men and birds, and they were all kept in order and ranks.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="18">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Till they reached the Valley of Naml. Said the lady of Naml: "O Naml, go into your dwellings lest Solomon and his hordes should crush you unawares."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Until when they came to the valley of the ants, a she ant exclaimed, “O ants, enter your houses – may not Sulaiman and his armies crush you, unknowingly.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>till, when they came on the Valley of Ants, an ant said, 'Ants, enter your dwelling-places, lest Solomon and his hosts crush you, being unaware!'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Until when they came unto the valley of the ants, an ant said: O ants! enter Your habitations lest Sulaiman and his hosts crush you while they perceive not.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Till, when they came to the valley of the ants, one of the ants said: "O ants! Enter your dwellings, lest Sulaiman (Solomon) and his hosts crush you, while they perceive not."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Until, when they came upon the Valley of Ants, an ant said, “O ants! Go into your nests, lest Solomon and his troops crush you without noticing.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(Solomon was once on the move with them) until when they reached a valley of ants one of the ants said: "O ants, get into your holes, lest Solomon and his hosts crush you (under their feet) without even knowing."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Till, when they came to the valley of the ants, one of the ants said: "O ants! Enter your dwellings, lest Sulayman and his armies should crush you, while they perceive not."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Till, when they reached the Valley of the Ants, an ant exclaimed: O ants! Enter your dwellings lest Solomon and his armies crush you, unperceiving.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and when they came to the Valley of the Ants, an ant said: 'Ants, go into your dwellings lest Solomon and his army should, unknowingly, crush you'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Until, when they came upon the valley of the ants, an ant said, "O ants, enter your dwellings that you not be crushed by Solomon and his soldiers while they perceive not."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When they arrived in the valley of the ants, one ant said to the others, "Enter your dwellings lest you be carelessly crushed by Soloman and his army."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Until when they came to the valley of the Naml, a Namlite said: O Naml! enter your houses, (that) Sulaiman and his hosts may not crush you while they do not know.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and when they came to the Valley of the Ants, one ant said, "Ants! Go into your dwellings, in case Solomon and his hosts inadvertently crush you."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>At length, when they came to a (lowly) valley of ants, one of the ants said: "O ye ants, get into your habitations, lest Solomon and his hosts crush you (under foot) without knowing it."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="19">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Solomon) smiled, amused at her speech, and said: "O Lord grant me that I should be grateful for the favours You have bestowed on me and my parents, and do good things of Your pleasing; and admit me among Your righteous devotees by Your grace."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He therefore smiled beamingly at her speech*, and submitted, “My Lord, bestow me guidance so that I thank you for the favour which You bestowed upon me and my parents, and so that I may perform the good deeds which please You, and by Your mercy include me among Your bondmen who are worthy of Your proximity.” (Prophet Sulaiman heard the voice of the she ant from far away.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>But he smiled, laughing at its words, and he said, 'My Lord, dispose me that I may be thankful for Thy blessing wherewith Thou hast blessed me and my father and mother, and that I may do righteousness well-pleasing to Thee; and do Thou admit me, by Thy mercy, amongst Thy righteous servants.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>So he smiled, amused at her speech, and said: my Lord! arouse me that I should be thankful for Thy favour wherewith Thou hast favoured me and my parents, and that I should work righteously pleasing Thee, and out of Thy mercy enter me among Thine righteous bondmen.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So he [Sulaiman (Solomon)] smiled, amused at her speech and said: "My Lord! Inspire and bestow upon me the power and ability that I may be grateful for Your Favours which You have bestowed on me and on my parents, and that I may do righteous good deeds that will please You, and admit me by Your Mercy among Your righteous slaves."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He smiled and laughed at her words, and said, “My Lord, direct me to be thankful for the blessings you have bestowed upon me and upon my parents, and to do good works that please You. And admit me, by Your grace, into the company of Your virtuous servants.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Smiling at the ant's utterance, Solomon burst into laughter and said: "My Lord! Hold me under (Your) control that I may render thanks for the favour which You have bestowed on me and on my parents, and that I may act righteously in a manner that would please You. Include me, out of Your Mercy, among Your righteous servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So he (Sulayman) smiled, amused at her speech and said: "My Lord! Grant me the power and ability that I may be grateful for Your favors which You have bestowed on me and on my parents, and that I may do righteous good deeds that will please You, and admit me by Your mercy among Your righteous servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (Solomon) smiled, laughing at her speech, and said: My Lord, arouse me to be thankful for Thy favour wherewith Thou hast favoured me and my parents, and to do good that shall be pleasing unto Thee, and include me in (the number of) Thy righteous slaves.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He smiled, and laughed at its words, and said: 'My Lord, inspire me that I should be thankful for Your blessing with which You have blessed me and my parents, and that I may do good works that will please You. Admit me, by Your Mercy, among Your righteous worshipers'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So [Solomon] smiled, amused at her speech, and said, "My Lord, enable me to be grateful for Your favor which You have bestowed upon me and upon my parents and to do righteousness of which You approve. And admit me by Your mercy into [the ranks of] Your righteous servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Solomon) smiled at the ant's remarks and said, "Lord, inspire me to thank you for Your favors to me and my parents and to act righteously so as to please you. Admit me, by your mercy into the company of Your righteous servants".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So he smiled, wondering at her word, and said: My Lord! grant me that I should be grateful for Thy favor which Thou hast bestowed on me and on my parents, and that I should do good such as Thou art pleased with, and make me enter, by Thy mercy, into Thy servants, the good ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Solomon smiled broadly at its words and said, "Lord, inspire me to be thankful for the blessings You have granted me and my parents, and to do good deeds that please You; and include me, by Your grace, among Your righteous servants!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So he smiled, amused at her speech; and he said: "O my Lord! so order me that I may be grateful for Thy favours, which thou hast bestowed on me and on my parents, and that I may work the righteousness that will please Thee: And admit me, by Thy Grace, to the ranks of Thy righteous Servants."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="20">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When he reviewed the Tair, he said: "How is it I do not see Hud-hud? Is he absent?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And he surveyed the birds – he therefore said, “What is to me that I do not see the Hudhud (hoopoe), or is he really absent?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And he reviewed the birds; then he said, 'How is it with me, that I do not see the hoopoe? Or is he among the absent?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And he sought after the birds and said: what aileth me that I see not the hoopoe; is he among the absentees?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He inspected the birds, and said: "What is the matter that I see not the hoopoe? Or is he among the absentees?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then he inspected the birds, and said, “Why do I not see the hoopoe? Or is he among the absentees?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(On another occasion) Solomon inspected the birds and said: "Why is it that I do not see the hoopoe? Is he among the absentees?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He inspected the birds, and said: "What is the matter that I see not the hoopoe Or is he among the absentees"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And he sought among the birds and said: How is it that I see not the hoopoe, or is he among the absent?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He reviewed the birds and said: 'Why is it that I do not see the hoopoe here? Or is he among the absent?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And he took attendance of the birds and said, "Why do I not see the hoopoe - or is he among the absent?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Solomon) inspected the birds and said, "How is it that I cannot see the hoopoe. Is he absent?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And he reviewed the birds, then said: How is it I see not the hoopoe or is it that he is of the absentees?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Then Solomon inspected the birds, and said, "How is it that I do not see the hoopoe? Is he absent then?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And he took a muster of the Birds; and he said: "Why is it I see not the Hoopoe? Or is he among the absentees?</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="21">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>I will punish him severely, or cut his throat, unless he bring a valid excuse."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“I will indeed punish him severely or slay him, or he must bring to me some clear evidence.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Assuredly I will chastise him with a terrible chastisement, or I will slaughter him, or he bring me a clear authority.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Surely I shall torment him with a severe torment, or I shall slaughter him, unless he bringeth unto me a warranty manifest.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"I will surely punish him with a severe torment, or slaughter him, unless he brings me a clear reason."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>I will punish him most severely, or slay him, unless he gives me a valid excuse.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>I will inflict a severe punishment on him or maybe even slaughter him unless he comes forth with a convincing reason (for his absence)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"I will surely punish him with a severe torment or slaughter him, unless he brings me a clear reason."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>I verily will punish him with hard punishment or I verily will slay him, or he verily shall bring me a plain excuse.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Surely, I will punish him with a terrible punishment, or I will slaughter him or he gives me a good reason'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>I will surely punish him with a severe punishment or slaughter him unless he brings me clear authorization."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>I shall certainly punish him severely or slaughter him unless he has a good reason for his absence."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>I will most certainly punish him with a severe punishment, or kill him, or he shall bring to me a clear plea.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>I shall surely punish him severely or order him to be executed, unless he gives me a good reason for his absence."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"I will certainly punish him with a severe penalty, or execute him, unless he bring me a clear reason (for absence)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="22">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>But he was not long in coming, and reported: "I have been around where you have not been. I come from Saba with positive news.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So Hudhud did not stay absent for long, and presenting himself submitted, “I have witnessed a matter that your majesty has not seen, and I have brought definite information to you from the city of Saba.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>But he tarried not long, and said, 'I have comprehended that which thou hast not comprehended, and I have come from Sheba to thee with a sure tiding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Buthe tarried not far, and he said: I have encompassed that which thou hast- not encompassed, and I come unto thee from Saba with a tidings sure.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>But the hoopoe stayed not long, he (came up and) said: "I have grasped (the knowledge of a thing) which you have not grasped and I have come to you from Saba' (Sheba) with true news.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>But he did not stay for long. He said, “I have learnt something you did not know. I have come to you from Sheba, with reliable information.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Not before long the hoopoe came up and said: "I have obtained a knowledge which you could not. I have brought for you sure news about Sheba.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>But (the hoopoe) stayed not long, he said: "I have grasped which you have not grasped and I have come to you from Saba' with true news."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>But he was not long in coming, and he said: I have found out (a thing) that thou apprehendest not, and I come unto thee from Sheba with sure tidings.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He was not long in coming, and said: 'I know what you do not know. I come to you from Sheba with certain news.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>But the hoopoe stayed not long and said, "I have encompassed [in knowledge] that which you have not encompassed, and I have come to you from Sheba with certain news.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Not long after the hoopoe came forward and said, "I have information which you do not have. I have come from the land of Sheba with a true report.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And he tarried not long, then said: I comprehend that which you do not comprehend and I have brought to you a sure information from Sheba.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>But he was not long in coming, and said, "I have learnt something you did not know. I have come to you from Sheba with reliable news.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>But the Hoopoe tarried not far: he (came up and) said: "I have compassed (territory) which thou hast not compassed, and I have come to thee from Saba with tidings true.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="23">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>I found a woman reigning over them, and she has been favoured with everything; and she has a throne that is magnificent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“I have seen a woman who rules over them, and she has been given from all things, and she has a mighty throne.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>I found a woman ruling over them, and she has been given of everything, and she possesses a mighty throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily have found a woman ruling over them and she hath been vouchsafed somewhat of everything, and hers is a mighty throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"I found a woman ruling over them, and she has been given all things that could be possessed by any ruler of the earth, and she has a great throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>I found a woman ruling over them, and she was given of everything, and she has a magnificent throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>I found there a woman ruling over them, one who has been endowed with all things and has a mighty throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"I found a woman ruling over them, she has been given all things, and she has a great throne."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! I found a woman ruling over them, and she hath been given (abundance) of all things, and hers is a mighty throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>There I found a woman ruling over them. She possess everything and has a great throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, I found [there] a woman ruling them, and she has been given of all things, and she has a great throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>I found a woman ruling the people there and she possessed something of (almost) everything and a great throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely I found a woman ruling over them, and she has been given abundance and she has a mighty throne:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>I found a woman ruling over them, who has been given everything and she has a mighty throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"I found (there) a woman ruling over them and provided with every requisite; and she has a magnificent throne.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="24">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>I found that she and her people worship the sun in place of God, for Satan has made their deeds look attractive to them and has turned them away from the Path, so they do not find the way</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“I found her and her nation prostrating before the sun instead of Allah, and Satan has made their deeds seem good to them thereby preventing them from the Straight Path – so they do not attain guidance.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>I found her and her people prostrating to the sun, apart from God; Satan has decked out fair their deeds to them and he has barred them from the way, and therefore they are not guided,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>I have found her and her people adoring the sun instead of Allah, and the Satan hath made their works fairseeming unto them, and hath barred them from the way, so they are not guided.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"I found her and her people worshipping the sun instead of Allah, and Shaitan (Satan) has made their deeds fair-seeming to them, and has barred them from (Allah's) Way, so they have no guidance,"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>I found her and her people worshiping the sun, instead of God. Satan made their conduct appear good to them, and diverted them from the path, so they are not guided.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>I found that she and her people prostrate themselves before the sun rather than Allah. " Satan has made their deeds appear attractive to them and has, thus, debarred them from the Right Path so they do not find true guidance</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"I found her and her people worshipping the sun instead of Allah, and Shaytan has made their deeds fair seeming to them to prevent them from the way, so they have no guidance."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>I found her and her people worshipping the sun instead of Allah; and Satan maketh their works fairseeming unto them, and debarreth them from the way (of Truth), so that they go not aright;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But she and her people prostrate to the sun instead of Allah. And satan has made their deeds seem pleasing to them and barred them from the Path, and therefore they are not guided.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>I found her and her people prostrating to the sun instead of Allah, and Satan has made their deeds pleasing to them and averted them from [His] way, so they are not guided,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>I found her and her people prostrating before the sun instead of God. Satan has made their deeds attractive to them. He has kept them away from the right path and they have no guidance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>I found her and her people adoring the sun instead of Allah, and the Shaitan has made their deeds fair-seeming to them and thus turned them from the way, so they do not go aright</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>I found her and her people worshipping the sun, instead of God. Satan has made their conduct appear good to them, and has thus diverted them from the right path, so that they might not be guided.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"I found her and her people worshipping the sun besides Allah: Satan has made their deeds seem pleasing in their eyes, and has kept them away from the Path,- so they receive no guidance,-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="25">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>To worship God who brings to light what is hidden in the heavens and the earth, and is cognisant of what you hide and what you disclose.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“Why do they not prostrate to Allah, Who brings forth the things hidden in the heavens and the earth, and knows all what you hide and all what you disclose?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>so that they prostrate not themselves to God, who brings forth what is hidden in the heavens and earth; and He knows what you conceal and what you publish.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>So that they adore not Allah who bringeth forth the hidden in the heavens and the earth, and knoweth that which conceal and that which ye make known.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Al-La (this word has two interpretations) (A) [As Shaitan (Satan) has barred them from Allah's Way] so that they do not worship (prostrate before) Allah, or (B) So that they may worship (prostrate before) Allah, Who brings to light what is hidden in the heavens and the earth, and knows what you conceal and what you reveal. [Tafsir At-Tabari, Vol. 19, Page 149]</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>If only they would worship God, who brings to light the mysteries of the heavens and the earth, and knows what you conceal and what you reveal.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>that they would prostrate themselves before Allah Who brings to light all that is hidden in the heavens and the earth and knows all that you conceal and all that you reveal.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So they do not prostrate themselves before Allah, Who brings to light what is hidden in the heavens and the earth, and knows what you conceal and what you reveal.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>So that they worship not Allah, Who bringeth forth the hidden in the heavens and the earth, and knoweth what ye hide and what ye proclaim,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Do they not prostrate themselves to Allah who brings forth all that is concealed in the heavens and earth and He knows what they hide and what they reveal?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[And] so they do not prostrate to Allah, who brings forth what is hidden within the heavens and the earth and knows what you conceal and what you declare -</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Satan has done this) so that they will not worship God who brings forth whatever is hidden in the heavens and the earth and knows whatever you conceal or reveal.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>That they do not make obeisance to Allah, Who brings forth what is hidden in the heavens and the earth and knows what you hide and what you make manifest:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Should they not worship God who brings forth what is hidden in the heavens and earth and knows both what you conceal and what you make known?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"(Kept them away from the Path), that they should not worship Allah, Who brings to light what is hidden in the heavens and the earth, and knows what ye hide and what ye reveal.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="26">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>God: There is no god but He, the Lord of the glorious throne."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“Allah – there is no True God except Him, the Owner of the Great Throne.” (Command of Prostration # 8)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>God: there is no god but He, the Lord of the Mighty Throne.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Allah! there is no God but he, the Lord of the Magnificent Throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Allah, La ilaha illa Huwa (none has the right to be worshipped but He), the Lord of the Supreme Throne!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>God—There is no god but He, the Lord of the Sublime Throne.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Allah - none is worthy of worship save He; He is the Lord of the Mighty Throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Allah, La ilaha illa Huwa, the Lord of the Supreme Throne!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Allah; there is no Allah save Him, the Lord of the Tremendous Throne.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Allah, there is no god except He, the Lord of the Mighty Throne'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Allah - there is no deity except Him, Lord of the Great Throne."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>God is the only Lord and master of the Great Throne."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Allah, there is no god but He: He is the Lord of mighty power.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>He is God: there is no deity but He, the Lord of the mighty throne."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Allah!- there is no god but He!- Lord of the Throne Supreme!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="27">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Solomon) said: 'We shall see if you speak the truth or you are a liar.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Said Sulaiman, “We shall now see whether you spoke the truth or are among the liars.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Said he, 'Now We will see whether thou hast spoken truly, or whether thou art amongst those that lie.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Sulaiman said: we shall see now whether thou hast spoken the truth or whether thou art of the liars.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>[Sulaiman (Solomon)] said: "We shall see whether you speak the truth or you are (one) of the liars.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “We will see, whether you have spoken the truth, or whether you are a liar.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Solomon said: "Soon shall we see whether you have spoken the truth or are one of those that lie.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>(Sulayman) said: "We shall see whether you speak the truth or you are (one) of the liars."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>(Solomon) said: We shall see whether thou speakest truth or whether thou art of the liars.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He replied: 'We shall see if what you have said is true or whether you are among those who lie.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[Solomon] said, "We will see whether you were truthful or were of the liars.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Solomon said, "We shall see whether you are truthful or a liar.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: We will see whether you have told the truth or whether you are of the liars:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Solomon said, "We shall soon see whether you have spoken the truth, or whether you are a liar.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(Solomon) said: "Soon shall we see whether thou hast told the truth or lied!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="28">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Take this letter from me, and deliver it to them and withdraw, then see what reply they give in return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“Go with this letter of mine and drop it upon them – then move aside from them and see what they answer in return.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Take this letter of mine, and cast it unto them, then turn back from them and see what they shall return '</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Go thou with this epistle of mine, and cast it down unto them, and turn aside from them, and see how they return.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"Go you with this letter of mine, and deliver it to them, then draw back from them, and see what (answer) they return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Go with this letter of mine, and deliver it to them; then withdraw from them, and see how they respond.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Take this letter of mine, deliver it to them, and then draw back from them, and observe what they do."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Go you with this letter of mine and deliver it to them, then draw back from them and see what they return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Go with this my letter and throw it down unto them; then turn away and see what (answer) they return,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Take my letter, and drop it to them. Then turn aside and see what they shall return'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Take this letter of mine and deliver it to them. Then leave them and see what [answer] they will return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Take this letter of mine and deliver it to them, then return and see what their reply will be."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Take this my letter and hand it over to them, then turn away from them and see what (answer) they return.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Go with this letter of mine and lay it before them, then withdraw from them and see how they respond."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Go thou, with this letter of mine, and deliver it to them: then draw back from them, and (wait to) see what answer they return"...</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="29">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(The Queen said): "O nobles, a venerable letter has been delivered to me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>The woman said, “O chieftains, indeed a noble letter has been dropped upon me.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>She said, 'O Council, see, a letter honourable has been cast unto me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>She said: O chiefs! verily there hath been cast unto me an honourable epistle.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>She said: "O chiefs! Verily! Here is delivered to me a noble letter,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>She said, “O Counselors, a gracious letter was delivered to me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>The Queen said:" Know my nobles that a gracious letter has been delivered to me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>She said: "O chiefs! Verily, here is delivered to me a noble letter, "</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>(The Queen of Sheba) said (when she received the letter): O chieftains! Lo! there hath been thrown unto me a noble letter.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>She (the Queen of Sheba) said: 'O Council, look, an honorable letter has been dropped to me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>She said, "O eminent ones, indeed, to me has been delivered a noble letter.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(The Queen of Sheba) said to her officials, "A gracious letter has been dropped before me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>She said: O chief! surely an honorable letter has been delivered to me</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>The Queen of Sheba said, "O Counsellors, an honourable letter has been delivered to me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(The queen) said: "Ye chiefs! here is delivered to me - a letter worthy of respect.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="30">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>It is from Solomon, and (says): 'In the name of Allah, Ar-Rahman, Ar-Rahim.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“Indeed it is from Sulaiman, and it is (begins) with ‘Allah – beginning with the name of – the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.’”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>It is from Solomon, and it is "In the Name of God, the Merciful, the Compassionate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily it is from Sulaiman, and verily it is: in the name of Allah, the Compassionate, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"Verily! It is from Sulaiman (Solomon), and verily! It (reads): In the Name of Allah, the Most Beneficent, the Most Merciful;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>It is from Solomon, and it is, ‘In the Name of God, the Gracious, the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>It is from Solomon, and it is: "In the name of Allah, the Most Merciful, the Most Compassionate."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Verily, it is from Sulayman, and it (reads): `In the Name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful;'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! it is from Solomon, and lo! it is: In the name of Allah, the Beneficent, the Merciful;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>It is from Solomon and it is "In the Name of Allah, the Merciful, the Most Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, it is from Solomon, and indeed, it reads: 'In the name of Allah, the Entirely Merciful, the Especially Merciful,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>It reads, 'From Soloman. In the Name of God, the Beneficent and the Merciful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely it is from Sulaiman, and surely it is in the name of Allah, the Beneficent, the Merciful;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>It is from Solomon. It reads, "In the name of God, Most Gracious, Most Merciful,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"It is from Solomon, and is (as follows): 'In the name of Allah, Most Gracious, Most Merciful:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="31">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Do not rise against me, but come to me in submission.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“That ‘Do not wish eminence above me, and present yourselves humbly to me, with submission.’”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Rise not up against me, but come to me in surrender." '</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Saying: exalt not yourselves against me, and come unto me submissive.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"Be you not exalted against me, but come to me as Muslims (true believers who submit to Allah with full submission)' "</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Do not defy me, and come to me submissively.’”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(It says): "Do not act towards me with defiance, but come to me in submission."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>`Be you not exalted against me, but come to me submitting (as Muslims).' "</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Exalt not yourselves against me, but come unto me as those who surrender.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Do not rise up against me, but come to me in surrender (Muslims)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Be not haughty with me but come to me in submission [as Muslims].' "</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Do not consider yourselves superior to me but come to me as Muslims (in submission)".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Saying: exalt not yourselves against me and come to me in submission.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>do not exalt yourselves above me, but come to me in all submission."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"'Be ye not arrogant against me, but come to me in submission (to the true Religion).'"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="32">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>." Advise me, O nobles," she said "in this matter. I do not decide any thing until you concur."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>She said, “O chieftains, advise me in this matter of mine; I do not give a final decision until you are present with me.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>She said, 'O Council, pronounce to me concerning my affair; I am not used to decide an affair until you bear me witness.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>She said: O chiefs! counsel me in my affair. I am wont not to resolve on any affair until ye are present with me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>She said: "O chiefs! Advise me in (this) case of mine. I decide no case till you are present with me."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>She said, “O counselors, advise me in this matter of mine. I never make a decision unless you are present.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(After reading the letter) the Queen said: "Nobles, let me have your counsel in this matter for I make no firm decision without you."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>She said: "O chiefs! Advise me in case of mine. I decide no case till you are present with me."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>She said: O chieftains! Pronounce for me in my case. I decide no case till ye are present with me.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>She said: 'O Council, let me hear your counsel, concerning my affairs, for I am not used to deciding an affair until you bear me witness'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>She said, "O eminent ones, advise me in my affair. I would not decide a matter until you witness [for] me."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>She said, "My officials, what are your views on this matter? I will not decide until I have your views.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>She said: O chiefs! give me advice respecting my affair: I never decide an affair until you are in my presence.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Now advise me in this, Counsellors. I never decide any affair till I have conferred with you."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>She said: "Ye chiefs! advise me in (this) my affair: no affair have I decided except in your presence."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="33">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>They said: "We are men of valour, and brave fighters. It is for you to decide. So consider what you should command."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>They said, “We possess great strength and are great warriors, and the decision is yours, therefore consider what you will command.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>They said, 'We possess force and we possess great might. The affair rests with thee; so consider what thou wilt command.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>They said: we are owners of power and owners of great violence, but the command is with thee; see then whatsoever thou shalt command.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They said: "We have great strength, and great ability for war, but it is for you to command; so think over what you will command."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>They said, “We are a people of might and great courage, but the decision is yours, so consider what you wish to command.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>They said: "We are strong and are given to vehement fighting. But the decision is yours. Therefore, consider what you would like to command."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They said: "We have great strength, and great ability for war, but it is for you to command; so think over what you will command."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>They said: We are lords of might and lords of great prowess, but it is for thee to command; so consider what thou wilt command.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>They replied: 'We are possessors of force and great might. It is for you to command, so consider what you will'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>They said, "We are men of strength and of great military might, but the command is yours, so see what you will command."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They replied, "We have great power and valor. You are the commander, so decide as you like".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>They said: We are possessors of strength and possessors of mighty prowess, and the command is yours, therefore see what you will command.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They said, "We are strong and our prowess in battle is great, but the decision is in your hands, so consider what you will command."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They said: "We are endued with strength, and given to vehement war: but the command is with thee; so consider what thou wilt command."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="34">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>She said: "Surely when kings enter a city they destroy it and despoil the honour of its nobility. So will they do (to us).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>She said, “Indeed the kings, when they enter a township, destroy it and disgrace its honourable people; and this is what they do.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>She said, 'Kings, when they enter a city, disorder it and make the mighty ones of its inhabitants abased. Even so they too will do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>She said: verily the kings, when they enter a City, despoil it, and make the most powerful inhabitants thereof the most abased; so will they do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>She said: "Verily! Kings, when they enter a town (country), they despoil it, and make the most honourable amongst its people low. And thus they do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>She said, “When kings enter a city, they devastate it, and subjugate its dignified people. Thus they always do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>The Queen said: "When the kings enter a country they cause corruption in it and abase those of its people who are held in honour. This is what they are wont to do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>She said: "Verily, kings, when they enter a town, they destroy it and make the most honorable among its people the lowest. And thus they do."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>She said: Lo! kings, when they enter a township, ruin it and make the honour of its people shame. Thus will they do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>She said: 'When kings enter a village, they ruin it and humiliate its nobles. And this they will do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>She said, "Indeed kings - when they enter a city, they ruin it and render the honored of its people humbled. And thus do they do.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>She said, "When Kings enter a town they destroy it and disrespect its honorable people. That is what they will do, too.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>She said: Surely the kings, when they enter a town, ruin it and make the noblest of its people to be low, and thus they (always) do;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>She said, "Surely, when mighty kings invade a country, they despoil it and humiliate its noblest inhabitants, these men will do the same,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>She said: "Kings, when they enter a country, despoil it, and make the noblest of its people its meanest thus do they behave.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="35">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>But I will send them a gift and see what the envoys bring back (in return)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“And I shall send a present to them, then see what reply the envoys bring.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Now I will send them a present, and see what the envoys bring back.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>So verily I am going to send a present unto them, and see with what answer the envoys come back.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>"But verily! I am going to send him a present, and see with what (answer) the messengers return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>I am sending them a gift, and will see what the envoys bring back.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>I will send them a gift and then see with what answer my envoys return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"But verily, I am going to send him a present, and see with what (answer) the messengers return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>But lo! I am going to send a present unto them, and to see with what (answer) the messengers return.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But I shall send them a gift and see what the messengers bring back'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>But indeed, I will send to them a gift and see with what [reply] the messengers will return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>I will send a gift and we shall see what response the Messengers will bring."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And surely I am going to send a present to them, and shall wait to see what (answer) do the apostles bring back.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>but I shall send them a present and see with what reply my envoys will return."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"But I am going to send him a present, and (wait) to see with what (answer) return (my) ambassadors."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="36">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So, when the envoys came to Solomon he said: "Do you wish to increase my wealth? Yet what God has given me is better than what He has given you. No. Be gratified in your present.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So when the envoy came to Sulaiman, he said, “Are you helping me with wealth? What Allah has bestowed upon me is better than what He has given you; rather it is you who are delighted at your gift.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>But when he came to Solomon he said, 'What, would you succour me with wealth, and what God gave me is better than what He has given you? Nay, but instead you rejoice in your gift!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then when he came unto Sulaiman, he said: are ye going to add riches to me. Then that which Allah hath vouchsafed unto me is better than that which He hath vouchsafed unto you. Aye! it is ye who exult in your present.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So when (the messengers with the present) came to Sulaiman (Solomon), he said: "Will you help me in wealth? What Allah has given me is better than that which He has given you! Nay, you rejoice in your gift!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When he came to Solomon, he said, “Are you supplying me with money? What God has given me is better than what He has given you. It is you who delight in your gift.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Now, when (the envoy of the Queen) came to Solomon, he said: "Do you want to aid me with wealth? Whatever Allah has granted me is much more than what He has given you. (Keep for yourselves) your gift in which you are exulting.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So, when (the messengers with the gift) came to Sulayman, he said: "Will you help me in wealth What Allah has given me is better than that which He has given you! Nay, you rejoice in your gift!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>So when (the envoy) came unto Solomon, (the King) said: What! Would ye help me with wealth? But that which Allah hath given me is better than that which He hath given you. Nay it is ye (and not I) who exult in your gift.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But when he came to Solomon, he said: 'Is it wealth that you would give me, when Allah has given me that which is better than He has given to you? No, but instead you rejoice in your gift!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So when they came to Solomon, he said, "Do you provide me with wealth? But what Allah has given me is better than what He has given you. Rather, it is you who rejoice in your gift.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When her Messengers came to Soloman, he said, "Have you brought me wealth? What God has given to me is far better than what He has given to you, but you are happy with your gifts.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So when he came to Sulaiman, he said: What! will you help me with wealth? But what Allah has given me is better than what He has given you. Nay, you are exultant because of your present;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>So when [the envoy] came to Solomon he said, "What! Are you offering me wealth? But that which God has given me is better than that which He has given you. Yet you rejoice in your gift.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Now when (the embassy) came to Solomon, he said: "Will ye give me abundance in wealth? But that which Allah has given me is better than that which He has given you! Nay it is ye who rejoice in your gift!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="37">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Go back to them. We shall soon come with our armies which they will not be able to face. We shall drive them out of (the land) with ignominy, and they will be humbled."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“Go back to them – so we shall indeed come upon them with an army they cannot fight, and degrading them shall certainly drive them out from that city, so they will be humiliated.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Return thou to them; we shall assuredly come against them with hosts they have not power to resist, and we shall expel them from there, abased and utterly humbled.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Go back unto them. Then surely we shall come unto them with hosts which they cannot withstand, and we shall drive them forth therefrom abased and they shall be humbled.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>[Then Sulaiman (Solomon) said to the chief of her messengers who brought the present]: "Go back to them. We verily shall come to them with hosts that they cannot resist, and we shall drive them out from there in disgrace, and they will be abased."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Go back to them. We will come upon them with troops they cannot resist; and we will expel them from there, disgraced and humiliated.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Envoy, go back to those who sent you and we shall certainly come upon them with hosts whom they will be unable to resist. We shall drive them out from there, and they will suffer humiliation and disgrace."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>"Go back to them. We verily, shall come to them with armies that they cannot resist, and we shall drive them out from there in disgrace, and they will be abased."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Return unto them. We verily shall come unto them with hosts that they cannot resist, and we shall drive them out from thence with shame, and they will be abased.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Go back then, we shall surely come against them with soldiers of which they have no power to oppose, and we shall drive them from there abased and humiliated'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Return to them, for we will surely come to them with soldiers that they will be powerless to encounter, and we will surely expel them therefrom in humiliation, and they will be debased."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Go back to your people and we shall soon come there with an army which they will not be able to face. We shall drive them from their town, humble, and disgraced."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Go back to them, so we will most certainly come to them with hosts which they shall have no power to oppose, and we will most certainly expel them therefrom in abasement, and they shall be in a state of ignominy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Go back to them: we shall most certainly come upon them with forces which they will never be able to withstand, and shall most certainly cause them to be driven from their lands, disgraced and humbled!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Go back to them, and be sure we shall come to them with such hosts as they will never be able to meet: We shall expel them from there in disgrace, and they will feel humbled (indeed)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="38">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>He (then) said (to his courtiers): "O you nobles, is there any one who can bring me her throne before they come to me in submission?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Said Sulaiman, “O court members, which one of you can bring me her throne before they come humbled in my presence?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>He said, 'O Council, which one of you will bring me her throne, before they come to me in surrender?'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He said: O chiefs! which of you will bring unto me her throne, ere they come unto me submitting themselves?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He said: "O chiefs! Which of you can bring me her throne before they come to me surrendering themselves in obedience?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “O notables, which one of you will bring me her throne before they come to me in submission?”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Solomon said: "My nobles, which of you can bring me her throne before they come to me in submission?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He said: "O chiefs! Which of you can bring me her throne before they come to me surrendering themselves in obedience (as Muslims)"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He said: O chiefs! Which of you will bring me her throne before they come unto me, surrendering?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And he said: 'O Council, which of you will bring me her throne, before they come to me, Muslims (submissive to Allah)'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[Solomon] said, "O assembly [of jinn], which of you will bring me her throne before they come to me in submission?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Solomon asked his people, "Who among you can bring her throne before (she, the queen of Sheba) comes to me submissively?"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: O chiefs! which of you can bring to me her throne before they come to me in submission?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Solomon then said, "O Counsellors,  which of you can bring me her throne before they come to me in submission?</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He said (to his own men): "Ye chiefs! which of you can bring me her throne before they come to me in submission?"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="39">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>A crafty jinn said: "I will bring it before you rise from your seat, for I am strong and trustworthy."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>An extremely evil jinn said, “I will bring it in your presence before you disperse the assembly; and I am indeed strong and trustworthy upon it.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>An efreet of the jinns said, 'I will bring it to thee, before thou risest from thy place; I have strength for it</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>A giant from the jinns said: I shall bring it unto thee ere thou arisest from thy place; verily I am strong for it and trusty.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>An Ifrit (strong) from the jinns said: "I will bring it to you before you rise from your place (council). And verily, I am indeed strong, and trustworthy for such work."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>An imp of the sprites said, “I will bring it to you before you rise from your seat. I am strong and reliable enough to do it.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>A stalwart of the jinn said: "I will bring it to you before you rise from your council. Surely I have the power to do so and I am trustworthy."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>An `Ifrit from the Jinn said: "I will bring it to you before you rise from your place. And verily, I am indeed strong and trustworthy for such work."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>A stalwart of the jinn said: I will bring it thee before thou canst rise from thy place. Lo! I verily am strong and trusty for such work.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>An efreet (an extremely strong jinn) among the jinn replied: 'I will bring it to you before you rise from your place; I have the strength and am trustworthy'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>A powerful one from among the jinn said, "I will bring it to you before you rise from your place, and indeed, I am for this [task] strong and trustworthy."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>A monstrous jinn said, "I can bring it before you even stand up. I am powerful and trustworthy".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>One audacious among the jinn said: I will bring it to you before you rise up from your place; and most surely I am strong (and) trusty for it.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>A demon from among the jinn said, "I will bring it to you before you get up from your seat. I am strong and trustworthy enough to do it."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Said an 'Ifrit, of the Jinns: "I will bring it to thee before thou rise from thy council: indeed I have full strength for the purpose, and may be trusted."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="40">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>But one who had knowledge of the letter, said: "I will bring it to you in the twinkling of an eye." When Solomon saw it before him, (he said): "This is by the grace of my Lord that He may test me whether I am grateful or I am thankless. Yet if one is grateful, he is grateful for himself, and if one is thankless, then surely my Lord is unconcerned and magnanimous."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Said one who had knowledge of the Book, “I will bring it in your majesty’s presence before you bat your eyelid”; then when he saw it set in his presence*, Sulaiman said, “This is of the favours of my Lord; so that He may test me whether I give thanks or am ungrateful; and whoever gives thanks only gives thanks for his own good; and whoever is ungrateful – then indeed my Lord is the Independent (Not Needing Anything), the Owner Of All Praise.” (A miracle which occurred through one of Allah’s friends.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and I am trusty.' Said he who possessed knowledge of the Book, 'I will bring it to thee, before ever thy glance returns to thee.' Then, when he saw it settled before him, he said, 'This is of my Lord's bounty that He may try me, whether I am thankful or ungrateful. Whosoever gives thanks gives thanks only for his own soul's good, and whosoever is ungrateful -- my Lord is surely All-sufficient, All-generous.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>The one who had some knowledge of the Book said: I shall bring it unto thee ere thy eye twinkleth. Then when he saw it placed before him, he said: this is of the grace of my Lord that he may prove me whether I give thanks or am ungrateful. Whosoever giveth thanks he only giveth thanks for his own soul; and whosoever is ungrateful then verily my Lord is Self-sufficient, Munificent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>One with whom was knowledge of the Scripture said: "I will bring it to you within the twinkling of an eye!" then when [Sulaiman (Solomon)] saw it placed before him, he said: "This is by the Grace of my Lord to test me whether I am grateful or ungrateful! And whoever is grateful, truly, his gratitude is for (the good of) his ownself, and whoever is ungrateful, (he is ungrateful only for the loss of his ownself). Certainly! My Lord is Rich (Free of all wants), Bountiful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He who had knowledge from the Book said, “I will bring it to you before your glance returns to you.” And when he saw it settled before him, he said, “This is from the grace of my Lord, to test me, whether I am grateful or ungrateful. He who is grateful, his gratitude is to his own credit; but he who is ungrateful—my Lord is Independent and Generous.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And he who had some knowledge of the Book said: "I will bring it before the twinkling of your eye." When Solomon saw the throne placed firmly beside him, he cried out: "This is by the grace of my Lord so that He may test me whether I give thanks for (His Bounty) or act with ingratitude. Whoever is grateful is so to his own good; and whoever is ungrateful, let him know that my Lord is Immensely Resourceful, Most Bountiful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>One with whom was knowledge of the Scripture, said: "I will bring it to you within the twinkling of an eye!" Then when he saw it placed before him, he said: "This is by the grace of my Lord -- to test me whether I am grateful or ungrateful! And whoever is grateful, truly, his gratitude is for himself; and whoever is ungrateful, certainly my Lord is Rich, Bountiful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>One with whom was knowledge of the Scripture said: I will bring it thee before thy gaze returneth unto thee. And when he saw it set in his presence, (Solomon) said: This is of the bounty of my Lord, that He may try me whether I give thanks or am ungrateful. Whosoever giveth thanks he only giveth thanks for (the good of) his own soul; and whosoever is ungrateful (is ungrateful only to his own soul's hurt). For lo! my Lord is Absolute in independence, Bountiful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But he who had knowledge of the Book, said: 'I will bring it to you before your glance comes back to you' And when he saw it set before him, he (Solomon) said: 'This is a favor from my Lord that He might test me whether I am thankful or ungrateful. Whosoever gives thanks gives thanks only for his (own soul's) good, but he who is ungrateful, truly my Lord is Rich and Generous'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Said one who had knowledge from the Scripture, "I will bring it to you before your glance returns to you." And when [Solomon] saw it placed before him, he said, "This is from the favor of my Lord to test me whether I will be grateful or ungrateful. And whoever is grateful - his gratitude is only for [the benefit of] himself. And whoever is ungrateful - then indeed, my Lord is Free of need and Generous."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The one who had knowledge from the Book said, "I can bring it to you before you even blink your eye." When Solomon saw the throne placed before him, he said, "This is a favor from my Lord by which He wants to test whether I am grateful or ungrateful. Whoever thanks God does so for his own good. Whoever is ungrateful to God should know that my Lord is Self-Sufficient and Benevolent."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>One who had the knowledge of the Book said: I will bring it to you in the twinkling of an eye. Then when he saw it settled beside him, he said: This is of the grace of my Lord that He may try me whether I am grateful or ungrateful; and whoever is grateful, he is grateful only for his own soul, and whoever is ungrateful, then surely my Lord is Self-sufficient, Honored.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>But one of them who had some knowledge of the Book said, "I will bring it to you in the twinkling of an eye." When Solomon saw it placed before him, he exclaimed, "This is by the grace of my Lord, to test whether I am grateful or ungrateful. Whosoever is grateful, it is for the good of his own self; and whosoever is ungrateful, then surely my Lord is self-sufficient and generous."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Said one who had knowledge of the Book: "I will bring it to thee within the twinkling of an eye!" Then when (Solomon) saw it placed firmly before him, he said: "This is by the Grace of my Lord!- to test me whether I am grateful or ungrateful! and if any is grateful, truly his gratitude is (a gain) for his own soul; but if any is ungrateful, truly my Lord is Free of all Needs, Supreme in Honour!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="41">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Turning to his nobles) he said: "Change the appearance of her throne. Let us see if she is rightly guided, or is not guided at all."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Said Sulaiman, “Disguise her throne in front of her so that we may see whether she finds the way* or becomes of those who remain unknowing.” (*Recognises her throne.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>He said, 'Disguise her throne for her, and we shall behold whether she is guided or if she is of those that are not guided.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He said: disguise for her her throne, that we may see whether she be guided or be of those who are not guided.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He said: "Disguise her throne for her that we may see whether she will be guided (to recognise her throne), or she will be one of those not guided."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “Disguise her throne for her, and we shall see whether she will be guided, or remains one of the misguided.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Solomon said: " Set the throne before her casually, and let us see whether she gets to the Truth or is one of those who are not guided to what is right."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He said: "Disguise her throne for her that we may see whether she will be guided, or she will be one of those not guided."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He said: Disguise her throne for her that we may see whether she will go aright or be of those not rightly guided.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>(Then) he said: 'Let her throne be disguised, so that we can see whether she is guided or if she is among those who are not guided'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>He said, "Disguise for her her throne; we will see whether she will be guided [to truth] or will be of those who is not guided."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Then he said, "Make a few changes to her throne and let us see whether she will recognize it or not."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: Alter her throne for her, we will see whether she follows the right way or is of those who do not go aright.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>He said, "Disguise her throne. We shall see whether or not she will recognize it."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He said: "Transform her throne out of all recognition by her: let us see whether she is guided (to the truth) or is one of those who receive no guidance."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="42">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When she arrived, they asked her: "Is your throne like this?" She said: "As though this is it. We had come to have knowledge and already submitted."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Then when she came, it was said to her, “Is your throne like this? She said, “As if this is it! And we came to know about this incident beforehand and submit (to you).”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So, when she came, it was said, 'Is thy throne like this?' She said, 'It seems the same.' 'And we were given the knowledge before her, and we were in surrender,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then when she arrived, it was said: is thy throne like unto? She said: it is as though it were it; and we have been vouchsafed the knowledge before this, and we have been Muslims.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So when she came, it was said (to her): "Is your throne like this?" She said: "(It is) as though it were the very same." And [Sulaiman (Solomon) said]: "Knowledge was bestowed on us before her, and we were submitted to Allah (in Islam as Muslims before her)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When she arrived, it was said, “Is your throne like this?” She said, “As if this is it.” “We were given knowledge before her, and we were submissive.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>When the Queen arrived, she was asked: "Is your throne like this one?" She said: "It seems as if it is the same. We had already come to know this and we had submitted ourselves."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So when she came, it was said, "Is your throne like this" She said: "As though it were the very same." And he said, "Knowledge was bestowed on us before her, and we had submitted to Allah (as Muslims)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>So, when she came, it was said (unto her): Is thy throne like this? She said: (It is) as though it were the very one. And (Solomon said): We were given the knowledge before her and we had surrendered (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when she came she was asked: 'Is your throne like this' And she replied: 'It looks like it' And we were given the knowledge before her, and wereMuslims.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So when she arrived, it was said [to her], "Is your throne like this?" She said, "[It is] as though it was it." [Solomon said], "And we were given knowledge before her, and we have been Muslims [in submission to Allah].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When she came she was asked, "Is your throne like this?" She replied, "It seems that this is it. We had received the knowledge before this and were submissive (to Solomon's power)".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So when she came, it was said: Is your throne like this? She said: It is as it were the same, and we were given the knowledge before it, and we were submissive.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When she came to Solomon, she was asked, "Is your throne like this?" She replied, "It looks as though it were the same, and we had been given knowledge [of your power] before this, and we have already submitted."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So when she arrived, she was asked, "Is this thy throne?" She said, "It was just like this; and knowledge was bestowed on us in advance of this, and we have submitted to Allah (in Islam)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="43">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>She was (in fact) turned away by what she worshipped other than God, for she came of an unbelieving people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And the thing she used to worship instead of Allah prevented her; she was indeed from the disbelieving people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>but that she served, apart from God, barred her, for she was of a people of unbelievers.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And that which she was wont to worship instead of Allah hindered her; verily she was of an infidel people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And that which she used to worship besides Allah has prevented her (from Islam), for she was of a disbelieving people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>But she was prevented by what she worshiped besides God; she belonged to a disbelieving people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>What prevented her (from accepting the True Faith) was her worshipping deities other than Allah, for she belonged to an unbelieving people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And Saddaha that which she used to worship besides Allah has prevented her (from Islam), for she was of a disbelieving people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (all) that she was wont to worship instead of Allah hindered her, for she came of disbelieving folk.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>That which she worshipped, other than Allah, had prevented her, for she came from an unbelieving nation.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And that which she was worshipping other than Allah had averted her [from submission to Him]. Indeed, she was from a disbelieving people."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Her idols prevented her from believing in God and she was an infidel.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And what she worshipped besides Allah prevented her, surely she was of an unbelieving people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>And that which she used to worship beside God had stopped her [from believing]; for she came of a disbelieving people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And he diverted her from the worship of others besides Allah: for she was (sprung) of a people that had no faith.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="44">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>She was invited to enter the court. When she saw it, she took it for a sheet of water, and (pulling up her skirts) uncovered her legs. (Solomon) told her: "This is paved with tiles of glass." "O Lord," she said, "I have wronged myself, and I submit to the Lord of all the worlds with Solomon."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>It was said to her, “Enter the hall”; and when she saw it she thought it was a pool and bared her shins*; said Sulaiman, “This is only a smooth hall, affixed with glass”; she said, “My Lord, I have indeed wronged myself, and I now submit myself along with Sulaiman to Allah, the Lord Of The Creation.” (* In order to cross it)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>It was said to her, 'Enter the pavilion.' But when she saw it, she supposed it was a spreading water, and she bared her legs. He said, 'It is a pavilion smoothed of crystal. She said, 'My Lord, indeed I have wronged myself, and I surrender with Solomon to God, the Lord of all Being.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>It was said unto her: enter the palace. Then when she saw it,, he deemed it a pool and bared her shanks. He said: verily it is a palace evenly floored with glass. She said: my Lord! verily I wronged my soul, and now submit myself together with Sulaiman unto Allah, the Lord of the Worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>It was said to her: "Enter As-Sarh" [(a glass surface with water underneath it) or a palace], but when she saw it, she thought it was a pool, and she (tucked up her clothes) uncovering her legs, Sulaiman (Solomon) said: "Verily, it is Sarh [(a glass surface with water underneath it) or a palace] paved smooth with slab of glass." She said: "My Lord! Verily, I have wronged myself, and I submit (in Islam, together with Sulaiman (Solomon), to Allah, the Lord of the 'Alamin (mankind, jinns and all that exists)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>It was said to her, “Go inside the palace.” And when she saw it, she thought it was a deep pond, and she bared her legs. He said, “It is a palace paved with glass.” She said, “My Lord, I have done wrong to myself, and I have submitted with Solomon, to God, Lord of the Worlds.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>She was told: "Enter the palace." But when she saw it, she thought it was a pool of water and she bared both her calves (to enter into it). Solomon said: "This is a slippery floor of crystal." Thereupon she cried out: "My Lord, I have been inflicting much wrong on myself. Now I submit myself with Solomon to Allah, the Lord of the whole Universe."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>It was said to her: "Enter As-Sarh," but when she saw it, she thought it was a pool, and she (tucked up her clothes) uncovering her legs. Sulayman said: "Verily, it is a Sarh Mumarrad of Qawarir." She said: "My Lord! Verily, I have wronged myself, and I submit, together with Sulayman to Allah, the Lord of all that exits."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>It was said unto her: Enter the hall. And when she saw it she deemed it a pool and bared her legs. (Solomon) said: Lo! it is a hall, made smooth, of glass. She said: My Lord! Lo! I have wronged myself, and I surrender with Solomon unto Allah, the Lord of the Worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>It was said to her: 'Enter the pavilion' And when she saw it, she thought it was a pool of water, and bared her legs. But he said: 'It is a pavilion smoothed with crystal' She said: 'My Lord, I have wronged myself, and I become a Muslim (submissive) with Solomon to Allah, Lord of the Worlds'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>She was told, "Enter the palace." But when she saw it, she thought it was a body of water and uncovered her shins [to wade through]. He said, "Indeed, it is a palace [whose floor is] made smooth with glass." She said, "My Lord, indeed I have wronged myself, and I submit with Solomon to Allah, Lord of the worlds."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>She was told to enter the palace. When she saw it, she thought that it was a pool and raised her clothe up to her legs. Solomon said, "This is a palace constructed with glass." She said, "My Lord, indeed I have wronged myself and I submit myself with Solomon to the will of God, the Lord of the Universe."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>It was said to her: Enter the palace; but when she saw it she deemed it to be a great expanse of water, and bared her legs. He said: Surely it is a palace made smooth with glass. She said: My Lord! surely I have been unjust to myself, and I submit with Sulaiman to Allah, the Lord of the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Then she was bidden to enter the palace; but when she saw it, she thought it was a deep pool of water, and bared her legs. But Solomon explained, "It is just a palace paved with glass," and she said, "My Lord, I have wronged myself: now I submit myself along with Solomon, to God, the Lord of the Universe."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>She was asked to enter the lofty Palace: but when she saw it, she thought it was a lake of water, and she (tucked up her skirts), uncovering her legs. He said: "This is but a palace paved smooth with slabs of glass." She said: "O my Lord! I have indeed wronged my soul: I do (now) submit (in Islam), with Solomon, to the Lord of the Worlds."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="31">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When they brought fleet-footed chargers in the evening to show him,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>When fast footed steeds were presented to him at evening.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>When in the evening were presented to him the standing steeds,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Recall what time there were presented Unto him, at eventide, s coursers swift-footed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>When there were displayed before him, in the afternoon, well trained horses of the highest breed [for Jihad (holy fighting in Allah's Cause)].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When the beautiful horses were paraded before him in the evening.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And when one evening well-trained and running horses of noble breed were brought to him</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>When there were displayed before him, in the afternoon, well trained horses of the highest breed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>When there were shown to him at eventide lightfooted coursers</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>When his dressage steeds were presented to him in the evening,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[Mention] when there were exhibited before him in the afternoon the poised [standing] racehorses.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When the noble galloping horses were displayed to him one evening,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>When there were brought to him in the evening (horses) still when standing, swift when running--</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When well-bred horses, which were fleet of foot were paraded before him near the close of day,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Behold, there were brought before him, at eventide coursers of the highest breeding, and swift of foot;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="32">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>He said: "The love of horses is worthy of desire to me for the remembrance of my Lord;" and when they were out of sight, (he said):</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Therefore Sulaiman said, “I cherish the love of these horses*, out of remembrance of my Lord”; he then ordered them to be raced until they vanished in a curtain out of sight. (To be used in holy war.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>he said, 'Lo, I have loved the love of good things better than the remembrance of my Lord, until the sun was bidden behind the veil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He said: verily I have loved the love of earthly good above the remembrance of my Lord until the sun hath disappeared behind the veil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And he said: "Alas! I did love the good (these horses) instead of remembering my Lord (in my 'Asr prayer)" till the time was over, and (the sun) had hidden in the veil (of night).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “I have preferred the love of niceties to the remembrance of my Lord—until it disappeared behind the veil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>he said: “Lo! I have come to love this wealth on account of the remembrance of my Lord.” And when the horses disappeared,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He said: "I did love the good instead of remembering my Lord," till the time was over, and (the sun) had hidden in the veil (of night).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And he said: Lo! I have preferred the good things (of the world) to the remembrance of my Lord; till they were taken out of sight behind the curtain.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>he said: 'Indeed I have loved the love of good things better than the remembrance of my Lord until the sun has vanished behind a veil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And he said, "Indeed, I gave preference to the love of good [things] over the remembrance of my Lord until the sun disappeared into the curtain [of darkness]."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>he said, "My love of horses for the cause of God has made me continue watching them until sunset, thus making me miss my prayer".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Then he said: Surely I preferred the good things to the remembrance of my Lord-- until the sun set and time for Asr prayer was over, (he said):</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>he said, "I have put the love of good things above the remembrance of my Lord," until [the sun] disappeared behind its veil and the horses disappeared from sight,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And he said, "Truly do I love the love of good, with a view to the glory of my Lord,"- until (the sun) was hidden in the veil (of night):</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="33">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"Bring them back to me," and he began to rub and stroke their shanks and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He then ordered, “Bring them back to me”; and he began caressing their shins and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Return them to me!' And he began to stroke their shanks and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Bring them back Unto me; and he set about slashing their legs and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Then he said "Bring them (horses) back to me." Then he began to pass his hand over their legs and their necks (till the end of the display).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Bring them back to me.” And he began caressing their legs and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(he ordered): “Bring these horses back to me,” and then he began to gently stroke their shanks and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then he said: "Bring them back to me." Then he began to pass his hand over their legs and their necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>(Then he said): Bring them back to me, and fell to slashing (with his sword their) legs and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Bring them back to me' And he hacked their legs and necks (slaughtering them for Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[He said], "Return them to me," and set about striking [their] legs and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>He said, "Bring them back to me." Then he started to rub their legs and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Bring them back to me; so he began to slash (their) legs and necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>"Bring them back to me!" -- [he said] and began to stroke their legs and their necks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>"Bring them back to me." then began he to pass his hand over (their) legs and their necks.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="34">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We surely tried Solomon, and placed another body on his throne. So he turned to God</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We indeed tested Sulaiman, and placed a dead body on his throne – he therefore inclined towards His Lord.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Certainly We tried Solomon, and We cast upon his throne a mere body; then he repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We tried Sulaiman, and set upon his throne a mere body. Thereafter he was penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And, indeed We did try Sulaiman (Solomon) and We placed on his throne Jasadan (a devil, so he lost his kingdom for a while) but he did return (to his throne and kingdom by the Grace of Allah and he did return) to Allah with obedience and in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We tested Solomon, and placed a body on his throne; then he repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Surely We put Solomon to the test and cast upon his throne a mere body. Thereupon he penitently turned (to Us).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed, We tried Sulayman and We placed on his throne Jasad (a body), and he returned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And verily We tried Solomon, and set upon his throne a (mere) body. Then did he repent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Indeed, We tried Solomon and placed a body (of a child) upon his throne, then he repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We certainly tried Solomon and placed on his throne a body; then he returned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We tested Solomon by (causing death to his son) and leaving his body on Solomon's chair. Then he turned to Us in repentance,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We tried Sulaiman, and We put on his throne a (mere) body, so he turned (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We tried Solomon by placing upon his throne a [lifeless] body; and thereupon he turned towards Us].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We did try Solomon: We placed on his throne a body (without life); but he did turn (to Us in true devotion):</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="35">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Saying: "O Lord, forgive me, and give me such a dominion as none will merit after me. You are the great bestower."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He said, “My Lord! Forgive me and bestow upon me a kingdom, which shall not befit anyone after me; indeed only You are the Great Bestower.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>He said, 'My Lord, forgive me, and give me a kingdom such as may not befall anyone after me; surely Thou art the All-giver.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He said: my Lord! forgive me, and bestow on me a dominion which no one may obtain beside me: verily Thou! Thou art the Bestower.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He said: "My Lord! Forgive me, and bestow upon me a kingdom such as shall not belong to any other after me: Verily, You are the Bestower."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “My Lord, forgive me, and grant me a kingdom never to be attained by anyone after me. You are the Giver.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>He said: “My Lord, forgive me and bestow upon me a kingdom such as none other after me will deserve. Surely You are the Bounteous Giver.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He said: "My Lord! Forgive me, and bestow upon me a kingdom such as shall not belong to any other after me. Verily, You are the Bestower."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He said: My Lord! Forgive me and bestow on me sovereignty such as shall not belong to any after me. Lo! Thou art the Bestower.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He said: 'Forgive me my Lord, and give me a kingdom the like of which will not befall any after me, surely, You are the Giver'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>He said, "My Lord, forgive me and grant me a kingdom such as will not belong to anyone after me. Indeed, You are the Bestower."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>saying, "Lord, forgive me and grant me a kingdom that no one after me can have the like. You are All-munificent".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: My Lord! do Thou forgive me and grant me a kingdom which is not fit for (being inherited by) anyone after me;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>He prayed, "Lord forgive me! Grant me such power as no one after me will have -- You are the Most Generous Provider."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He said, "O my Lord! Forgive me, and grant me a kingdom which, (it may be), suits not another after me: for Thou art the Grantor of Bounties (without measure).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="102">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And they follow what devilish beings used to chant against the authority of Solomon, though Solomon never disbelieved and only the devils denied, who taught sorcery to men, which, they said, had been revealed to the angels of Babylon, Harut and Marut, who, however, never taught it without saying: "We have been sent to deceive you, so do not renounce (your faith)." They learnt what led to discord between husband and wife. Yet they could not harm any one or without the dispensation of God. And they learnt what harmed them and brought no gain. They knew indeed whoever bought this had no place in the world to come, and that surely they had sold themselves for something that was vile. If only they had sense!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And they followed what the devils used to read during the rule of Sulaiman (Solomon – peace and blessings be upon him); and Sulaiman did not disbelieve, but the devils disbelieved – they teach people magic; and that which was sent down to the two angels, Harut and Marut in Babylon; and the two (angels) never taught a thing to anyone until they used to say, “We are only a trial, therefore do not lose your faith” and they used to learn from them that by which they cause division between man and his wife; and they cannot harm anyone by it except by Allah’s command; and they learn what will harm them, not benefit them; and surely they know that whoever bargains for this will not have a share in the Hereafter; and for what an abject thing they have sold themselves; if only they knew!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and they follow what the Satans recited over Solomon's kingdom. Solomon disbelieved not, but the Satans disbelieved, teaching the people sorcery, and that which was sent down upon Babylon's two angels, Harut and Marut; they taught not any man, without they said, 'We are but a temptation; do not disbelieve.' From them they learned how they might divide a man and his wife, yet they did not hurt any man thereby, save by the leave of God, and they learned what hurt them, and did not profit them, knowing well that whoso buys it shall have no share in the world to come; evil then was that they sold themselves for, if they had but known.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And they follow that which the Satans recited in the reign of Sulaiman; and Sulaiman blasphemed not, but the Satans blasphemed.; teaching people magic; and they follow that also which was sent down unto the two angels in Babil, Harut, and Marut. Unto none the twain taught it until they had said: We are but a temptation, so blaspheme not; but they learned from the twain that wherewith they might separate man from his wife; and they could harm none thereby save by Allah's will. And they have learnt that which harmeth them, and profiteth them not; and assuredly they know that whosoever purchaseth it, his is no portion in the Hereafter. And surely vile is the price for which they have bartered themselves, if they but knew!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They followed what the Shayatin (devils) gave out (falsely of the magic) in the lifetime of Sulaiman (Solomon). Sulaiman did not disbelieve, but the Shayatin (devils) disbelieved, teaching men magic and such things that came down at Babylon to the two angels, Harut and Marut, but neither of these two (angels) taught anyone (such things) till they had said, "We are only for trial, so disbelieve not (by learning this magic from us)." And from these (angels) people learn that by which they cause separation between man and his wife, but they could not thus harm anyone except by Allah's Leave. And they learn that which harms them and profits them not. And indeed they knew that the buyers of it (magic) would have no share in the Hereafter. And how bad indeed was that for which they sold their ownselves, if they but knew.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And they followed what the devils taught during the reign of Salomon. It was not Solomon who disbelieved, but it was the devils who disbelieved. They taught the people witchcraft and what was revealed in Babylon to the two angels Harut and Marut. They did not teach anybody until they had said, “We are a test, so do not lose faith.” But they learned from them the means to cause separation between man and his wife. But they cannot harm anyone except with God's permission. And they learned what would harm them and not benefit them. Yet they knew that whoever deals in it will have no share in the Hereafter. Miserable is what they sold their souls for, if they only knew.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(Instead of this,) they began to follow that (magic) to which the devils falsely attributed (the greatness of) the kingdom of Solomon. In fact Solomon was never involved in any practice of disbelief, but the satans, who taught magic to the people were themselves guilty of disbelief. They were after that thing which was sent to Harut and Marut, the two angels at Babylon. Whenever these two angels taught black art to anyone, they would always give a clear warning beforehand, saying, "We are merely a trial for you; so you should not commit blasphemy. But in spite of this warning, those people used to learn from the angels the art which caused division between husband and wife. Although it was obvious that they could not do any harm to anyone by means of this magic without Allah's permission, yet they learnt that art which could not be profitable even for them but was actually harmful. Moreover, they knew it full well that anyone, who purchased that art, would have no share in the Hereafter. What a vile commodity it was for which they sold off their souls, if they had but known it!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They followed what the Shayatin (devils) gave out (falsely of the magic) in the lifetime of Sulayman (Solomon). Sulayman did not disbelieve, but the Shayatin (devils) disbelieved, teaching men magic and such things that came down at Babylon to the two angels, Harut and Marut, but neither of these two (angels) taught anyone (such things) till they had said, "We are for trial, so disbelieve not (by learning this magic from us)." And from these (angels) people learn that by which they cause separation between man and his wife, but they could not thus harm anyone except by Allah's leave. And they learn that which harms them and profits them not. And indeed they knew that the buyers of it (magic) would have no share in the Hereafter. And how bad indeed was that for which they sold their own selves, if they but knew.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And follow that which the devils falsely related against the kingdom of Solomon. Solomon disbelieved not; but the devils disbelieved, teaching mankind magic and that which was revealed to the two angels in Babel, Harut and Marut. Nor did they (the two angels) teach it to anyone till they had said: We are only a temptation, therefore disbelieve not (in the guidance of Allah). And from these two (angles) people learn that by which they cause division between man and wife; but they injure thereby no-one save by Allah's leave. And they learn that which harmeth them and profiteth them not. And surely they do know that he who trafficketh therein will have no (happy) portion in the Hereafter; and surely evil is the price for which they sell their souls, if they but knew.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and follow what the devils recited over the Kingdom of Solomon. Solomon did not disbelieve, it is the devils who disbelieved, teaching people magic and that which was sent down upon the angels Harut and Marut in Babylon. They did not teach anyone, until both had said: 'We have been sent as a trial; do not disbelieve' From them they learned how they might separate a husband and his wife. However, they did not harm anyone with it, except by the permission of Allah. Indeed, they learned what harms them and does not profit them, yet they knew that anyone who buys it would have no share in the Everlasting Life. Evil is that for which they have sold their souls, if they but knew!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And they followed [instead] what the devils had recited during the reign of Solomon. It was not Solomon who disbelieved, but the devils disbelieved, teaching people magic and that which was revealed to the two angels at Babylon, Harut and Marut. But the two angels do not teach anyone unless they say, "We are a trial, so do not disbelieve [by practicing magic]." And [yet] they learn from them that by which they cause separation between a man and his wife. But they do not harm anyone through it except by permission of Allah. And the people learn what harms them and does not benefit them. But the Children of Israel certainly knew that whoever purchased the magic would not have in the Hereafter any share. And wretched is that for which they sold themselves, if they only knew.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They followed the incantations that the devils used against the kingdom of Solomon. Solomon did not hide the truth but the devils did. They taught magic to the people and whatever was revealed to the two angels, Harut and Marut, in Babylon. The two angels did not teach anything to anyone without saying, "Our case is a temptation for the people, so do not hide the truth." People learned something from the two angels that could cause discord between a man and his wife. However, they could harm no one except by the permission of God. In fact, the (people) learned things that would harm them and render them no benefit. They knew very well that one who engaged in witchcraft would have no reward in the life hereafter. Would that they had known that they had sold their souls for that which is vile!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And they followed what the Shaitans chanted of sorcery in the reign of Sulaiman, and Sulaiman was not an unbeliever, but the Shaitans disbelieved, they taught men sorcery and that was sent down to the two angels at Babel, Harut and Marut, yet these two taught no man until they had said, "Surely we are only a trial, therefore do not be a disbeliever." Even then men learned from these two, magic by which they might cause a separation between a man and his wife; and they cannot hurt with it any one except with Allah's permission, and they learned what harmed them and did not profit them, and certainly they know that he who bought it should have no share of good in the hereafter and evil was the price for which they sold their souls; had they but known this.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They pursued what the devils falsely attributed to the kingdom of Solomon. Solomon was not an unbeliever: it is the devils who are unbelievers. They taught people witchcraft, and that which was sent down to Harut and Marut, the two angels in Babylon. But these two taught no one until they had said, "We are but a trial, therefore, do not disbelieve [in God's guidance]." So men learnt from them that by which they caused discord between man and wife; but they harmed no one thereby, except by the command of God; [on the contrary], these people learned that which would harm them and do them no good, knowing full well that whoever acquired [this knowledge] would have no share in the Hereafter. Evil indeed was the [price] for which they sold their souls, if only they had known it.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They followed what the evil ones gave out (falsely) against the power of Solomon: the blasphemers Were, not Solomon, but the evil ones, teaching men Magic, and such things as came down at babylon to the angels Harut and Marut. But neither of these taught anyone (Such things) without saying: "We are only for trial; so do not blaspheme." They learned from them the means to sow discord between man and wife. But they could not thus harm anyone except by Allah's permission. And they learned what harmed them, not what profited them. And they knew that the buyers of (magic) would have no share in the happiness of the Hereafter. And vile was the price for which they did sell their souls, if they but knew!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="14">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When We ordained (Solomon's) death, none but the weevil, that was eating away his staff (on which he rested), pointed out to them that he was dead. When he fell down (dead) the jinns realised that if they had knowledge of the Unknown they would never have suffered demeaning labour.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So when We sent the command of death towards him, no one revealed his death to the jinns except the termite of the earth which ate his staff; and when he came to the ground, the truth about the jinns was exposed – if they had known the hidden, they would not have remained in the disgraceful toil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And when We decreed that he should die, naught indicated to them that he was dead but the Beast of the Earth devouring his staff; and when he fell down, the jinn saw clearly that, had they only known the Unseen, they would not have continued in the humbling chastisement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then when We decreed death for him, naught discovered his death to them' save a moving creature of the earth which gnawed away his staff. Then when he fell, the Jinn clearly perceived that, if they had known the unseen they would not have tarried in the ignominious torment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Then when We decreed death for him [Sulaiman (Solomon)], nothing informed them (jinns) of his death except a little worm of the earth, which kept (slowly) gnawing away at his stick, so when he fell down, the jinns saw clearly that if they had known the unseen, they would not have stayed in the humiliating torment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then, when We decreed death for him, nothing indicated his death to them except an earthworm eating at his staff. Then, when he fell down, it became clear to the sprites that, had they known the unseen, they would not have remained in the demeaning torment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>When We executed Our decree of death on Solomon, nothing indicated to the jinn that he was dead except a worm eating away his staff. So when Solomon fell down, the jinn realised that had they known what lies in the realm beyond perception, they would not have continued to be in this humiliating chastisement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then when We decreed death for him, nothing informed them (Jinn) of his death except a little worm of the earth which kept (slowly) gnawing away at his stick. So when he fell down, the Jinn saw clearly that if they had known the Unseen, they would not have stayed in the humiliating torment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And when We decreed death for him, nothing showed his death to them save a creeping creature of the earth which gnawed away his staff. And when he fell the jinn saw clearly how, if they had known the Unseen, they would not have continued in despised toil.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And when We decreed (Solomon's) death, they had no indication that he was dead until (they saw a termite), a crawler of the earth eating away his staff. And when he fell down, the jinn realized that had they known the unseen, they would not have continued in their humiliating punishment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And when We decreed for Solomon death, nothing indicated to the jinn his death except a creature of the earth eating his staff. But when he fell, it became clear to the jinn that if they had known the unseen, they would not have remained in humiliating punishment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>When We decreed that Solomon should die, no one knew of his death except for a creeping creature of the earth who ate-up his staff. When he fell down, the jinn realized that if they had known about the unseen, they would not have remained in such a humiliating torment for so long.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>But when We decreed death for him, naught showed them his death but a creature of the earth that ate away his staff; and when it fell down, the jinn came to know plainly that if they had known the unseen, they would not have tarried in abasing torment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When We decreed Solomon's death, nothing indicated his death to them except a worm from the earth, which was eating away at his cane. When he fell down, the jinn plainly realized that if they had known what was unseen, they would not have had to continue with such humiliating labour.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Then, when We decreed (Solomon's) death, nothing showed them his death except a little worm of the earth, which kept (slowly) gnawing away at his staff: so when he fell down, the Jinns saw plainly that if they had known the unseen, they would not have tarried in the humiliating Penalty (of their Task).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="635">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, "Solomon (the son of) David said, 'Tonight I will sleep with seventy ladies each of whom will conceive a child who will be a knight fighting for "Allah's Cause.' His companion said, 'If Allah will.' But Solomon did not say so; therefore none of those women got pregnant except one who gave birth to a half child." The Prophet further said, "If the Prophet Solomon had said it (i.e. 'If Allah will') he would have begotten children who would have fought in Allah's Cause." Shuaib and Ibn Abi Az-Zinad said, "Ninety (women) is more correct (than seventy)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="561">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah's Prophet Solomon who had sixty wives, once said, "Tonight I will have sexual relation (sleep) with all my wives so that each of them will become pregnant and bring forth (a boy who will grow into) a cavalier and will fight in Allah's Cause." So he slept with his wives and none of them (conceived and) delivered (a child) except one who brought a half (body) boy (deformed). Allah's Prophet said, "If Solomon had said; 'If Allah Will,' then each of those women would have delivered a (would-be) cavalier to fight in Allah's Cause." (See Hadith No. 74 A, Vol. 4).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>