<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="yunus" generated="2026-03-30T00:18:10.853Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story of Jonah (Yunus)</title>
    <verses_count>24</verses_count>
    <translations_count>318</translations_count>
    <reordered>2026-03-30T00:18:10.863Z</reordered>
    <reorder_source>yunus_reorder.csv</reorder_source>
  </metadata>
  <verses>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="84">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided them, as We had guided Noah before them, and of his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus We reward those who are upright and do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob); We guided all of them; and We guided Nooh before them and of his descendants, Dawud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Moosa and Haroon; and this is the way We reward the virtuous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave to him Isaac and Jacob -- each one We guided, And Noah We guided before; and of his seed David and Solomon, Job and Joseph, Moses and Aaron -- even so We recompense the good-doers --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Is-haq and Ya'qub: each one We guided. And Nuh We had guided afore, and of his progeny Da-ud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Musa and Harun. And thus We recompense the well-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob), each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh (Noah), and among his progeny Dawud (David), Sulaiman (Solomon), Ayub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses), and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob—each of them We guided. And We guided Noah previously; and from his descendants David, and Solomon, and Job, and Joseph, and Moses, and Aaron. Thus We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon Abraham (offspring) Ishaq (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob) and each of them did We guide to the right way as We had earlier guided Noah to the right way; and (of his descendants We guided) Da'ud (David) and Sulayman (Solomon), Ayyub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses) and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward those who do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq and Ya`qub, each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh and among his progeny Dawud, Sulayman, Ayyub, Yusuf, Musa, and Harun. Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Isaac and Jacob; each of them We guided; and Noah did We guide aforetime; and of his seed (We guided) David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided both; and We guided Noah before them, among his descendants were David and Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron as such, We recompense the gooddoers,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob - all [of them] We guided. And Noah, We guided before; and among his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave (Abraham) Isaac and Jacob. Both had received Our guidance. Noah received Our guidance before Abraham and so did his descendants: David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron. Thus is the reward for the righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave to him Ishaq and Yaqoub; each did We guide, and Nuh did We guide before, and of his descendants, Dawood and Sulaiman and Ayub and Yusuf and Musa and Haroun; and thus do We reward those who do good (to others).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob, each of whom We guided as We had guided Noah before. Among his descendants were David and Solomon, and Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob: all (three) guided: and before him, We guided Noah, and among his progeny, David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron: thus do We reward those who do good:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="85">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Zachariah and John We guided, and guided Jesus and Elias who were all among the upright.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And (We guided) Zakaria and Yahya (John) and Eisa and Elias; all these are worthy of Our proximity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Zachariah and John, Jesus and Elias; each was of the righteous;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And also Zakariyya and Yahya and Isa and llyas: each one was of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And Zakariya (Zachariya), and Yahya (John) and 'Iesa (Jesus) and Iliyas (Elias), each one of them was of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Zechariah, and John, and Jesus, and Elias—every one of them was of the upright.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(And of his descendants We guided) Zakariya (Zachariah), Yahya (John), Isa (Jesus) and Ilyas (Elias): each one of them was of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And Zakariyya, and Yahya and `Isa and Iliyas, each one of them was of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Zachariah and John and Jesus and Elias. Each one (of them) was of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and (Prophets) Zachariah, John, Jesus and Elias, each was of the righteous,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Zechariah and John and Jesus and Elias - and all were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We also gave guidance to Zacharias, John, Jesus, and Elias, who were all pious people,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Zakariya and Yahya and Isa and Ilyas; every one was of the good;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Zachariah, John, Jesus, and Elijah, every one of them was righteous,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And Zakariya and John, and Jesus and Elias: all in the ranks of the righteous:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="86">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We gave guidance to Ishmael, Elisha and Jonah and Lot; And We favoured them over the other people of the world,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And Ismael (Ishmael) and Yasa’a (Elisha) and Yunus (Jonah) and Lut (Lot); and to each one during their times, We gave excellence over all others.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Ishmael and Elisha, Jonah and Lot-each one We preferred above all beings;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Ismai'l and Alyas'a and Yunus and Lut: each one of them We preferred above the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And Isma'il (Ishmael) and Al-Yas'a (Elisha), and Yunus (Jonah) and Lout (Lot), and each one of them We preferred above the 'Alamin (mankind and jinns) (of their times).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Ishmael, and Elijah, and Jonah, and Lot—We favored each one of them over all other people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(And of his descendants We guided) Isma'il (Ishmael), al-Yasa' (Elisha), Yunus (Jonah), and Lut (Lot). And each one of them We favoured over all mankind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And Isma`il and Al-Yasa`, and Yunus and Lut, and each one of them We preferred above the `Alamin (mankind and Jinns, of their times).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Ishmael and Elisha and Jonah and Lot. Each one (of them) did We prefer above (Our) creatures,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and Ishmael, Elisha, Jonah and Lot. Each We preferred above the worlds,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Ishmael and Elisha and Jonah and Lot - and all [of them] We preferred over the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>and Ishmael, Elisha, Jonah, and Lot whom We exalted over all people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Ismail and Al-Yasha and Yunus and Lut; and every one We made to excel (in) the worlds:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Ishmael, Elisha, Jonah, and Lot -- We favoured each one of them above other people,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And Isma'il and Elisha, and Jonas, and Lot: and to all We gave favour above the nations:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="139">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Verily Jonah is one of the apostles.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And indeed Yunus is one of the Noble Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Jonah too was one of the Envoys;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And verily Yunus was Of the sent ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And, verily, Yunus (Jonah) was one of the Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Jonah was one of the messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And Jonah too was one of the Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And verily, Yunus was one of the Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And lo! Jonah verily was of those sent (to warn)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Jonah, too, was one of the Messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And indeed, Jonah was among the messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Jonah was certainly a Messenger.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Yunus was most surely of the apostles.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Jonah too was one of the messengers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So also was Jonah among those sent (by Us).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="140">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When he fled on the laden ship,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>When he left towards the laden ship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>when he ran away to the laden ship</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Recall what time he ran away Unto a laden ship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>When he ran to the laden ship,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When he fled to the laden boat.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Call to mind when he fled to the laden ship,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>When he ran to the laden ship:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>When he fled unto the laden ship,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He ran away to the laden ship,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[Mention] when he ran away to the laden ship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>He abandoned his people</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>When he ran away to a ship completely laden,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>He fled to the overloaded ship.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>When he ran away (like a slave from captivity) to the ship (fully) laden,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="141">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And lots were cast (when a storm overtook them), he was rejected, (and thrown overboard).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Then lots were drawn and he became of those who were pushed into the sea.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and cast lots, and was of the rebutted,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then he joined the lots, and was of the condemned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He (agreed to) cast lots, and he was among the losers,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He gambled and lost.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>cast lots, and was among the losers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then he (agreed to) cast lots, and he was among the losers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And then drew lots and was of those rejected;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and cast lots, and he was among the losers (of the lots that were cast).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And he drew lots and was among the losers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>and sailed away in a laden ship, wherein people cast lots. Because he lost, he was thrown into the water.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So he shared (with them), but was of those who are cast off.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>And then they cast lots and he was the one who lost,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He (agreed to) cast lots, and he was condemned:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="142">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Then he was swallowed by a large fish as he was worthy of blame.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>The fish then swallowed him and he blamed himself. (For not waiting for Allah’s command.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>then the whale swallowed him down, and he blameworthy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And a fish swallowed him, and he was reproaching himself.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Then a (big) fish swallowed him and he had done an act worthy of blame.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then the fish swallowed him, and he was to blame.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Then a fish swallowed him, and he was blameworthy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Then a (big) fish swallowed him as he had done an act worthy of blame.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And the fish swallowed him while he was blameworthy;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>So the whale swallowed him, for he was blameworthy,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Then the fish swallowed him, while he was blameworthy.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The fish swallowed him up and he deserved (all this).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So the fish swallowed him while he did that for which he blamed himself</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and the fish swallowed him while he was blaming himself.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Then the big Fish did swallow him, and he had done acts worthy of blame.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="143">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Had he not been one of those who struggled hard,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And were he not one of those who praise. –</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Now had he not been of those that glorify God,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And had he not been of those who hallow Him,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Had he not been of them who glorify Allah,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Had he not been one of those who praised.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Had he not been one of those who glorify Allah,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Had he not been of them who glorify Allah,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And had he not been one of those who glorify (Allah)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and had he not been among those who exalt (Allah),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And had he not been of those who exalt Allah,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Had he not glorified God,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>But had it not been that he was of those who glorify (Us),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Had he not been one of those who acknowledge the glory of God,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Had it not been that he (repented and) glorified Allah,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="144">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>He would have stayed in its belly till the day the dead are raised.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>He would have remained in its belly till the day when all will be raised.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>he would have tarried in its belly until the day they shall be raised;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>He would have tarried in the belly thereof till the Day when they are raised.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>He would have indeed remained inside its belly (the fish) till the Day of Resurrection.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He would have stayed in its belly until the Day they are raised.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>he would certainly have remained in its belly till the Day of Resurrection.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>He would have indeed remained inside its belly (the fish) till the Day of Resurrection.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>He would have tarried in its belly till the day when they are raised;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>he would have lingered in its belly till the Day they are resurrected.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>He would have remained inside its belly until the Day they are resurrected.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>he would certainly have remained inside the fish until the Day of Resurrection.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He would certainly have tarried in its belly to the day when they are raised.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>he would certainly have remained inside the fish till the Day of Resurrection.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>He would certainly have remained inside the Fish till the Day of Resurrection.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="87">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And (remember) Dhu'n-Noon (Jonah of the fish), when he went away in anger and imagined We will not test him (with distress). Then he called out from the darkness: "There is no god other than You. All glory to You; surely I was a sinner.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Zun-Noon,* when he left in anger, assuming that We would not restrict him – he therefore called out in the realms of darkness, saying, “There is no God except You, Purity is to You; I have indeed committed a lapse.” (* Prophet Yunus – peace and blessings upon him)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Dhul Nun -- when he went forth enraged and thought that We would have no power over him; then he called out in the darkness, 'There is no god but Thou. Glory be to Thee! I have done evil.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Zun-nun! recall what time he departed in anger and imagined that We could not straiten him, then he cried in the darknesses, that: there is no god but Thou! hallowed be Thou! verily I have been of the wrong-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) Dhan-Nun (Jonah), when he went off in anger, and imagined that We shall not punish him (i.e. the calamites which had befallen him)! But he cried through the darkness (saying): La ilaha illa Anta [none has the right to be worshipped but You (O Allah)], Glorified (and Exalted) are You [above all that (evil) they associate with You]. Truly, I have been of the wrong-doers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Jonah, when he stormed out in fury, thinking We had no power over him. But then He cried out in the darkness, “There is no god but You! Glory to You! I was one of the wrongdoers!”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We bestowed Our favour upon Dhu al-Nun. Recall, when he went forth enraged, thinking We have no power to take him to task. Eventually he cried out in the darkness:" There is no god but You. Glory be to You! I have done wrong."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) Dhun-Nun, when he went off in anger, and imagined that We shall not punish him! But he cried through the darknesses (Zulumat) (saying): "There is no God but You, Glorified be You! Truly, I have been of the Zalimin wrongdoers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (mention) Dhu'n-Nun, when he went off in anger and deemed that We had no power over him, but he cried out in the darkness, saying: There is no Allah save Thee. Be Thou Glorified! Lo! I have been a wrong-doer.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And ThulNun (Prophet Jonah), he went away in anger thinking We had no power over him. But in the darkness he cried: 'There is no god except You. Exaltations to You! I was among the harmdoers'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] the man of the fish, when he went off in anger and thought that We would not decree [anything] upon him. And he called out within the darknesses, "There is no deity except You; exalted are You. Indeed, I have been of the wrongdoers."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Dhun Nun went away in anger and thought that We would never have power over him, but in darkness he cried, "Lord, You are the Only God whom I glorify. I have certainly done wrong to myself (so forgive me)".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Yunus, when he went away in wrath, so he thought that We would not straiten him, so he called out among afflictions: There is no god but Thou, glory be to Thee; surely I am of those who make themselves to suffer loss.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Remember the man in the whale [Jonah] when he went away in anger, thinking We had no power over him. But he cried out in the darkness, "There is no deity but You. Glory be to You! I was indeed wrong."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And remember Zun-nun, when he departed in wrath: He imagined that We had no power over him! But he cried through the deptHs of darkness, "There is no god but thou: glory to thee: I was indeed wrong!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="68" verse="48">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So wait with patience for the judgement of your Lord, and do not be like (onah) of the fish who called (to his Lord) when he was choked with anger.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Therefore wait for your Lord’s command, and do not be like the one of the fish; who cried out when he was distraught. (Prophet Yunus – peace be upon him.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So be thou patient under the judgment of thy Lord, and be not as the Man of the Fish, when he called, choking inwardly.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Be patient thou, then, with thy Lord's judgment, and be thou not like him of the fish, when he cried out while he was in anguish.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So wait with patience for the Decision of your Lord, and be not like the Companion of the Fish, when he cried out (to Us) while he was in deep sorrow. (See the Quran, Verse 21:87).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>So wait patiently for the Decision of your Lord, and do not be like the Fellow of the Fish who cried out in despair.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>So bear with patience until the Judgement of your Lord comes, and do not belike the man in the fish (i.e., Jonah) who called out, choking with grief:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So, wait with patience for the decision of your Lord, and be not like the Companion of the Fish when he cried out (to Us) while he was Makzum.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>But wait thou for thy Lord's decree, and be not like him of the fish, who cried out in despair.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>So be patient with the judgement of your Lord and do not be like the Companion of the Whale (Jonah), when he called out choking inwardly.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Then be patient for the decision of your Lord, [O Muhammad], and be not like the companion of the fish when he called out while he was distressed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Exercise patience until the promise of your Lord (to punish the unbelievers) comes true. Do not be like Jonah (who left his people without the permission of God; he wanted them to be punished immediately),</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So wait patiently for the judgment of your Lord, and be not like the companion of the fish, when he cried while he was in distress.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Wait patiently for your Lord's judgement; do not be like the man who, having been swallowed by a whale, called out in distress.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So wait with patience for the Command of thy Lord, and be not like the Companion of the Fish,- when he cried out in agony.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="68" verse="49">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Had it not been for a favour from his Lord he would have been cast blame-worthy on a barren plain.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Were it not for his Lord’s favour that reached him, he would have surely been cast onto the desolate land, reproached.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Had there not overtaken him a blessing from his Lord he would have been cast upon the wilderness, being condemned.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Had not grace from his Lord reached him, he had surely been cast into the wilderness in a plight.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Had not a Grace from his Lord reached him, he would indeed have been (left in the stomach of the fish, but We forgave him), so he was cast off on the naked shore, while he was to be blamed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Were it not for his Lord’s favor that reached him, he would have been thrown into the wilderness, fully despised.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>had his Lord not bestowed His favour upon him, he would have been cast upon that barren shore (and would have remained there) in disgrace.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Had not a grace from his Lord reached him, he would indeed have been (left in the stomach of the fish, but We forgave him), so he was cast off on the naked shore, while he was to be blamed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Had it not been that favour from his Lord had reached him he surely had been cast into the wilderness while he was reprobate.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Had the favor of his Lord not come upon him, he would have been blamed, cast upon the shore.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>If not that a favor from his Lord overtook him, he would have been thrown onto the naked shore while he was censured.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>and who cried (for help) to his Lord, while imprisoned and helpless inside the fish. Had it not been for a favor from his Lord, he would have been left out in the open, deserving blame for his shortcomings.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Were it not that favor from his Lord had overtaken him, he would certainly have been cast down upon the naked Found while he was blamed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Had his Lord's grace not been bestowed upon him, he would have been cast away in disgrace upon that desolate shore.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Had not Grace from his Lord reached him, he would indeed have been cast off on the naked shore, in disgrace.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="88">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We heard his cry, and saved him from the anguish. That is how We deliver those who believe.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>We therefore heard his prayer and rescued him from grief; and similarly We shall rescue the Muslims.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>So We answered him, and delivered him out of grief; even so do, We deliver the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>So We answered him, and We delivered him from the distress, and Thus do We deliver the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So We answered his call, and delivered him from the distress. And thus We do deliver the believers (who believe in the Oneness of Allah, abstain from evil and work righteousness).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>So We answered him, and saved him from the affliction. Thus We save the faithful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Thereupon We accepted his prayer, and rescued him from grief. Thus do We rescue the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So We answered his call, and delivered him from the distress. And thus We do deliver the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Then we heard his prayer and saved him from the anguish. Thus we save believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We heard his prayer and saved him from grief. As such We shall save the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So We responded to him and saved him from the distress. And thus do We save the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We answered his prayer and saved him from his grief. Thus We save the faithful ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So We responded to him and delivered him from the grief and thus do We deliver the believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>So We heard his prayer and delivered him from sorrow. Thus shall We deliver the true believers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>So We listened to him: and delivered him from distress: and thus do We deliver those who have faith.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="145">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>So We cast him, sick, on a barren shore,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>We then put him ashore on a plain, and he was sick.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>but We cast him upon the wilderness, and he was sick,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then We cast him on a bare desert whilst he was sick.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>But We cast him forth on the naked shore while he was sick,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then We threw him into the wilderness, and he was sick.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>But We threw him on a wide bare tract of land while he was ill;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>But We cast him forth on the naked shore while he was sick,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Then We cast him on a desert shore while he was sick;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>But We cast him, upon the shore, and he was ill,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>But We threw him onto the open shore while he was ill.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We cast him out of the fish unto dry land and he was sick.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Then We cast him on to the vacant surface of the earth while he was sick.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>But We caused him to be cast forth on to the beach, sick as he was,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>But We cast him forth on the naked shore in a state of sickness,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="146">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We made a gourd tree grow over him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We grew a tree of gourd (as a shelter) above him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and We caused to grow over him a tree of gourds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We caused to grow over him a tree, a gourd.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We caused a plant of gourd to grow over him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We made a gourd tree grow over him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and caused a gourd tree to grow over him,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We caused a plant of gourd to grow over him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We caused a tree of gourd to grow above him;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and We caused a pumpkin tree to grow over him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We caused to grow over him a gourd vine.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made a plant of gourd grow up for him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We caused to grow up for him a gourdplant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and We caused a gourd tree to grow over him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We caused to grow, over him, a spreading plant of the gourd kind.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="147">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We sent him to a hundred thousand men or more,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We sent him towards a hundred thousand people, in fact more.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Then We sent him unto a hundred thousand, or more,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We had sent him to a hundred thousand: rather they exceeded.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We sent him to a hundred thousand (people) or even more.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Then We sent him to a hundred thousand, or more.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and We sent him forth to a nation of a hundred thousand or more,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We sent him to a hundred thousand (people) or even more.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We sent him to a hundred thousand (folk) or more</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Then We sent him to a hundred thousand or more,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We sent him to [his people of] a hundred thousand or more.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We sent him to a hundred thousand or more people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We sent him to a hundred thousand, rather they exceeded.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We sent him as a messenger to a hundred thousand people or more,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And We sent him (on a mission) to a hundred thousand (men) or more.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="37" verse="148">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And they came to believe; so We allowed them to enjoy the good things of life for an age.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So they accepted faith – We therefore gave them usage for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and they believed; so We gave them enjoyment for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And they believed, whrefore We let them enjoy life for a season.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And they believed; so We gave them enjoyment for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And they believed, so We gave them enjoyment for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and they believed. So We let them enjoy life for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And they believed; so We gave them enjoyment for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And they believed, therefor We gave them comfort for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and they believed, and We gave them enjoyment for awhile.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And they believed, so We gave them enjoyment [of life] for a time.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They believed in him so We granted them enjoyment for an appointed time.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And they believed, so We gave them provision till a time.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and they believed in him: so We let them live in ease for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And they believed; so We permitted them to enjoy (their life) for a while.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="10" verse="98">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Why has there been no habitation that believed and profited by their faith, except the people of Jonah? When they came to believe, We removed from them the affliction of shame in the world, and made them prosperous for a time.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So if only had there been one dwelling* that believed and its belief would have benefited it – except the nation of Yunus (Jonah)! When they accepted faith, We removed the disgraceful punishment in the life of this world from them, and let them enjoy for a while. (* That was destroyed after being warned.)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Why was there never a city that believed, and its belief profited it? -- Except the people of Jonah; when they believed, We removed from them the chastisement of degradation in this present life, and We gave unto them enjoyment for a time.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Why then was there not a township which believed, so that its faith might have profited it, except the people of Yunus! When they believed, We removed from them the torment of humiliation in the life of the world, and We let them enjoy for a season.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Was there any town (community) that believed (after seeing the punishment), and its Faith (at that moment) saved it (from the punishment)? (The answer is none,) - except the people of Yunus (Jonah); when they believed, We removed from them the torment of disgrace in the life of the (present) world, and permitted them to enjoy for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>If only there was one town that believed and benefited by its belief. Except for the people of Jonah. When they believed, We removed from them the suffering of disgrace in the worldly life, and We gave them comfort for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Did it ever happen that the people of a town believed on seeing God's chastisement and its believing profited them? (There is no such instance) except of the people of Yunus. When they believed We granted them reprieve from humiliating chastisement in this world, and We let them enjoy themselves for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Was there any town (community) that believed (after seeing the punishment), and its faith (at that moment) saved it (from the punishment)-- except the people of Yunus; when they believed, We removed from them the torment of disgrace in the life of the (present) world, and permitted them to enjoy for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>If only there had been a community (of all those that were destroyed of old) that believed and profited by its belief as did the folk of Jonah! When they believed We drew off from them the torment of disgrace in the life of the world and gave them comfort for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Why, was there never a village that believed and its belief benefited them? Except Jonah's nation, when they believed, We spared them from a degrading punishment in this life and We gave them enjoyment for awhile.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Then has there not been a [single] city that believed so its faith benefited it except the people of Jonah? When they believed, We removed from them the punishment of disgrace in worldly life and gave them enjoyment for a time.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Why did no one except the people of Jonah believe (in their punishment before their death) so that they could have benefitted from their faith? When the people of Jonah believed, We saved them from a disgraceful torment in this life and provided them with the means of enjoyment for an appointed time.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And wherefore was there not a town which should believe so that their belief should have profited them but the people of Yunus? When they believed, We removed from them the chastisement of disgrace in this world's life and We gave them provision till a time.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Why was there no other people, save the people of Jonah, who should have believed so that their belief would have benefited them. Once they believed, We lifted the torment of shame from them during their worldly life and let them enjoy Our provision for a while.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Why was there not a single township (among those We warned), which believed,- so its faith should have profited it,- except the people of Jonah? When they believed, We removed from them the penalty of ignominy in the life of the present, and permitted them to enjoy (their life) for a while.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="163">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We have sent revelations to you as We sent revelations to Noah and the prophets (who came) after him; and We sent revelations to Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob, and their offspring, and to Jesus and Job, and to Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and to David We gave the Book of Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed We sent a divine revelation to you (Prophet Mohammed – peace and blessing be upon him) as We did send divine revelations to Nooh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; and We sent divine revelations to Ibrahim (Abraham) and Ismael (Ishmael) and Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob) and their offspring, and Eisa (Jesus) and Ayyub (Job) and Yunus (Jonah) and Haroon (Aaron) and Sulaiman (Solomon), and We bestowed the Zaboor (the Holy Book) upon Dawud (David).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We have revealed to thee as We revealed to Noah, and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, Jesus and Job, Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We have revealed unto thee even as We revealed unto Nuh and the prophets after him, and as We revealed unto Ibrahim and Isma'il and Is-haq and Ya'qub and the tribes, and 'Isa and Ayyub and Yunus and Harun and Sulaiman, and unto Daud We vouchsafed a Scripture.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, We have inspired you (O Muhammad SAW) as We inspired Nuh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; We (also) inspired Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma'il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya'qub (Jacob), and Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya'qub (Jacob)], 'Iesa (Jesus), Ayub (Job), Yunus (Jonah), Harun (Aaron), and Sulaiman (Solomon), and to Dawud (David) We gave the Zabur (Psalms).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We have inspired you, as We had inspired Noah and the prophets after him. And We inspired Abraham, and Ishmael, and Isaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs, and Jesus, and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron, and Solomon. And We gave David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(O Muhammad!) We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the offspring of Jacob, and Jesus and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, We have sent the revelation to you as We sent the revelation to Nuh and the Prophets after him; We (also) sent the revelation to Ibrahim, Isma`il, Ishaq, Ya`qub, and Al-Asbat, (the offspring of the twelve sons of Ya`qub) `Isa, Ayyub, Yunus, Harun, and Sulayman; and to Dawud We gave the Zabur.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! We inspire thee as We inspired Noah and the prophets after him, as We inspired Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob and the tribes, and Jesus and Job and Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and as We imparted unto David the Psalms;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and to the Prophets after him, and We revealed to (Prophets) Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the tribes, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and We gave to David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, We have revealed to you, [O Muhammad], as We revealed to Noah and the prophets after him. And we revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, the Descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and to David We gave the book [of Psalms].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), We have sent revelations to you just as were sent to Noah and the Prophets who lived after him and to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, his descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon. We gave the Psalms to David.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely We have revealed to you as We revealed to Nuh, and the prophets after him, and We revealed to Ibrahim and Ismail and Ishaq and Yaqoub and the tribes, and Isa and Ayub and Yunus and Haroun and Sulaiman and We gave to Dawood</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We have sent revelation to you [Prophet] as We did to Noah and the prophets who came after him, to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon and David, to whom We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We have sent thee inspiration, as We sent it to Noah and the Messengers after him: we sent inspiration to Abraham, Isma'il, Isaac, Jacob and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and solomon, and to David We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="85">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Remember) Ishmael, Edris and Dhu'l-Kifl. They were men of fortitude,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Ismail, and Idrees, and Zul-Kifl; they were all patiently enduring.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Ishmael, Idris, Dhul Kifl -- each was of the patient,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Isma'il and ldris and Zul-Kifl! each were of the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) Isma'il (Ishmael), and Idris (Enoch) and Dhul-Kifl (Isaiah), all were from among As-Sabirin (the patient ones, etc.).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Ishmael, and Enoch, and Ezekiel; each was one of the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And (We bestowed the same favour) upon Ishmael, Idris and Dhu al-Kifl, for they were all steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) Isma`il, Idris and Dhul-Kifl: All were from among the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And (mention) Ishmael, and Idris, and Dhu'l-Kifl. All were of the steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And Ishmael, Idris, and ThulKifl (the son of Job) each were patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] Ishmael and Idrees and Dhul-Kifl; all were of the patient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Ismael, Idris and Dhul Kifl all were people of great patience.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Ismail and Idris and Zulkifl; all were of the patient ones;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Remember Ishmael and Idris and Dhul Kifl: they were all patient and steadfast.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And (remember) Isma'il, Idris, and Zul-kifl, all (men) of constancy and patience;</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="86">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And they were admitted to Our grace. Verily they were among the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy; indeed they are among those who deserve Our proximity.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and We admitted them into Our mercy; they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We caused them to enter into our mercy, verily they are of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We admitted them to Our Mercy. Verily, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy. They were among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy, for they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We admitted them to Our mercy. Verily, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We brought them in unto Our mercy. Lo! they are among the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We admitted them to Our Mercy, for they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We admitted them into Our mercy. Indeed, they were of the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We encompassed them in Our mercy; they were righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We caused them to enter into Our mercy, surely they were of the good ones.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We admitted them to Our mercy. They were all righteous men.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We admitted them to Our mercy: for they were of the righteous ones.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="624">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah:
The Prophet said, "None of you should say that I am better than Yunus (i.e. Jonah)." Musadded added, "Jonah bin Matta."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="128">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, "Whoever says that I am better than Jonah bin Matta, is a liar."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="93" verse="630">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 9</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol09</book_id>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas:
The Prophet said that his Lord said: "It does not befit a slave that he should say that he is better than Jonah (Yunus) bin Matta.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>