<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story query="david, dawud" generated="2026-02-01T21:15:42.766Z">
  <metadata>
    <title>Story generated from search: "david, dawud"</title>
    <verses_count>44</verses_count>
    <translations_count>311</translations_count>
    <reordered>2026-02-01T21:15:42.772Z</reordered>
    <reorder_source>dawud_reorder.csv</reorder_source>
  </metadata>
  <verses>
    <verse chapter="4" verse="163">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We have sent revelations to you as We sent revelations to Noah and the prophets (who came) after him; and We sent revelations to Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob, and their offspring, and to Jesus and Job, and to Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and to David We gave the Book of Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Indeed We sent a divine revelation to you (Prophet Mohammed – peace and blessing be upon him) as We did send divine revelations to Nooh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; and We sent divine revelations to Ibrahim (Abraham) and Ismael (Ishmael) and Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob) and their offspring, and Eisa (Jesus) and Ayyub (Job) and Yunus (Jonah) and Haroon (Aaron) and Sulaiman (Solomon), and We bestowed the Zaboor (the Holy Book) upon Dawud (David).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>We have revealed to thee as We revealed to Noah, and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, Jesus and Job, Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We have revealed unto thee even as We revealed unto Nuh and the prophets after him, and as We revealed unto Ibrahim and Isma'il and Is-haq and Ya'qub and the tribes, and 'Isa and Ayyub and Yunus and Harun and Sulaiman, and unto Daud We vouchsafed a Scripture.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, We have inspired you (O Muhammad SAW) as We inspired Nuh (Noah) and the Prophets after him; We (also) inspired Ibrahim (Abraham), Isma'il (Ishmael), Ishaque (Isaac), Ya'qub (Jacob), and Al-Asbat [the twelve sons of Ya'qub (Jacob)], 'Iesa (Jesus), Ayub (Job), Yunus (Jonah), Harun (Aaron), and Sulaiman (Solomon), and to Dawud (David) We gave the Zabur (Psalms).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We have inspired you, as We had inspired Noah and the prophets after him. And We inspired Abraham, and Ishmael, and Isaac, and Jacob, and the Patriarchs, and Jesus, and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron, and Solomon. And We gave David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(O Muhammad!) We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and the Prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the offspring of Jacob, and Jesus and Job, and Jonah, and Aaron and Solomon, and We gave to David Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, We have sent the revelation to you as We sent the revelation to Nuh and the Prophets after him; We (also) sent the revelation to Ibrahim, Isma`il, Ishaq, Ya`qub, and Al-Asbat, (the offspring of the twelve sons of Ya`qub) `Isa, Ayyub, Yunus, Harun, and Sulayman; and to Dawud We gave the Zabur.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! We inspire thee as We inspired Noah and the prophets after him, as We inspired Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac and Jacob and the tribes, and Jesus and Job and Jonah and Aaron and Solomon, and as We imparted unto David the Psalms;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>We have indeed revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and the prophets after him, and [as] We revealed to Abraham and Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, Jesus and Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon—and We gave David the Psalms—</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah and to the Prophets after him, and We revealed to (Prophets) Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the tribes, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and We gave to David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, We have revealed to you, [O Muhammad], as We revealed to Noah and the prophets after him. And we revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, the Descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon, and to David We gave the book [of Psalms].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), We have sent revelations to you just as were sent to Noah and the Prophets who lived after him and to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, his descendants, Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon. We gave the Psalms to David.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely We have revealed to you as We revealed to Nuh, and the prophets after him, and We revealed to Ibrahim and Ismail and Ishaq and Yaqoub and the tribes, and Isa and Ayub and Yunus and Haroun and Sulaiman and We gave to Dawood</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We have sent revelation to you [Prophet] as We did to Noah and the prophets who came after him, to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and Solomon and David, to whom We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We have sent thee inspiration, as We sent it to Noah and the Messengers after him: we sent inspiration to Abraham, Isma'il, Isaac, Jacob and the Tribes, to Jesus, Job, Jonah, Aaron, and solomon, and to David We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="6" verse="84">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided them, as We had guided Noah before them, and of his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus We reward those who are upright and do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq (Isaac) and Yaqub (Jacob); We guided all of them; and We guided Nooh before them and of his descendants, Dawud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Moosa and Haroon; and this is the way We reward the virtuous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave to him Isaac and Jacob -- each one We guided, And Noah We guided before; and of his seed David and Solomon, Job and Joseph, Moses and Aaron -- even so We recompense the good-doers --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Is-haq and Ya'qub: each one We guided. And Nuh We had guided afore, and of his progeny Da-ud and Sulaiman and Ayyub and Yusuf and Musa and Harun. And thus We recompense the well-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaque (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob), each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh (Noah), and among his progeny Dawud (David), Sulaiman (Solomon), Ayub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses), and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob—each of them We guided. And We guided Noah previously; and from his descendants David, and Solomon, and Job, and Joseph, and Moses, and Aaron. Thus We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And We bestowed upon Abraham (offspring) Ishaq (Isaac) and Ya'qub (Jacob) and each of them did We guide to the right way as We had earlier guided Noah to the right way; and (of his descendants We guided) Da'ud (David) and Sulayman (Solomon), Ayyub (Job), Yusuf (Joseph), Musa (Moses) and Harun (Aaron). Thus do We reward those who do good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Ishaq and Ya`qub, each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nuh and among his progeny Dawud, Sulayman, Ayyub, Yusuf, Musa, and Harun. Thus do We reward the good-doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed upon him Isaac and Jacob; each of them We guided; and Noah did We guide aforetime; and of his seed (We guided) David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided each of them. And Noah We had guided before, and from his offspring, David and Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron—thus do We reward the virtuous—</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob and guided both; and We guided Noah before them, among his descendants were David and Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron as such, We recompense the gooddoers,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob - all [of them] We guided. And Noah, We guided before; and among his descendants, David and Solomon and Job and Joseph and Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the doers of good.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave (Abraham) Isaac and Jacob. Both had received Our guidance. Noah received Our guidance before Abraham and so did his descendants: David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron. Thus is the reward for the righteous people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave to him Ishaq and Yaqoub; each did We guide, and Nuh did We guide before, and of his descendants, Dawood and Sulaiman and Ayub and Yusuf and Musa and Haroun; and thus do We reward those who do good (to others).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob, each of whom We guided as We had guided Noah before. Among his descendants were David and Solomon, and Job, Joseph, Moses and Aaron. Thus do We reward the righteous.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We gave him Isaac and Jacob: all (three) guided: and before him, We guided Noah, and among his progeny, David, Solomon, Job, Joseph, Moses, and Aaron: thus do We reward those who do good:</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="17" verse="55">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Your Lord knows whoever is in the heavens and the earth. We exalted some of the prophets over the others; and to David We gave the Book of Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And your Lord knows well all those who are in the heavens and the earth; and indeed among the Prophets We gave excellence to some above others, and We gave the Zaboor to Dawud.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And thy Lord knows very well all who are in the heavens and the earth; and We have preferred some Prophets over others; and We gave to David Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And thine Lord is the Best Knower of those who are in the heavens and the earth. And assuredly We have preferred some prophets over some others: and We vouchsafed unto Daud a Scripture.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And your Lord knows best all who are in the heavens and the earth. And indeed, We have preferred some of the Prophets above others, and to Dawud (David) We gave the Zabur (Psalms).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Your Lord knows well everyone in the heavens and the earth. We have given some prophets advantage over others; and to David We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Your Lord knows all who dwell in the heavens and the earth. We have exalted some Prophets over others, and We gave the Psalms to David.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And your Lord knows best all who are in the heavens and the earth. And indeed, We have preferred some of the Prophets above others, and to Dawud We gave the Zabur.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And thy Lord is Best Aware of all who are in the heavens and the earth. And we preferred some of the prophets above others, and unto David We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Your Lord knows best whoever is in the heavens and the earth. Certainly, We gave some prophets an advantage over the others, and We gave David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Your Lord knows very well all who are in the heavens and the earth. We have preferred some Prophets above others, and to David We gave the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And your Lord is most knowing of whoever is in the heavens and the earth. And We have made some of the prophets exceed others [in various ways], and to David We gave the book [of Psalms].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We have given preference to some Prophets over others and We gave the psalms to David.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And your Lord best knows those who are in the heavens and the earth; and certainly We have made some of the prophets to excel others, and to Dawood We gave a scripture.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Your Lord knows best about everyone in the heavens and on the earth. We gave some prophets more than others: We gave David the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And it is your Lord that knoweth best all beings that are in the heavens and on earth: We did bestow on some prophets more (and other) gifts than on others: and We gave to David (the gift of) the Psalms.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="2" verse="251">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>By the will of God they defeated them, and David killed Goliath, and God gave him kingship and wisdom, and taught him whatsoever He pleased. If God did not make men deter one another this earth would indeed be depraved. But gracious is God to the people of the world.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>So they routed them by the command of Allah; and Dawud (David) slew Jalut, and Allah gave him the kingdom and wisdom, and taught him all whatever He willed; and if Allah does not ward off some men by others, the earth will be destroyed, but Allah is Most Munificent towards the entire creation.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And they routed them, by the leave of God, and David slew Goliath; and God gave him the kingship, and Wisdom, and He taught him such as He willed. Had God not driven back the people, some by the means of others, the earth had surely corrupted; but God is bounteous unto all beings.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Then they vanquished them by the leave of Allah, and Da'ud slew Jalut, and Allah vouchsafed him dominion, and Wisdom and taught him of that which He Willed. And, it not for Allah's repelling people, some of them by means of others, the earth surely were corrupted; but Allah is Gracious unto the Worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>So they routed them by Allah's Leave and Dawud (David) killed Jalut (Goliath), and Allah gave him [Dawud (David)] the kingdom [after the death of Talut (Saul) and Samuel] and Al-Hikmah (Prophethood), and taught him of that which He willed. And if Allah did not check one set of people by means of another, the earth would indeed be full of mischief. But Allah is full of Bounty to the 'Alamin (mankind, jinns and all that exists).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And they defeated them by God’s leave, and David killed Goliath, and God gave him sovereignty and wisdom, and taught him as He willed. Were it not for God restraining the people, some by means of others, the earth would have gone to ruin. But God is gracious towards mankind.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Consequently, by Allah's grace, they routed the unbelievers, and David killed Goliath; and Allah gave him kingship and wisdom and taught him whatever other things He willed. And if Allah had not been repelling one set of people by means of another, the earth would have been filled with chaos. But Allah is bountiful to the world (and so repels chaos in this way).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>So they routed them by Allah's leave and Dawud (David) killed Jalut (Goliath), and Allah gave him (Dawud) the kingdom [after the death of Talut and Samuel] and Al-Hikmah (prophethood), and taught him of that which He willed. And if Allah did not check one set of people by means of another, the earth would indeed be full of mischief. But Allah is full of bounty to the `Alamin (mankind, Jinn and all that exists).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>So they routed them by Allah's leave and David slew Goliath; and Allah gave him the kingdom and wisdom, and taught him of that which He willeth. And if Allah had not repelled some men by others the earth would have been corrupted. But Allah is a Lord of Kindness to (His) creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Thus they routed them with Allah’s will, and David killed Goliath, and Allah gave him kingdom and wisdom and taught him whatever He liked. Were it not for Allah’s repelling the people by means of one another, the earth would surely have been corrupted; but Allah is gracious to the world’s people.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>By the permission of Allah, they routed them. David slew Goliath, and Allah bestowed on him the kingship and wisdom, and taught him from that He willed. Had Allah not pushed the people, some by the other, the earth would have been corrupted. But Allah is Bountiful to the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>So they defeated them by permission of Allah, and David killed Goliath, and Allah gave him the kingship and prophethood and taught him from that which He willed. And if it were not for Allah checking [some] people by means of others, the earth would have been corrupted, but Allah is full of bounty to the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They defeated their enemy through God's will. David slew Goliath and God granted David the kingdom and wisdom and also taught him whatever He wanted. Had God not made one group of people repel the other, the earth would have become full of corruption, but God is generous to His creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So they put them to flight by Allah's permission. And Dawood slew Jalut, and Allah gave him kingdom and wisdom, and taught him of what He pleased. And were it not for Allah's repelling some men with others, the earth would certainly be in a state of disorder; but Allah is Gracious to the creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>And so by the command of God they defeated them. David killed Goliath, and God gave him kingship and wisdom, and imparted to him the knowledge of whatever He willed. Had it not been for God's repelling some people by means of others, the earth would have been filled with corruption. But God is bountiful to His creatures.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>By Allah's will they routed them; and David slew Goliath; and Allah gave him power and wisdom and taught him whatever (else) He willed. And did not Allah Check one set of people by means of another, the earth would indeed be full of mischief: But Allah is full of bounty to all the worlds.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="10">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We favoured David with excellence, (and commanded): "O Jibal and Tair, glorify the greatness of God with him." And We made iron pliable for him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And indeed We gave Dawud the utmost excellence from Us; “O the hills and birds, repent towards Allah along with him”; and We made iron soft for him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave David bounty from Us: 'O you mountains, echo God's praises with him, and you birds!' And We softened for him iron:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We vouchsafed Unto Da'ud grace from us,' and said: mountains! repeat Our praise with him; and also ye birds! And We softened for him the iron.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We bestowed grace on David from Us (saying): "O you mountains. Glorify (Allah) with him! And you birds (also)! And We made the iron soft for him."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We bestowed upon David favor from Us: “O mountains, and birds: echo with him.” And We softened iron for him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We bestowed Our favour upon David. (We commanded): “O mountains, sing Allah's praises with him”; (and so did We command) the birds. We softened the iron for him, (saying):</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed We bestowed grace on Dawud from Us (saying): "O you mountains! Glorify with him! And you birds (also)! And We made the iron soft for him."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And assuredly We gave David grace from Us, (saying): O ye hills and birds, echo his psalms of praise! And We made the iron supple unto him,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly We gave David our grace: ‘O mountains and birds, chime in with him!’ And We made iron soft for him,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave David bounty from Us. 'O mountains, and birds, echo (the praise of Allah) with him' And We softened iron for him,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We certainly gave David from Us bounty. [We said], "O mountains, repeat [Our] praises with him, and the birds [as well]." And We made pliable for him iron,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We granted David a favor by commanding the mountains and birds to sing Our praise along with him and softened iron for him</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We gave to Dawood excellence from Us: O mountains! sing praises with him, and the birds; and We made the iron pliant to him,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We bestowed upon David great favour. We said, "O mountains and birds! Join with him in celebrating Our praise." We softened iron for him, saying,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We bestowed Grace aforetime on David from ourselves: "O ye Mountains! Sing ye back the Praises of Allah with him! and ye birds (also)! And We made the iron soft for him;-</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="17">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Bear with patience what they say, and remember Our votary David, man of strength. He surely turned to Us in penitence.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Have patience upon what they say, and remember Our bondman Dawud, the one blessed with favours; he is indeed most inclined (towards His Lord).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Bear patiently what they say, and remember Our servant David, the man of might; he was a penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Bear thou with that which they say, and remember Our bondman, Da-ud, endured with strength; verily he was oft-returning onto Us.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Be patient (O Muhammad SAW) of what they say, and remember Our slave Dawud (David), endued with power. Verily, he was ever oft-returning in all matters and in repentance (toward Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Be patient in the face of what they say, and mention Our servant David, the resourceful. He was obedient.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(O Prophet), bear with patience what they say, and call to mind Our servant David, who was endowed with great strength and who constantly turned (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Be patient of what they say and remember Our slave Dawud, endued with Al-Ayd. Verily, he was ever oft-returning in all matters and in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Bear with what they say, and remember Our bondman David, lord of might, Lo! he was ever turning in repentance (toward Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Be patient over what they say, and remember Our servant, David, [the man] of strength. Indeed he was a penitent [soul].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Bear patiently with what they say, and remember Our worshiper David, a man of might. He was ever turning in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Be patient over what they say and remember Our servant, David, the possessor of strength; indeed, he was one who repeatedly turned back [to Allah].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>(Muhammad), bear patiently what they say and recall Our servant, David, who had strong hands and who was most repentant.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Bear patiently what they say, and remember Our servant Dawood, the possessor of power; surely he was frequent in returning (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Bear with their words patiently. Remember Our servant David, a man of strength who always turned to Us:</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Have patience at what they say, and remember our servant David, the man of strength: for he ever turned (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="18">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We subjugated the chiefs (of tribes) to struggle day and night with him,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>With him We subjected the mountains to give glory at evening and sunrise,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Verily We so subjected the mountains that they should hallow Us with him at nightfall and sunrise.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Verily, We made the mountains to glorify Our Praises with him [Dawud (David)] in the 'Ashi (i.e. after the mid-day till sunset) and Ishraq (i.e. after the sunrise till mid-day).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>We committed the mountains to glorify with him, in the evening and at daybreak.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>With him We had subjected the mountains that they join him in celebrating Allah's glory, evening and morning,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Verily, We made the mountains to glorify Our praises with him in the `Ashi and Ishraq.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Lo! We subdued the hills to hymn the praises (of their Lord) with him at nightfall and sunrise,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>We disposed the mountains to glorify [Allah] with him at evening and dawn,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We subjected the mountains to exalt (Me) with him in the evening and at sunrise,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Indeed, We subjected the mountains [to praise] with him, exalting [Allah] in the [late] afternoon and [after] sunrise.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made the mountains join him in glorifying Us in the evening and in the morning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Surely We made the mountains to sing the glory (of Allah) in unison with him at the evening and the sunrise,</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We made the mountains join him in glorifying Us at sunset and sunrise;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>It was We that made the hills declare, in unison with him, Our Praises, at eventide and at break of day,</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="19">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.hilali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>And the levied Tair. They were all obedient to him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and the birds, duly mustered, every one to him reverting;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And the birds also, gathering all oft-returning onto Him on his account.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (so did) the birds assembled: all with him [Dawud (David)] did turn (to Allah i.e. glorified His Praises).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And the birds, gathered together. All obedient to him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>and the birds, too, in their flocks, and turn again and again to celebrating Allah's glory.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (so did) the birds assembled, all obedient to him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And the birds assembled; all were turning unto Him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>and the birds [as well], mustered [in flocks]; all echoing him [in a chorus].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>and the birds, too, gathered each obedient to him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And the birds were assembled, all with him repeating [praises].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made the birds assemble around him in flocks.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And the birds gathered together; all joined in singing with him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>and the birds, too, in flocks, all turned to Him.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And the birds gathered (in assemblies): all with him did turn (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="15">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We gave David and Solomon knowledge; and they said: "All praise be to God who has favoured us over many of His creatures who believe."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We indeed bestowed great knowledge to Dawud and Sulaiman; and they both said, “All praise is to Allah, Who bestowed us superiority over many of His believing bondmen.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave David and Solomon knowledge and they said, 'Praise belongs to God who has preferred us over many of His believing servants.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And assuredly We vouchsafed unto Daud and Sulaiman a knowledge, and the twain said: praise unto Allah Who hath preferred us above many of His believing bondmen!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And indeed We gave knowledge to Dawud (David) and Sulaiman (Solomon), and they both said: "All the praises and thanks be to Allah, Who has preferred us above many of His believing slaves!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We gave David and Solomon knowledge. They said, “Praise God, who has favored us over many of His believing servants.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(On the other hand), We granted knowledge to David and Solomon and they said: "All praise be to Allah Who has exalted us above many of His believing servants!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And indeed We gave knowledge to Dawud and Sulayman, and they both said: "All praise be to Allah, Who has preferred us above many of His believing servants!"</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We verily gave knowledge unto David and Solomon, and they said: Praise be to Allah, Who hath preferred us above many of His believing slaves!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Certainly, We gave knowledge to David and Solomon, and they said, ‘All praise belongs to Allah, who granted us an advantage over many of His faithful servants.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave knowledge to David and Solomon. They said: 'Praise be to Allah who has preferred us above many of His believing worshipers'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We had certainly given to David and Solomon knowledge, and they said, "Praise [is due] to Allah, who has favored us over many of His believing servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We gave knowledge to David and Soloman. They said, "It is only God who deserves all praise. He has exalted us above many of His believing servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And certainly We gave knowledge to Dawood and Sulaiman, and they both said: Praise be to Allah, Who has made us to excel many of His believing servants.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We bestowed knowledge on David and Solomon and they both said, "Praise be to God who has exalted us above many of His believing servants."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>We gave (in the past) knowledge to David and Solomon: And they both said: "Praise be to Allah, Who has favoured us above many of his servants who believe!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="22">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>When they came before David, he was frightened of them. "Do not be afraid," they said. "The two of us are disputing the wrong one has done the other. So judge between us with equity, and do not be unjust, and guide us to the right path.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>When they entered upon David, so he feared them – they said, “Do not fear! We are two disputants, one of whom has wronged the other, therefore judge fairly between us and do not judge unjustly – and show us the right way.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>when they entered upon David, and he took fright at them; and they said, 'Fear not; two disputants we are -- one of us has injured the other; so judge between us justly, and transgress not, and guide us to the right path.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>When they went in unto Da-ud, he was frightened at them. They said: fear not we are two contending parties; one of us hath oppressed the other, so judge between us with truth, and be not iniquitious, and guide us unto the even path.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>When they entered in upon Dawud (David), he was terrified of them, they said: "Fear not! (We are) two litigants, one of whom has wronged the other, therefore judge between us with truth, and treat us not with injustice, and guide us to the Right Way.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>When they entered upon David, and he was startled by them. They said, “Do not fear. Two disputants; one of us has wronged the other; so judge between us fairly, and do not be biased, and guide us to the straight way.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>As they came upon David -- and he was frightened of them -- they said: “Be not afraid. We are just two litigants: one of us has committed excess against the other. So judge rightly between us, and be not unjust; and guide us to the Right Way.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>When they entered in upon Dawud, he was terrified of them. They said: "Fear not! (We are) two litigants, one of us has wronged the other, therefore judge between us with truth, and treat us not with injustice, and guide us to the right way.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>How they burst in upon David, and he was afraid of them. They said: Be not afraid! (We are) two litigants, one of whom hath wronged the other, therefor judge aright between us; be not unjust; and show us the fair way.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>When they entered into the presence of David, he was alarmed by them. They said, ‘Do not be afraid. [We are only] two contenders: one of us has bullied the other. So judge justly between us, and do not exceed [the bounds of justice], and show us the right path.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>they went to David whereupon he was afraid of them, but they said: 'Do not be afraid, we are two that have a dispute, one of us has wronged the other. Judge between us justly, and do not transgress, and guide us to the Right Path.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>When they entered upon David and he was alarmed by them? They said, "Fear not. [We are] two adversaries, one of whom has wronged the other, so judge between us with truth and do not exceed [it] and guide us to the sound path.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>and entered where David was (praying). He was frightened, so they said, "Do not be afraid. We are only two disputing parties of which one of us has transgressed against the other. Judge between us with truth and justice and guide us to the right path".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>When they entered in upon Dawood and he was frightened at them, they said: Fear not; two litigants, of whom one has acted wrongfully towards the other, therefore decide between us with justice, and do not act unjustly, and guide us to the right way.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>When they reached David, he took fright, but they said, "Do not be afraid. We are two disputants, one of whom has wronged the other: judge between us fairly, do not be unjust, and guide us to the right path.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>When they entered the presence of David, and he was terrified of them, they said: "Fear not: we are two disputants, one of whom has wronged the other: Decide now between us with truth, and treat us not with injustice, but guide us to the even Path..</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="24">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(David) said: "He is unjust in demanding your ewe to add to his (many) ewes. Many partners are surely -- unjust to one another, except those who believe and do the right; but there are only a few of them." It occurred to David that he was being tried by Us, and he begged his Lord to forgive him, and fell down in homage and repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Said Dawud, “He is indeed being unjust to you in that he demands to add your ewe to his ewes; and indeed most partners wrong one another, except those who believe and do good deeds – and they are very few!” Thereupon Dawud realised that We had tested him, so he sought forgiveness from his Lord, and fell prostrate and inclined (towards his Lord). (Command of Prostration # 10)</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Said he, 'Assuredly he has wronged thee in asking for thy ewe in addition to his sheep; and indeed many intermixers do injury one against the other, save those who believe, and do deeds of righteousness -- and how few they are!' And David thought that We had only tried him; therefore he sought forgiveness of his Lord, and he fell down, bowing, and he repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Da-ud said: assuredly he hath wronged thee in demanding thine ewe in addition to his ewes, and verily many of the partners oppress each other save such as believe and work righteous works, and few are they. And Da-ud imagined that We had tried him; so he asked forgiveness of his Lord, and he fell down bowing and turned in penitence.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>[Dawud (David)] said (immediately without listening to the opponent): "He has wronged you in demanding your ewe in addition to his ewes. And, verily, many partners oppress one another, except those who believe and do righteous good deeds, and they are few." And Dawud (David) guessed that We have tried him and he sought Forgiveness of his Lord, and he fell down prostrate and turned (to Allah) in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>He said, “He has done you wrong by asking your ewe in addition to his ewes. Many partners take advantage of one another, except those who believe and do good deeds, but these are so few.” David realized that We were testing him, so he sought forgiveness from his Lord, and fell down to his knees, and repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>David said: “He has certainly wronged you in seeking to add your ewe to his ewes; and indeed many who live together commit excesses, one to the other, except those that believe and act righteously; and they are but few.” (While so saying) David realized that it is We Who have put him to test; therefore, he sought the forgiveness of his Lord, and fell down, bowing and penitently turning (to Him).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>[Dawud] said: "He has wronged you in demanding your ewe in addition to his ewes. And, verily, many partners oppress one another, except those who believe and do righteous good deeds, and they are few." And Dawud guessed that We have tried him and he sought forgiveness of his Lord, and he fell down prostrate and turned (to Allah) in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>(David) said: He hath wronged thee in demanding thine ewe in addition to his ewes, and lo! many partners oppress one another, save such as believe and do good works, and they are few. And David guessed that We had tried him, and he sought forgiveness of his Lord, and he bowed himself and fell down prostrate and repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>He said, ‘He has certainly wronged you by asking your ewe in addition to his own ewes, and indeed many partners bully one another, except such as have faith and do righteous deeds, and few are they.’ Then David knew that We had tested him, whereat he pleaded with his Lord for forgiveness, and fell down in prostration and repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>He (David) replied: 'He has without doubt wronged you in seeking to add your ewe to his sheep. Many intermixers wrong one another; except those who believe, and do good works, and they are few indeed' David realized that We had tried him and sought the forgiveness of his Lord and fell down, prostrate and repented.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[David] said, "He has certainly wronged you in demanding your ewe [in addition] to his ewes. And indeed, many associates oppress one another, except for those who believe and do righteous deeds - and few are they." And David became certain that We had tried him, and he asked forgiveness of his Lord and fell down bowing [in prostration] and turned in repentance [to Allah].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>David said, "He has certainly been unjust in demanding your ewe from you. Most partners transgress against each other except for the righteously striving believers who are very few." David realized that it was a test from Us so he asked forgiveness from his Lord and knelt down before him in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>He said: Surely he has been unjust to you in demanding your ewe (to add) to his own ewes; and most surely most of the partners act wrongfully towards one another, save those who believe and do good, and very few are they; and Dawood was sure that We had tried him, so he sought the protection of his Lord and he fell down bowing and turned time after time (to Him).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>David said, "He has certainly wronged you by demanding that your ewe be added to his ewes! Thus many partners wrong one another -- [all] save those who believe [in God] and do righteous deeds: but how few are they!" And [suddenly] David understood that We were only putting him to the test, and so he asked his Lord to forgive him his sins; he fell to his knees, and turned to Him in repentance.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>(David) said: "He has undoubtedly wronged thee in demanding thy (single) ewe to be added to his (flock of) ewes: truly many are the partners (in business) who wrong each other: Not so do those who believe and work deeds of righteousness, and how few are they?"... and David gathered that We had tried him: he asked forgiveness of his Lord, fell down, bowing (in prostration), and turned (to Allah in repentance).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="26">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>"O David, We have made you trustee on the earth. So judge between men equitably, and do not follow your lust lest it should lead you astray from the way of God. Surely for those who go astray from the way of God, is severe punishment, for having forgotten the Day of Reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>“O Dawud! We have indeed appointed you as a Viceroy in the earth, therefore judge between mankind with the truth, and do not follow desire for it will lead you astray from Allah’s path; indeed for those who stray away from Allah’s path is a severe punishment, because they forgot the Day of Reckoning.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>'David, behold, We have appointed thee a viceroy in the earth; therefore judge between men justly, and follow not caprice, lest it lead thee astray from the way of God. Surely those who go astray from the way of God -- there awaits them a terrible chastisement, for that they have forgotten the Day of Reckoning.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>O Da-ud! verily We have appointed thee a vicegerent in the earth, so judge between mankind with truth, and follow not desire, lest it cause thee to err from the path of Allah. Verily those who err from the path of Allah - Unto them shall be a severe torment, for they forgat the Day of Reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>O Dawud (David)! Verily! We have placed you as a successor on earth, so judge you between men in truth (and justice) and follow not your desire for it will mislead you from the Path of Allah. Verily! Those who wander astray from the Path of Allah (shall) have a severe torment, because they forgot the Day of Reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>“O David, We made you a ruler in the land, so judge between the people with justice, and do not follow desire, lest it diverts you from God’s path. Those who stray from God’s path will have a painful punishment, for having ignored the Day of Account.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>(We said to him): “O David, We have appointed you vicegerent on earth. Therefore, rule among people with justice and do not follow (your) desire lest it should lead you astray from Allah's Path. Allah's severe chastisement awaits those who stray away from Allah's Path, for they had forgotten the Day of Reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>O Dawud! Verily, We have placed you as a successor on the earth; so judge you between men in truth (and justice) and follow not your desire -- for it will mislead you from the path of Allah. Verily, those who wander astray from the path of Allah (shall) have a severe torment, because they forgot the Day of Reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>(And it was said unto him): O David! Lo! We have set thee as a viceroy in the earth; therefor judge aright between mankind, and follow not desire that it beguile thee from the way of Allah. Lo! those who wander from the way of Allah have an awful doom, forasmuch as they forgot the Day of Reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>‘O David! Indeed, We have made you a vicegerent on the earth. So judge between people with justice, and do not follow your desires, or they will lead you astray from the way of Allah. Indeed there is a severe punishment for those who stray from the way of Allah, because of their forgetting the Day of Reckoning.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>(We said): 'David, We have made you a caliph in the earth. Judge with justice among people and do not yield to your own preference in case it should lead you from the Path of Allah. Surely, a terrible punishment awaits those who stray from the Path of Allah, because they forget the Day of Reckoning'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>[We said], "O David, indeed We have made you a successor upon the earth, so judge between the people in truth and do not follow [your own] desire, as it will lead you astray from the way of Allah." Indeed, those who go astray from the way of Allah will have a severe punishment for having forgotten the Day of Account.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We told him. "David, We have appointed you as Our deputy on earth so judge among the people with truth. Do not follow (worldly) desires lest you go astray from the way of God. Those who go astray from the way of God will suffer severe torment for forgetting the Day of Reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>o Dawood! surely We have made you a ruler in the land; so judge between men with justice and do not follow desire, lest it should lead you astray from the path of Allah; (as for) those who go astray from the path of Allah, they shall surely have a severe punishment because they forgot the day of reckoning.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We said, "David, We have given you mastery over the land. Judge fairly between people. Do not follow your desires, lest they divert you from God's path: those who wander from His path will have a severe punishment, because they ignore the Day of Reckoning."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>O David! We did indeed make thee a vicegerent on earth: so judge thou between men in truth (and justice): Nor follow thou the lusts (of thy heart), for they will mislead thee from the Path of Allah: for those who wander astray from the Path of Allah, is a Penalty Grievous, for that they forget the Day of Account.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="78">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>(Remember) David and Solomon, when they pronounced judgement about the field which was eaten up at night by sheep belonging to certain people. We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And remember Dawud and Sulaiman, when they were deciding the dispute of a field, when some people’s sheep had strayed into it at night; and We were Present at the time of their deciding.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And David and Solomon -- when they gave judgment concerning the tillage, when the sheep of the people strayed there, and We bore witness to their judgment;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Daud and Sulaiman! recall what time they gave judgment regarding the tillage when certain people's sheep had pastured therein at night; and of the judgment concerning them We were the Witnesses.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And (remember) Dawud (David) and Sulaiman (Solomon), when they gave judgement in the case of the field in which the sheep of certain people had pastured at night and We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And David and Solomon, when they gave judgment in the case of the field, when some people’s sheep wandered therein by night; and We were witnesses to their judgment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We bestowed the same favour upon David and Solomon. Recall, when they gave judgement regarding a tillage into which the sheep of some people had strayed at night, and We were witnesses to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And (remember) Dawud and Sulayman, when they gave judgement in the case of the field in which the sheep of certain people had Nafashat; and We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And David and Solomon, when they gave judgment concerning the field, when people's sheep had strayed and browsed therein by night; and We were witnesses to their judgment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And [remember] David and Solomon when they gave judgement concerning the tillage when the sheep of some people strayed into it by night, and We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>And David and Solomon they passed judgment upon the tilled land on which the people? s sheep had strayed. We bore witness to their judgment, and</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And [mention] David and Solomon, when they judged concerning the field - when the sheep of a people overran it [at night], and We were witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>David and Solomon were trying to settle the case of the people's sheep that grazed in a corn-field at night. We witnessed their decree in that matter.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Dawood and Sulaiman when they gave judgment concerning the field when the people's sheep pastured therein by night, and We were bearers of witness to their judgment.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Tell of David and Solomon who both passed judgement on the field into which some people's sheep had strayed [and grazed] at night. We bore witness to their judgement.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And remember David and Solomon, when they gave judgment in the matter of the field into which the sheep of certain people had strayed by night: We did witness their judgment.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="79">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We made Solomon understand the case, and bestowed on each wisdom and knowledge, We subdued the al-jibal (mountains) with David to sing Our praises, and at-tair (birds). It is We who did it.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We explained the case to Sulaiman; and to both We gave the kingdom and knowledge; and subjected the hills to proclaim the Purity along with Dawud, and (also subjected) the birds; and these were Our works.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>and We made Solomon to understand it, and unto each gave We judgment and knowledge. And with David We subjected the mountains to give glory, and the birds, and We were doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>So We gave the understanding thereof unto Sulaiman; and unto each We vouchsafed judgment and knowledge. And We so subjected the mountains that they shall hallow us along with Daud, and also the birds; and We were the doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And We made Sulaiman (Solomon) to understand (the case), and to each of them We gave Hukman (right judgement of the affairs and Prophethood) and knowledge. And We subjected the mountains and the birds to glorify Our Praises along with Dawud (David), And it was We Who were the doers (of all these things).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And so We made Solomon understand it, and to each We gave wisdom and knowledge. And We subjected the mountains along with David to sing Our praises, and the birds as well—surely We did.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We guided Solomon to the right verdict, and We had granted each of them judgement and knowledge. We made the mountains and the birds celebrate the praise of Allah with David. It was We Who did all this.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And We made Sulayman to understand (the case); and to each of them We gave wisdom (Hukm) and knowledge. And We subjected the mountains and the birds to glorify Our praises along with Dawud. And it was We Who were the doer (of all these things).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We made Solomon to understand (the case); and unto each of them We gave judgment and knowledge. And we subdued the hills and the birds to hymn (His) praise along with David. We were the doers (thereof).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>We gave its understanding to Solomon, and to each We gave judgement and knowledge. We disposed the mountains and the birds to glorify [Us] with David, and We have been the doer [of these things].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We made Solomon to understand it, and to both We gave judgment and knowledge. And with David We subjected the mountains and birds to exalt (Allah). All this We have done.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And We gave understanding of the case to Solomon, and to each [of them] We gave judgement and knowledge. And We subjected the mountains to exalt [Us], along with David and [also] the birds. And We were doing [that].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We made Solomon understand the law about the case and gave both David and Solomon knowledge and wisdom. We made the mountains and birds glorify the Lord along with David. We had also done to him such favors before.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>So We made Sulaiman to understand it; and to each one We gave wisdom and knowledge; and We made the mountains, and the birds to celebrate Our praise with Dawood; and We were the doers.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave Solomon the right understanding of the matter, and We bestowed wisdom and knowledge on both of them. We caused the mountains and the birds to celebrate Our praises along with David. We had the power to do this --</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>To Solomon We inspired the (right) understanding of the matter: to each (of them) We gave Judgment and Knowledge; it was Our power that made the hills and the birds celebrate Our praises, with David: it was We Who did (all these things).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="80" verse="760">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah's Apostle said, "There were two women with whom there were their two sons. A wolf came and took away the son of one of them. That lady said to her companion, 'The wolf has taken your son.' The other said, 'But it has taken your son.' So both of them sought the judgment of (the Prophet) David who judged that the boy should be given to the older lady. Then both of them went to (the Prophet) Solomon, son of David and informed him of the case. Solomon said, 'Give me a knife so that I may cut the child into two portions and give one half to each of you.' The younger lady said, 'Do not do so; may Allah bless you ! He is her child.' On that, he gave the child to the younger lady." Abu Huraira added: By Allah! I had never heard the word 'Sakkin' as meaning knife, except on that day, for we used to call it 'Mudya"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="5" verse="78">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Cursed were disbelievers among the children of Israel by David and Jesus, son of Mary, because they rebelled and transgressed the bounds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>Those among the Descendants of Israel who turned disbelievers were cursed by the tongue of Dawud, and of Eisa the son of Maryam; it was because of their disobedience and their rebellion.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>Cursed were the unbelievers of the Children of Israel by the tongue of David, and Jesus, Mary's son; that, for their rebelling and their transgression.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>Cursed were those who disbelieved from among the Children of Isra'il by the tongue of Daud and 'Isa, son of Maryam. That is because they disobeyed and were ever transgressing.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>Those among the Children of Israel who disbelieved were cursed by the tongue of Dawud (David) and 'Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary). That was because they disobeyed (Allah and the Messengers) and were ever transgressing beyond bounds.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>Cursed were those who disbelieved from among the Children of Israel by the tongue of David and Jesus son of Mary. That is because they rebelled and used to transgress.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>Those of the Children of Israel who took to unbelief have been cursed by the tongue of David and Jesus, son of Mary, for they rebelled and exceeded the bounds of right.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>Those among the Children of Israel who disbelieved were cursed by the tongue of Dawud and `Isa, son of Maryam. That was because they disobeyed (Allah and the Messengers) and were ever transgressing (beyond the bounds).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>Those of the Children of Israel who went astray were cursed by the tongue of David, and of Jesus, son of Mary. That was because they rebelled and used to transgress.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>The faithless among the Children of Israel were cursed on the tongue of David and Jesus son of Mary. That, because they would disobey and they used to commit transgression.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Those who disbelieved of the Children of Israel were cursed by the tongue of (Prophets) David and Jesus, the son of Mary, because they disobeyed and transgressed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>Cursed were those who disbelieved among the Children of Israel by the tongue of David and of Jesus, the son of Mary. That was because they disobeyed and [habitually] transgressed.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>The unbelievers among the Israelites, because of their disobedience and transgression, were condemned by David and Jesus, the son of Mary for their disobedience; they were transgressors.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>Those who disbelieved from among the children of Israel were cursed by the tongue of Dawood and Isa, son of Marium; this was because they disobeyed and used to exceed the limit.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Those of the Children of Israel who were bent on denying the truth were cursed by David and Jesus, the son of Mary. That was because they disobeyed and were given to transgression;</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>Curses were pronounced on those among the Children of Israel who rejected Faith, by the tongue of David and of Jesus the son of Mary: because they disobeyed and persisted in excesses.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="38" verse="30">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>We bestowed Solomon on David who was an excellent devotee, for he turned to God in penitence.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>And We bestowed Sulaiman to Dawud; what an excellent bondman! He is indeed most inclined.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And We gave unto David Solomon; how excellent a servant he was! He was a penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And We vouchsafed Unto Da-ud Sulaiman. How excellent a bondman! j Verily he was oft-returning.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And to Dawud (David) We gave Sulaiman (Solomon). How excellent (a) slave! Verily, he was ever oft-returning in repentance (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And We granted David, Solomon, an excellent servant. He was penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>We bestowed upon David (an illustrious son), Solomon. How excellent a servant (of Ours he was)! Indeed he constantly turned to Us in devotion.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And to Dawud We gave Sulayman. How excellent a servant! Verily, he was ever turning in repentance (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And We bestowed on David, Solomon. How excellent a slave! Lo! he was ever turning in repentance (toward Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>And to David We gave Solomon—what an excellent servant he was! Indeed, he was a penitent [soul].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>We gave Solomon to David; and he was an excellent worshiper, he was penitent.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And to David We gave Solomon. An excellent servant, indeed he was one repeatedly turning back [to Allah].</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>We granted Solomon to David, a blessed servant of Ours and certainly the most repentant person.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And We gave to Dawood Sulaiman, most excellent the servant! Surely he was frequent in returning (to Allah).</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>We gave David Solomon. He was an excellent servant who always turned to God.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>To David We gave Solomon (for a son),- How excellent in Our service! Ever did he turn (to Us)!</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="27" verse="16">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>Solomon was heir to David, and he said: "O people, we have been taught the language of Tair, and have been given of everything. This is a clear favour indeed."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>And Solomon was David's heir, and he said, 'Men, we have been taught the speech of the birds, and we have been given of everything; surely this is indeed the manifest bounty.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>And Sulaiman inherited from Daud. And he said: O mankind! verily have been taught the diction of we birds, and we have been vcuchsafed of every thing; and verily this is grace manifest.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>And Sulaiman (Solomon) inherited (the knowledge of) Dawud (David). He said: "O mankind! We have been taught the language of birds, and on us have been bestowed all things. This, verily, is an evident grace (from Allah)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>And Solomon succeeded David. He said, “O people, we were taught the language of birds, and we were given from everything. This is indeed a real blessing.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>And Solomon succeeded David and said: "O people, we have been taught the speech of birds and we have been endowed with all kinds of things. Surely this is a conspicuous favour (from Allah)."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>And Sulayman inherited from Dawud. He said: "O mankind! We have been taught the language of birds, and we have been given from everything. This, verily, is an evident grace."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>And Solomon was David's heir. And he said: O mankind! Lo! we have been taught the language of birds, and have been given (abundance) of all things. This surely is evident favour.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>Solomon inherited from David, and he said, ‘O people! We have been taught the speech of the birds, and we have been given out of everything. Indeed this is a manifest advantage.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>Solomon inherited David. He said: 'Know, my people, we have been taught the speech of birds and given everything. Surely, this is a clear bounty'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>And Solomon inherited David. He said, "O people, we have been taught the language of birds, and we have been given from all things. Indeed, this is evident bounty."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>Solomon became the heir to David. He said, "People, we have been taught the language of the birds and have been granted a share of everything. This indeed is a manifest favor (from God)".</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>And Sulaiman was Dawood's heir, and he said: O men! we have been taught the language of birds, and we have been given all things; most surely this is manifest grace.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>Solomon succeeded David. He said, "Know, my people, that we have been taught the speech of birds and endowed with all good things. Surely this is God's manifest grace."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>And Solomon was David's heir. He said: "O ye people! We have been taught the speech of birds, and on us has been bestowed (a little) of all things: this is indeed Grace manifest (from Allah.)"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="13">
      <chapter_name/>
      <book_id>en.ahmedali</book_id>
      <title>quran</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Ahmed Ali">
          <text>They made for him whatever he wished, synagogues and statues, dishes large as water-troughs, and cauldrons firmly fixed (on ovens; and We said): "O House of David, act, and give thanks." But few among My creatures are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Ahmed Raza Khan">
          <text>They made for him whatever he wished – synagogues and statues, basins like ponds, and large pots built into the ground; “Be thankful, O the people of Dawud!” And few among My bondmen are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Arberry">
          <text>fashioning for him whatsoever he would -- places of worship, statues, porringers like water-troughs, and anchored cooking-pots. 'Labour, O House of David, in thankfulness; for few indeed are those that are thankful among My servants.'</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Daryabadi">
          <text>They worked for him whatsoever he pleased, of lofty halls and statues and basins like cisterns and cauldrons Standing firm. Work ye, house of Da'ud! with thanksgiving; few of My bondmen are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Hilali &amp; Khan">
          <text>They worked for him what he desired, (making) high rooms, images, basins as large as reservoirs, and (cooking) cauldrons fixed (in their places). "Work you, O family of Dawud (David), with thanks!" But few of My slaves are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Itani">
          <text>They made for him whatever he wished: sanctuaries, statues, bowls like pools, and heavy cauldrons. “O House of David, work with appreciation,” but a few of My servants are appreciative.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Maududi">
          <text>They made for him whatever he would desire: stately buildings, images, basins like water-troughs and huge, built-in-cauldrons: “Work, O house of David, in thankfulness (to your Lord). Few of My servants are truly thankful.”</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Mubarakpuri">
          <text>They worked for him as he desired on Maharib, Tamathil, large basins like Jawab and Qudur Rasiyat. "Work you, O family of Dawud, with thanks!" But few of My servants are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Pickthall">
          <text>They made for him what he willed: synagogues and statues, basins like wells and boilers built into the ground. Give thanks, O House of David! Few of My bondmen are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qarai">
          <text>They built for him as many temples as he wished, and figures, basins like cisterns, and caldrons fixed [in the ground]. ‘O House of David, act thankfully, and few of My servants are grateful.’</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Qaribullah &amp; Darwish">
          <text>They made for him whatever he wanted, arches, statues, bowls as basins, and fixed cauldrons. (We said:) 'Give thanks, House of David and work' Yet only a few of My worshipers are thankful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Saheeh International">
          <text>They made for him what he willed of elevated chambers, statues, bowls like reservoirs, and stationary kettles. [We said], "Work, O family of David, in gratitude." And few of My servants are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Sarwar">
          <text>They would make for him anything that he wanted like fortresses, statues, large basins like reservoirs, and huge immovable cooking pots. It was said, "Family of David, worship and act gratefully. Only few of my servants are grateful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Shakir">
          <text>They made for him what he pleased of fortresses and images, and bowls (large) as watering-troughs and cooking-pots that will not move from their place; give thanks, O family of Dawood! and very few of My servants are grateful.</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Wahiduddin Khan">
          <text>They made for him whatever he desired: palaces and statues, basins like reservoirs, and large cooking vessels fixed in their places. We said, "Give thanks, house of David, for few of My servants are truly grateful."</text>
        </translation>
        <translation author="Yusuf Ali">
          <text>They worked for him as he desired, (making) arches, images, basons as large as reservoirs, and (cooking) cauldrons fixed (in their places): "Work ye, sons of David, with thanks! but few of My servants are grateful!"</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="628">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, "The reciting of the Zabur (i.e. Psalms) was made easy for David. He used to order that his riding animals be saddled, and would finish reciting the Zabur before they were saddled. And he would never eat except from the earnings of his manual work."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="237">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, "The recitation of Psalms (David's Quran) was made light and easy for David that he used to have his ridding animal be saddled while he would finish the recitation before the servant had saddled it."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="286">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Al-Miqdam:
The Prophet said, "Nobody has ever eaten a better meal than that which one has earned by working with one's own hands. The Prophet of Allah, David used to eat from the earnings of his manual labor."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="34" verse="287">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah's Apostle said, "The Prophet David used not to eat except from the earnings of his manual labor."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="21" verse="231">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 2</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol02</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abdullah bin 'Amr bin Al-'As:
Allah's Apostle told me, "The most beloved prayer to Allah is that of David and the most beloved fasts to Allah are those of David. He used to sleep for half of the night and then pray for one third of the night and again sleep for its sixth part and used to fast on alternate days."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="631">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abdullah bin Amr:
Allah's Apostle said to me, "The most beloved fasting to Allah was the fasting of (the Prophet) David who used to fast on alternate days. And the most beloved prayer to Allah was the prayer of David who used to sleep for (the first) half of the night and pray for 1/3 of it and (again) sleep for a sixth of it."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="31" verse="195">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Amr bin Al-'As:
"Once Allah's Apostle came to me," and then he narrated the whole narration, i.e. your guest has a right on you, and your wife has a right on you. I then asked about the fasting of David. The Prophet replied, "Half of the year," (i.e. he used to fast on every alternate day).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="31" verse="196">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Amr bin Al-'As:
Allah's Apostle said to me, "O 'Abdullah! Have I not been informed that you fast during the day and offer prayers all the night." 'Abdullah replied, "Yes, O Allah's Apostle!" The Prophet said, "Don't do that; fast for few days and then give it up for few days, offer prayers and also sleep at night, as your body has a right on you, and your wife has a right on you, and your guest has a right on you. And it is sufficient for you to fast three days in a month, as the reward of a good deed is multiplied ten times, so it will be like fasting throughout the year." I insisted (on fasting) and so I was given a hard instruction. I said, "O Allah's Apostle! I have power." The Prophet said, "Fast like the fasting of the Prophet David and do not fast more than that." I said, "How was the fasting of the Prophet of Allah, David?" He said, "Half of the year," (i.e. he used to fast on every alternate day).
Afterwards when 'Abdullah became old, he used to say, "It would have been better for me if I had accepted the permission of the Prophet (which he gave me i.e. to fast only three days a month)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="31" verse="197">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Amr:
Allah's Apostle was informed that I had taken an oath to fast daily and to pray (every night) all the night throughout my life (so Allah's Apostle came to me and asked whether it was correct): I replied, "Let my parents be sacrificed for you! I said so." The Prophet said, "You can not do that. So, fast for few days and give it up for few days, r ray and sleep. Fast three days a month as the reward of good deeds is multiplied ten times and that will be equal to one year of fasting." I replied, "I can do better than that." The Prophet said to me, "Fast one day and give up fasting for a day and that is the fasting of Prophet David and that is the best fasting." I said, "I have the power to fast better (more) than that." The Prophet said, "There is no better fasting than that."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="31" verse="198">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Amr:
The news of my daily fasting and praying every night throughout the night reached the Prophet. So he sent for me or I met him, and he said, "I have been informed that you fast everyday and pray every night (all the night). Fast (for some days) and give up fasting (for some days); pray and sleep, for your eyes have a right on you, and your body and your family (i.e. wife) have a right on you." I replied, "I have more power than that (fasting)." The Prophet said, "Then fast like the fasts of (the Prophet) David". I said, "How?" He replied, "He used to fast on alternate days, and he used not to flee on meeting the enemy." I said, "From where can I get that chance?" ('Ata' said, "I do not know how the expression of fasting daily throughout the life occurred.") So, the Prophet said, twice, "Whoever fasts daily throughout his life is just as the one who does not fast at all."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="31" verse="200">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Amr bin Al-'As:
The Prophet said to me, "You fast daily all the year and pray every night all the night?" I replied in the affirmative. The Prophet said, "If you keep on doing this, your eyes will become weak and your body will get tired. He who fasts all the year is as he who did not fast at all. The fasting of three days (a month) will be equal to the tasting of the whole year." I replied, "I have the power for more than this." The Prophet said, "Then fast like the fasting of David who used to fast on alternate days and would never flee from the battle field, on meeting the enemy.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="31" verse="201">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 3</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol03</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Amr:
Allah's Apostle was informed about my fasts, and he came to me and I spread for him a leather cushion stuffed with palm fires, but he sat on the ground and the cushion remained between me and him, and then he said, "Isn't it sufficient for you to fast three days a month?" I replied, "O Allah's Apostle! (I can fast more)." He said, "Five?" I replied, "O Allah's Apostle! (I can fast more)." He said, "Seven?" I replied, "O Allah's Apostle! (I can fast more)." He said, "Nine (days per month)?" I replied, "O Allah's Apostle! (I can fast more)" He said, "Eleven (days per month)?" And then the Prophet said, "There is no fast superior to that of the Prophet David it was for half of the year. So, fast on alternate days."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="629">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abdullah bin Amr:
Allah's Apostle was informed that I have said: "By Allah, I will fast all the days and pray all the nights as long as I live." On that, Allah's Apostle asked me. "Are you the one who says: 'I will fast all the days and pray all the nights as long as I live?' " I said, "Yes, I have said it." He said, "You cannot do that. So fast (sometimes) and do not fast (sometimes). Pray and sleep. Fast for three days a month, for the reward of a good deed is multiplied by ten time, and so the fasting of three days a month equals the fasting of a year." I said, "O Allah's Apostle! I can do (fast) more than this." He said, "Fast on every third day. I said: I can do (fast) more than that, He said: "Fast on alternate days and this was the fasting of David which is the most moderate sort of fasting." I said, "O Allah's Apostle! I can do (fast) more than that." He said, "There is nothing better than that."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="630">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abdullah bin Amr bin Al-As:
The Prophet said to me, "I have been informed that you pray all the nights and observe fast all the days; is this true?" I replied, "Yes." He said, "If you do so, your eyes will become weak and you will get bored. So fast three days a month, for this will be the fasting of a whole year, or equal to the fasting of a whole year." I said, "I find myself able to fast more." He said, "Then fast like the fasting of (the Prophet) David who used to fast on alternate days and would not flee on facing the enemy."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="73" verse="155">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Amr:
Allah's Apostle entered upon me and said, "Have I not been informed that you offer prayer all the night and fast the whole day?" I said, "Yes." He said, "Do not do so; Offer prayer at night and also sleep; Fast for a few days and give up fasting for a few days because your body has a right on you, and your eye has a right on you, and your guest has a right on you, and your wife has a right on you. I hope that you will have a long life, and it is sufficient for you to fast for three days a month as the reward of a good deed, is multiplied ten times, that means, as if you fasted the whole year." I insisted (on fasting more) so I was given a hard instruction. I said, "I can do more than that (fasting)" The Prophet said, "Fast three days every week." But as I insisted (on fasting more) so I was burdened. I said, "I can fast more than that." The Prophet said, "Fast as Allah's prophet David used to fast." I said, "How was the fasting of the prophet David?" The Prophet said, "One half of a year (i.e. he used to fast on alternate days). '</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="74" verse="294">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 8</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol08</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abdullah bin 'Amr:
The news of my fasting was mentioned to the Prophet . So he entered upon me and I put for him a leather cushion stuffed with palm-fibres. The Prophet sat on the floor and the cushion was between me and him. He said to me, "Isn't it sufficient for you (that you fast) three days a month?" I said, "O Allah's Apostle! (I can fast more than this)." He said, "You may fast) five days a month." I said, "O Allah's Apostle! (I can fast more than this)." He said, "(You may fast) seven days." I said, "O Allah's Apostle!" He said, "Nine." I said, "O Allah's Apostle!" He said, "Eleven." I said, "O Allah's Apostle!" He said, "No fasting is superior to the fasting of (the Prophet David) which was one half of a year, and he used, to fast on alternate days. (See Hadith No. 300, Vol 3)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="61" verse="572">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin Amr bin Al-As:
My father got me married to a lady of a noble family, and often used to ask my wife about me, and she used to reply, "What a wonderful man he is! He never comes to my bed, nor has he approached me since he married me." When this state continued for a long period, my father told the story to the Prophet who said to my father, "Let me meet him." Then I met him and he asked me, "How do you fast?" I replied, "I fast daily," He asked, "How long does it take you to finish the recitation of the whole Quran?" I replied, "I finish it every night." On that he said, "Fast for three days every month and recite the Qur'an (and finish it) in one month." I said, "But I have power to do more than that." He said, "Then fast for three days per week." I said, "i have the power to do more than that." He said, "Therefore, fast the most superior type of fasting, (that is, the fasting of (prophet) David who used to fast every alternate day; and finish the recitation of the whole Qur'an In seven days." I wish I had accepted the permission of Allah's Apostle as I have become a weak old man. It is said that 'Abdullah used to recite one-seventh of the Qur'an during the day-time to some of his family members, for he used to check his memorization of what he would recite at night during the daytime so that it would be easier for him to read at night. And whenever he wanted to gain some strength, he used to give up fasting for some days and count those days to fast for a similar period, for he disliked to leave those things which he used to do during the lifetime of the Prophet.</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="632">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Mujahid:
I asked Ibn 'Abbas, "Should we perform a prostration on reciting Surat-Sad?" He recited (the Sura) including: 'And among his progeny, David, Solomon..(up to)...so follow their guidance (6.84-91) And then he said, "Your Prophet is amongst those people who have been ordered to follow them (i.e. the preceding apostles).</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="633">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The prostration in Sura-Sad is not amongst the compulsory prostrations, though I saw the Prophet prostrating on reciting The Statement of Allah:--and to David We gave Solomon (for a son). How excellent (a) slave he was ever oft-returning in repentance (to us) (38.30) And His Statement:-- He said: My Lord Forgive me and grant me a kingdom such as shall not belong to any other after me.' (38.35) And His Statement:-- 'And they followed what the Devils gave out (falsely), of magic in the life-time of Solomon.' (2.102)</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="156">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Mujahid:
That he asked Ibn 'Abbas, "Is there a prostration Surat-al-Sad?" (38.24) Ibn Abbas said, "Yes," and then recited: "We gave...So follow their guidance." (6.85,90) Then he said, "He (David ) is one them (i.e. those prophets)." Mujahid narrated: I asked Ibn 'Abbas (regarding the above Verse). He said, "Your Prophet (Muhammad) was one of those who were ordered to follow them."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="60" verse="331">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Al-Awwam:
I asked Mujahid regarding the prostration in Surat Sad. He said, "I asked Ibn 'Abbas, 'What evidence makes you prostrate?' He said, "Don't you recite:--'And among his progeny, David and Solomon..(6.84). Those are they whom Allah had guided. So follow their guidance.' (6.90) So David was the one of those prophets whom Prophet (Muhammad) was ordered to follow. David prostrated, so Allah's Apostle (Muhammad) performed this prostration too.'</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="52" verse="74">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
Allah's Apostle said, "Once Solomon, son of David said, '(By Allah) Tonight I will have sexual intercourse with one hundred (or ninety-nine) women each of whom will give birth to a knight who will fight in Allah's Cause.' On that a (i.e. if Allah wills) but he did not say, 'Allah willing.' Therefore only one of those women conceived and gave birth to a half-man. By Him in Whose Hands Muhammad's life is, if he had said, "Allah willing', (he would have begotten sons) all of whom would have been knights striving in Allah's Cause."
Narrated Anas: The Prophet was the best, the bravest and the most generous of all the people. Once when the people of Medina got frightened, the Prophet rode a horse and went ahead of them and said, "We found this horse very fast."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="55" verse="635">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 4</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol04</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
The Prophet said, "Solomon (the son of) David said, 'Tonight I will sleep with seventy ladies each of whom will conceive a child who will be a knight fighting for "Allah's Cause.' His companion said, 'If Allah will.' But Solomon did not say so; therefore none of those women got pregnant except one who gave birth to a half child." The Prophet further said, "If the Prophet Solomon had said it (i.e. 'If Allah will') he would have begotten children who would have fought in Allah's Cause." Shuaib and Ibn Abi Az-Zinad said, "Ninety (women) is more correct (than seventy)."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="62" verse="169">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 7</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol07</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Huraira:
(The Prophet) Solomon son of (the Prophet) David said, "Tonight I will go round (i.e. have sexual relations with) one hundred women (my wives) everyone of whom will deliver a male child who will fight in Allah's Cause." On that an Angel said to him, "Say: 'If Allah will.' " But Solomon did not say it and forgot to say it. Then he had sexual relations with them but none of them delivered any child except one who delivered a half person. The Prophet said, "If Solomon had said: 'If Allah will,' Allah would have fulfilled his (above) desire and that saying would have made him more hopeful."</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
    <verse chapter="61" verse="568">
      <chapter_name>Sahih Bukhari Vol 6</chapter_name>
      <book_id>en.bukhari.vol06</book_id>
      <title>bukhari</title>
      <score>0</score>
      <translations>
        <translation author="Dr. Muhammad Muhsin">
          <text>Narrated Abu Musa:
That the Prophet said to him' "O Abu Musa! You have been given one of the musical wind-instruments of the family of David .'</text>
        </translation>
      </translations>
    </verse>
  </verses>
</story>